<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T18:05:02Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3670926" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3670926</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-06-10</datestamp>
        <setSpec>plosone</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3670926</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3670926</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3670926</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23755162</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23755162</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D13-02088</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064931</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
                  <subject>Biology</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
                    <subj-group>
                      <subject>Cognitive Neuroscience</subject>
                      <subj-group>
                        <subject>Motor Reactions</subject>
                      </subj-group>
                    </subj-group>
                    <subj-group>
                      <subject>Neuroimaging</subject>
                      <subj-group>
                        <subject>fMRI</subject>
                      </subj-group>
                    </subj-group>
                    <subj-group>
                      <subject>Neurophysiology</subject>
                      <subj-group>
                        <subject>Motor Systems</subject>
                      </subj-group>
                    </subj-group>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
                  <subject>Medicine</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject>
                    <subj-group>
                      <subject>Neurological System</subject>
                      <subj-group>
                        <subject>Motor Systems</subject>
                      </subj-group>
                    </subj-group>
                  </subj-group>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Mental Health</subject>
                    <subj-group>
                      <subject>Psychology</subject>
                      <subj-group>
                        <subject>Behavior</subject>
                        <subj-group>
                          <subject>Human Performance</subject>
                        </subj-group>
                      </subj-group>
                    </subj-group>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Altered Regional Homogeneity with Short-term Simulated Microgravity and Its Relationship with Changed Performance in Mental Transformation</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Changed ReHo with 72 h Simulated Microgravity</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Liao</surname>
                    <given-names>Yang</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Miao</surname>
                    <given-names>Danmin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Huan</surname>
                    <given-names>Yi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yin</surname>
                    <given-names>Hong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Xi</surname>
                    <given-names>Yibin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>Xufeng</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Department of Psychology, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an Shaanxi, China</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Department of Radiology, Xijing Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi’an Shaaxi, China</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zuo</surname>
                    <given-names>Xi-Nian</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role>Editor</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="edit1">
                <addr-line>Institute of Psychology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, China</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>psych@fmmu.edu.cn</email> (DM); <email>lllfmmu@fmmu.edu.cn</email> (XL)</corresp>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                  <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                  <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XL DM YH. Performed the experiments: YL HY YX. Analyzed the data: YL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YL. Wrote the paper: YL.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>3</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2013</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>8</volume>
              <issue>6</issue>
              <elocation-id>e64931</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>9</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2013 Liao et al</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Liao et al</copyright-holder>
                <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>In order to further the insight into the explanation of changed performance in mental transformation under microgravity, we discuss the change of performance in mental transformation and its relationship with altered regional homogeneity (ReHo) in resting-state brain by using simulated weightlessness model. Twelve male subjects with age between 24 and 31 received resting-state fMRI scan and mental transformation test both in normal condition and immediately after 72 hours −6° head down tilt (HDT). A paired sample t-test was used to test the difference of behavior performance and brain activity between these two conditions. Compare with normal condition, subjects showed a changed performance in mental transformation with short term simulated microgravity and appeared to be falling. Meanwhile, decreased ReHo were found in right inferior frontal gyrus (IFG) and left inferior parietal lobule (IPL) after 72 hours −6° HDT, while increased ReHo were found in bilateral medial frontal gyrus (MFG) and left superior frontal gyrus (SFG) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, corrected). Particularly, there was a significant correlation between ReHo values in left IPL and velocity index of mental transformation. Our findings indicate that gravity change may disrupt the function of right IFG and left IPL in the resting-state, among of which functional change in left IPL may contribute to changed abilities of mental transformation. In addition, the enhanced activity of the bilateral MFG and decreased activity of right IFG found in the current study maybe reflect a complementation effect on inhibitory control process.</p>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation of China, Grant No.81071616 and No.81272174. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="7"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Human is the subject in space exploration activities, whether his activity is normal is the key point for all sorts of space exploration tasks, thus how the space environment influence individual activities had became a generally focus among space medical and psychological researchers. It is commonly believed that individual cognitive and behavioral activities would be impaired in space environment because there are negative factors like microgravity, radiation, noise and fatigue, etc <xref rid="pone.0064931-Eddy1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Morphew1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Palinkas1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Sandal1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Among those negative factors, microgravity factor is the main difference between space environment and the earth environment, so relevant researches was a hot topic in recent years and there were many significative findings <xref rid="pone.0064931-Grigoriev1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>.</p>
              <p>While exposed to microgravity environment, astronauts always face problems such as changed body positions and need to recognize objects and other astronauts’ gestures from various perspectives <xref rid="pone.0064931-Jenkin1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Due to the perspective change make the recognition process difficult, astronauts usually need to use the mental rotation strategy (mentally rotate an internal representation of the object) to help complicating it. If one couldn’t successfully completed the mental rotation process and following recognition process, he would fail to correctly recognize the object and sign around the cabin wall as well as crewmembers’ gestures, accordingly, it would bring obstacles to activity in the cabin and communication between crewmembers. So, the mental rotation ability plays a significant role in living in space and correlated researches are of great importance. Based on this kind of demand, several previous studies had done some excellent work on observing the variation of mental rotation ability under microgravity environment <xref rid="pone.0064931-Grabherr1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Leone1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Matsakis1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p>
              <p>When Matsakis et al. initially discussed this issue in 1993, they suggested that the rate of mental rotation was increased in weightlessness as compared to pre-flight values by observing two astronauts’ performance in a mental rotation task <xref rid="pone.0064931-Matsakis1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Afterwards, Leone et al. came to a different conclusion in 1995. They declared that no deterioration of the mental rotation abilities of subjects occurring in space as compared to their own abilities prior to and after the flight <xref rid="pone.0064931-Leone1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In the above two studies, the applied stimuli are both nonsensical three-dimension objects, the results have limited value in practical application. While the stimuli are meaningful body parts, which commonly defined by the term mental transformation instead, it will be more close to practical application. However, it is a pity that research on mental transformation ability under microgravity has been seldom reported. As we have known, Grabherr et al. once made effort to discuss this issue by the method of parabolic flight. In their study, they found that task that requires the mental transformation of one’s own body or body parts became more difficult during microgravity <xref rid="pone.0064931-Grabherr1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p>
              <p>Indeed, compared to previous mental rotation researches, mental transformation research has its merit in higher application value. Nevertheless, the amount of reported literature is quite a few and the recent study is tracking studies which just simply use behavioral test to discuss subjects’ mental transformation ability change. In this mean, the result is not very credible and just a phenomenological discuss in a relatively primitive stage. Meanwhile, parabolic flight model is usually applied to simulate the transient change induced by microgravity <xref rid="pone.0064931-Villard1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. During the parabolic flight, there exists frequent gravity change, which may bring in mix factors such as acute stress. What’s more, due to the experiment environment is particular and advanced brain science facilities is nearly unable to fit in this environment <xref rid="pone.0064931-Newberg1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, the internal neural mechanism of mental transformation ability change has not yet been clarified.</p>
              <p>Fortunately, as a generally accepted technology in studies of microgravity among space science researchers <xref rid="pone.0064931-Baisch1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, −6° head down tilt (HDT) bed rest could stimulate the microgravity effect of redistribution of individual body fluid toward head in a relative longer duration than parabolic flight, thus it makes it is possible to explore the effect of microgravity on individual cognitive and behavioral activities on earth. In addition, with the development of the experimental techniques of cognitive neuroscience, the application of functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) technology in psychological research makes the exploration of the neural mechanism of the cognitive and behavioral processes possible <xref rid="pone.0064931-Ogawa1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Ogawa2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Especially, the resting-state fMRI technology could overcome the limitations of inconsistent results caused by different experimental designs and support more stable and effective evidence in the exploration of individual brain activities <xref rid="pone.0064931-Biswal1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Moreover, previous studies have propose that resting-state fMRI data can be used as an alternative to task fMRI data, which is of great importance when task fMRI data are not easily or accurately acquired <xref rid="pone.0064931-Zou1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Thus, it had been accepted as an effective technology in the research of internal neural mechanism of individual cognitive and behavioral activities. For this technology, regional homogeneity (ReHo) is a widely used new method in resting-state fMRI research <xref rid="pone.0064931-Zang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In ReHo analysis, Kendall's coefficient concordance (with value from 0 to 1) is used to calculate the coherence of time series of a given voxel with those of its nearest neighbors (26 voxels), thus we could learn the synchronization of the brain activities in a quantitative way. Our previous ALFF study has indicated that a gravity change-induced redistribution of body fluid may disrupt the baseline of local brain activity. But it should be noted that brain is a complex organ, it more emphasis on the interaction between neurons. Thus to clarify the brain activity change with short term microgravity from the perspective of functional connectivity (Such as ReHo, functional connectivity, brain network) is very meaningful. In addition, we could verify the result of the previous study in a different method by carry out the current study.</p>
              <p>In the current study, to address the question how and why astronauts’ mental transformation ability change in microgravity, we combined the resting-state fMRI technology and −6° head down tilt bed rest technology together to find the difference of ReHo as well as behavior reaction change in a mental transformation test before and after 72 hours of −6° HDT bed rest. The results may support some evidences and references to further the insight into the explanation of changed performance in mental transformation under microgravity and rich the knowledge about protection of astronauts’ brain function.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <sec id="s2a">
                <title>2.1. Subjects</title>
                <p>Sixteen health subjects were recruited in the present study; four subjects were excluded from the analysis because of excessive head motion (more than 2 mm or 2 degree in any axis). Totally, data of 12 subjects met the above mentioned criteria. Due to most of the astronauts are males, the subjects we selected are normal adult males. The valid subjects’ mean age is 26.4, range from 24 to 31. They were all right-handed as measured by Handedness Questionnaire <xref rid="pone.0064931-Annett1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Subjects reported no history of neurological injury, genetic mental disorders and substance abuse. With high resolution T1- and T2-weighted MRI examination, no subjects were found to have significant pathological change in brain. The study was approved by the Ethical Committee of the Fourth Military Medical University and all participants provided their written informed consent before the experiment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2b">
                <title>2.2. Design</title>
                <p>A pair comparison of subjects’ resting-state brain activities between normal condition and simulated microgravity condition were applied in the present study. The collected data of normal condition was subjects’ resting-state brain activities under normal seating posture condition. The collected data after simulated weightlessness condition was subjects’ resting-state brain activities after 72 hours −6° HDT bed rest. During the HDT bed rest, adequate water and foods were supplied to subjects and subjects’ head were forbidden to get out of bed in order to keep the redistribution of individual body fluid toward head. In order to avoid the fMRI scanning order of two conditions becoming an interference factor, the order of the scanning of the two conditions were balanced. Half of the subjects’ data of simulated microgravity condition were collected ten days after the data collection of normal condition while the others data collection order reversed. Moreover, in order to avoid the interference of biological rhythms, data collections were all carried out in the same time period in a day.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2c">
                <title>2.3. Behavioral Experiment</title>
                <sec id="s2c1">
                  <title>2.3.1. Experimental paradigm</title>
                  <p>Subjects were asked to complete the mental transformation test on a computer. The stimulus of hand pictures are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064931-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. At the beginning of each trial, a cross was presented in the center of the screen for a random duration (the duration ranging from 200 ms to 500 ms) by a commercial visual software (Stim2.0; Neuroscan Inc., USA). Initially the cross disappeared; the stimulus began to present until the subject complete the judgment by pressing the mouse button. Subjects’ task was to mental transformation the stimulus into upright position and judge whether the stimulus is right hand or not. There were six kind of orientation (0°, 60°120°, 180°, 240°, 300°) for both right and left hand pictures. Except for 0° and 180° stimulus repeated 60 times during the whole test, the other types stimulus all repeated 30 times. The sequences of trials were random by the computer.</p>
                  <fig id="pone-0064931-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064931.g001</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Stimulus used in the mental transformation test.</title>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.g001"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2c2">
                  <title>2.3.2. Analysis of behavioral data</title>
                  <p>Those trials which were rightly responded were accepted for the further analysis. The reaction time (RT) between stimulus onset and response was averaged across clockwise and counterclockwise orientation angles. For previous studies have demonstrated that there was no statistical differences between counter- and clockwise stimulus orientations in the same angle <xref rid="pone.0064931-Dalecki1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, we merged them into four rotation conditions into the following linear regression analysis. The four conditions are: (i) stimuli not rotated (0°), (ii) 60° rotation (included stimuli rotated 60°/300°), (iii) 120° rotation (included stimuli rotated 120°/240°) and (iv) 180° rotation (included stimuli rotated 180°). Linear regression analysis on raw RTs as a function of the angle of rotation (angle of rotation ranging from 0° to 180°) was carried out. These linear regressions gave us the slope of the regression line. While rotated the same orientations, the higher slope means the subject needs more time to complicate the mental transformation process. Then the inverse of the slope corresponds to the velocity of the mental transformation, that is, if a subject has a higher slope in the regression analysis, he ought to have a slower velocity of the mental transformation.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2c3">
                  <title>2.3.3. Statistic</title>
                  <p>To explore the velocity of the mental transformation differences between the normal condition and simulated microgravity condition, a pair-sample t-test was performed.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2d">
                <title>2.4. Image Acquisition and Analysis</title>
                <sec id="s2d1">
                  <title>2.4.1</title>
                  <p>Data acquisitions. Additionally, all subjects’ image data were collected by an experienced radiologist with a Siemens 3.0T nuclear magnetic resonance equipment in the radiology department of the Xijing Hospital of Fourth Military Medical University. Subjects were told to lay on the scanning platform flatly and place the head to the assigned location cozily. Sponge earplugs were used to plug the ear hole in order to minimize the interference of noises and some foam padding were used to restrict head motion. A standard 16-channels head coil was used to collect the data. The subjects were told to try to keep the head motionless, to keep calm with eyes closed and to not think of anything in particular. (In addition, the data of functional images after 72 hours stimulated weightlessness was collected in head down tilt position. We placed a special foam pad on the platform of the scanner, then the subjects could keep head tilt down position during data collection.) The scanning sequence and parameters were using the following settings: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.e003.jpg"/></inline-formula> anatomical images for location were T1-weighted images which used spin echo method (SE). TR = 500 ms, TE = 15 ms, flip angle (FA) = 90°, field of view (FOV) = 220 mm×220 mm, matrix = 256×144, slice thickness = 4 mm with no gap. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.e004.jpg"/></inline-formula> the high definition three dimensional T1-weighted images of the whole brain were used MPRAG sequence. TR = 2530 ms, TE = 3.39 ms, inversion time = 1100 ms, FA = 7°, FOV = 256 mm×256 mm, matrix = 256×192, slice thickness = 1.33 mm with no gap, 128 slices. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.e005.jpg"/></inline-formula> an echo planner imaging sequence was used to acquire functional images, TR = 2000 ms, TE = 30 ms, FA = 90°, FOV = 200 mm×200 mm, matrix = 64×64, slice thickness = 3 mm, gap = 0.6 mm, 33 slices, this part of scan contained 240 time points and lasted 8 minutes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2d2">
                  <title>2.4.2. Data preprocessing</title>
                  <p>Data Processing Assistant for Resting-State fMRI (DPARSF, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.restfmri.net/forum/DPARSF">http://www.restfmri.net/forum/DPARSF</ext-link>) V2.0 was used in data preprocessing <xref rid="pone.0064931-Yan1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The preprocessing steps were as follows: First, the data format of functional images was transform from DICOM to NFTI. Second, because of the subjects need some time to adjust, the first ten time points were discarded and 230 time points were left. Third, the left functional images were slice-time corrected, and aligned to the first image of each session for motion correction. Four subjects were excluded from the analysis because of excessive head motion (more than 2 mm or 2 degree in any axis). Fourth, the data was then spatially normalized with the Montreal Neurological Institute (MNI) template (resampling voxel size = 3×3×3 mm<sup>3</sup>)in the Resting-State fMRI Data Analysis Toolkit (REST, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.restfmri.net">www.restfmri.net</ext-link>) v1.0 <xref rid="pone.0064931-Song1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Fifth, Linear trend was removed and then the fMRI data were temporally band-pass filtered (0.01 ≤ f ≤ 0.08 Hz) to reduce the low-frequency drift and physiological high-frequency respiratory and cardiac noise. Then head motion, white matter and CSF signals were regressing out before ReHo computation as previous studies suggested <xref rid="pone.0064931-Power1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-VanDijk1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Zuo1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2d3">
                  <title>2.4.3. ReHo analysis</title>
                  <p>Kendall’s coefficient of concordance (KCC) was used to measure regional homogeneity or similarity of the ranked time series of a given voxel with its nearest 26 neighbor voxels in a voxel-wise way <xref rid="pone.0064931-Liang1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Kendall1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>:<disp-formula id="pone.0064931.e001"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.e001.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>where <italic>W</italic> is the KCC among given voxels, ranging from 0 to 1; <italic>R<sub>i</sub></italic> is the sum rank of the <italic>i</italic>th time point; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.e002.jpg"/></inline-formula> = ((n+1)<italic>K</italic>)/2 is the mean of the <italic>R<sub>i</sub></italic>; <italic>K</italic> is the number of time series within a measured cluster (27, one given voxel plus the number of its neighbors); and <italic>n</italic> is the number of ranks. DPARSF was used to calculate the KCC value of the time series of a given voxel with those of its nearest neighbors (26 voxels) in a voxel-wise analysis. The normalized ReHo map was got by divide the mean KCC value of all voxels from the KCC value of each voxel of the whole brain. Then the ReHo maps were spatially smoothed (4 mm FWHM Gaussian kernel).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2d4">
                  <title>2.4.4. Statistics</title>
                  <p>To explore the ReHo differences between the normal condition and simulated microgravity condition, a pair-sample t-test was performed on the normalized ReHo maps. The resultant statistical map was set at a combined threshold of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.005 and a minimum cluster size of 832 mm<sup>3</sup> (13 voxels), corresponding to a corrected threshold of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, as determined by AlphaSim. For presentation purposes, the statistical maps were transformed to Talairach coordinates <xref rid="pone.0064931-Talairach1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> and superimposed on the higher-resolution anatomical template available in REST. The difference areas found in paired-sample t-test was saved as masks separately in MRIcron (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nitrc.org/projects/mricron">http://www.nitrc.org/projects/mricron</ext-link>). Then they were used to exacting out the mean ReHo values of these areas in Matlab7.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mathworks.cn/products/matlab/">http://www.mathworks.cn/products/matlab/</ext-link>). Finally, these mean ReHo values was recorded into SPSS14.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/cn/analytics/spss/products/statistics/">http://www-01.ibm.com/software/cn/analytics/spss/products/statistics/</ext-link>) to calculate their correlations with velocity index of mental transformation.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s3a">
                <title>3.1. Behavioral Result in Mental Transformation Test</title>
                <p>The mean accuracy in behavioral test under normal condition is 0.976 (SEM = 0.006), the mean accuracy in behavioral test after HDT is 0.973 (SEM = 0.004). There is no significant difference in mean accuracy in behavioral test between these two conditions (<italic>P</italic> = 0.736). The reaction times in mental transformation test are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064931-g002">Fig. 2</xref>. Regression analysis suggest that there are significant linear trend between reaction time and stimulus orientation across all subjects (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). Thus the slopes of the regression lines are valid. Compared to normal condition, subjects showed increased slop of mental transformation with short term simulated microgravity which may indicate declined mental transformation ability in microgravity. But from a statistical point of view, this difference was not significant at 0.05 level.</p>
                <fig id="pone-0064931-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064931.g002</object-id>
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Behavioral results of mental transform test.</title>
                    <p>Left: Lineal regression of reaction time and stimulus orientation in mental transform test (Subject 1 in normal condition as the example). Right: Velocity index of mental transformation in normal condition and simulated microgravity condition.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.g002"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3b">
                <title>3.2. ReHo Results</title>
                <p>ReHo results between the normal condition and simulated microgravity condition are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064931-g003">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064931-t001">Tab. 1</xref>. Compared to normal condition, decreased ReHo was found in right inferior frontal gyrus (IFG) and left inferior parietal lobule (IPL) in simulated microgravity condition. In addition, increased ReHo were found in bilateral medial frontal gyrus (MFG) and left superior frontal gyrus (SFG) in simulated microgravity condition.</p>
                <fig id="pone-0064931-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064931.g003</object-id>
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Brain areas with significant ReHo differences between simulated microgravity condition and normal condition (A combined threshold of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.005 and a minimum cluster size of 832 mm<sup>3</sup> (13 voxels), corresponding to a corrected threshold of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, as determined by AlphaSim).</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.g003"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="pone-0064931-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064931.t001</object-id>
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Brain areas with significant ReHo differences between stimulated microgravity condition and normal condition.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic id="pone-0064931-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0064931.t001"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain regions</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxels size</td>
                          <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak-<italic>t</italic>
</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">area</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mm<sup>3</sup>)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value</td>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Stimulated microgravity condition&lt; Normal condition</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right IFG</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1216</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.41</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left IPL</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">896</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−34</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−53</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.61</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Stimulated microgravity condition &gt;Normal condition</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MFG</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4480</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.21</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left SFG</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">832</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="nt101">
                      <p>(A combined threshold of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.005 and a minimum cluster size of 832 mm<sup>3</sup> (13 voxels), corresponding to a corrected threshold of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, as determined by AlphaSim).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3c">
                <title>3.3. The Correlations between ReHo Values and Velocity Index of Mental Transformation</title>
                <p>In clusters for which significant group differences had been detected, we also tested for possible correlations between ReHo and velocity index of mental transformation. Finally, there was only a significant correlation between mean ReHo values in left inferior parietal lobule and velocity index of mental transformation in simulated microgravity condition(r = − 0.59, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064931-g004">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="pone-0064931-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064931.g004</object-id>
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Pearson correlation analyses examining the relation between mean ReHo values in left parietal lobule and velocity index of mental transformation.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0064931.g004"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The major finding of present study is the decreased ReHo in left parietal lobule with short term simulated microgravity and its significant correlation with velocity index of mental transformation. As a good quantitative indicator for reflecting the localized coherence of brain activity, ReHo could indicate the change of neural activities in certain brain areas <xref rid="pone.0064931-Zang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-You1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Qiu1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Ni1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Liu2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Thus, the ReHo changes found in the current study may reflect corresponding function changes, to some extent; it could help to clarify the internal neural mechanisms of mental transformation ability change under microgravity. Additionally, the declined trend of mental transformation ability and changed ReHo values in right inferior frontal gyrus, bilateral medial frontal gyrus and left superior frontal gyrus found with short term simulated microgravity are worthy discussed.</p>
              <p>At behavioral level, a declined trend of mental transformation ability was found with short term simulated microgravity. This was accordance with the previous study carried out by Grabherr et al. with parabolic flight model <xref rid="pone.0064931-Grabherr1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. They owed this result to the disturbed vestibular function induced by the missing of gravity information input. In contrast, the model to simulate microgravity used in the present study is different; the gravity information input still exists in HDT bed rest <xref rid="pone.0064931-Baisch1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. This difference may induce weaker damage to subjects in the present study than in Grabherr’s and could partly explain the insignificant between group differences in behavioral data found in the present study. Though it is, the result could support the idea of declined mental transformation ability with microgravity presented by Grabherr et al. in some extent. However, it is worth noting that with the gravity information input still existed in present study, there may be other contributors that contribute to the mental transformation ability change. The behavioral data in the present study is not enough to clarify this issue; we should look for some evidence from the image data.</p>
              <p>As the result found in the present study, mean ReHo vaule in left inferior parietal lobule has a significant correlation with the velocity index of mental transformation. Accordingly, the declined function of left inferior parietal lobule revealed by the decreased ReHo in the left inferior parietal lobule with short term microgravity may play a significant role in mental transformation ability change. Amount of previous studies have provided credible evidence to this inference. Initially, Kosslyn et al. found the bilateral inferior parietal lobule activation in the mental rotation of hand pictures by positron emission tomography <xref rid="pone.0064931-Kosslyn1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Later, an fMRI study carried out by Vingerhoets et al. similarly found the bilateral parietal areas activated during the mental transformation task <xref rid="pone.0064931-Vingerhoets1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Similar finding was reported again by Overney in 2005, they suggested that left parietal regions were strongly activated during mental transformation <xref rid="pone.0064931-Overney1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Thus, left inferior parietal lobule is with no doubt play an important role in the processing of mental representation (especially the mental representation of body parts, such as hand). The decreased ReHo found in this area with short term microgravity in the present study is ought to reflect a dysfunction there, which may in turn disturb the mental transformation process. Accordingly, the changed mental transformation ability found in the present study could be explained reasonably. Nevertheless, based on the data of the current study, we couldn’t conclude the reason of the dysfunction in left inferior parietal lobule yet. A possible reason is that the redistribution of individual body fluid toward head induced by simulated microgravity may affect the neuron metabolism in the left inferior parietal lobule, but this assumption lack direct evidence to support. An alternative assumption is that the dysfunction of left inferior parietal lobule is caused by the declined vestibular function. There are some indirect evidences to verify it in the previous studies. Several studies have reported the vestibular dysfunction in HDT bed rest <xref rid="pone.0064931-Grabherr1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Moreover, Overney et al. ever suggested that the parietal areas need to receive the input information input vestibular during the mental transformation process <xref rid="pone.0064931-Overney1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. While vestibular function declined during simulated microgravity, the vestibular-cortical interactions would be disturbed in sequent, which may accordingly disturb the neural activity in left inferior parietal lobule (which plays an important role in mental transformation process). For now, the latter assumption seems to be more credible, but it is still need to be clarified in the future. Even though, the dysfunction in left inferior lobule with short term simulated microgravity and its relationship with changed mental transformation ability found in the present study is valuable, it will further the insight of brain activity change in microgravity and promote the development of corresponding countermeasures.</p>
              <p>Moreover, it is worth paid attention to that declined function in right inferior frontal gyrus and enhanced function in bilateral medial frontal gyrus were also found in the present study. Previous studies <xref rid="pone.0064931-Benvenuti1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Pattyn1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Rau1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Vaitl1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> have demonstrated that individual frontal cortical functioning was inhibited under microgravity and in turn impair several psychological processes such as inhibitory control etc. But enhanced frontal areas activity in microgravity had been seldom reported. As far as we know, amount of previous findings had suggested that right inferior frontal gyrus and medial frontal gyrus play critical roles in inhibitory control process <xref rid="pone.0064931-Aron1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Aron2" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Dehaene1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Dosenbach1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Dosenbach2" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Horn1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Ridderinkhof1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Rubia1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Seeley1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Therefore, the enhanced activity of the bilateral medial frontal gyrus found in the current study maybe reflect a compensatory mechanism to the declined inhibitory control process. But due to there is no behavioral data for reference, whether this compensatory mechanism is stronger enough to cancel out the negative effect caused by the abnormal activity of the right inferior frontal gyrus is not clear yet. The relation of these two areas and their impact on inhibitory control is still a problem that worthy be addressed.</p>
              <p>In addition, hyperfunction in left superior frontal gyrus after short term simulated microgravity was found in the present study. In previous studies, superior frontal gyrus has been related to multiple cognitive processes, such as task-switching, expression identification and complex motor control <xref rid="pone.0064931-Martino1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-McLellan1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Slagter1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Crone1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Cutini1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>l. Due to the lack of corresponding behavioral data, we could hardly clarify the exact role of hyperfunction in left superior frontal gyrus found in the present study; it needs to be addressed in the future studies.</p>
              <p>The findings of the present finding are encouraging, but there still exist some limitation that need to be addressed. Firstly, because of technical limitations, the sampling rate (TR = 2 s) used in the data acquisition is low; therefore, simultaneously recording of cardiac rates is impossible <xref rid="pone.0064931-Liao1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064931-Zang2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Although we could not eliminate the cardiac rate interference from our data, our findings may seem to be reliable after multiple corrections in some extent. Secondly, those findings of present study are gained from the simulated experiment on earth and there are some limitations when they are extended to microgravity environment. These findings are still needed to be tested in real microgravity environment in the near future.</p>
              <sec id="s4a">
                <title>Conclusion</title>
                <p>In conclusion, gravity change may disrupt the function of right inferior frontal gyrus and left inferior parietal lobule in the resting-state, among of which functional change in left inferior parietal lobule may contribute to changed abilities of mental transformation. In addition, the enhanced activity of the bilateral medial frontal gyrus and decreased activity of right inferior frontal gyrus found in the current study maybe reflect a complementation effect on inhibitory control process. However, these results are gained from the simulated experiment on earth and there are some limitations when they are extended to microgravity environment. These findings are still needed to be tested in real microgravity environment in the near future.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>We sincerely thank volunteers for their participation, and all the medical staff involved in data collecting.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Eddy1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schiflett</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shebab</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cognitive performance aboard the life and microgravity spacelab</article-title>. <source>Acta Astronautica</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11541924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Morphew1">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morphew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Psychological and human factors in long duration spaceflight</article-title>. <source>MJM</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Palinkas1">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palinkas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Psychosocial issues in long-term space flight: Overview</article-title>. <source>Gravitational and Space Biology Bulletin</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11865866</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Sandal1">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sandal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Psychosocial issues in space: Future chalenges</article-title>. <source>Gravitational and Space Biology Bulletin</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11865868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Grigoriev1">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grigoriev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egorov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>General Mechanisms of the effect of weightlessness on the human body</article-title>. <source>Advance in Space Biology and Medicine</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Jenkin1">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jenkin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dyde</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenkin</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacher</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Perceptual upright: The relative effectiveness of dynamic and static images under different gravity states</article-title>. <source>Seeing and Perceiving</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21406155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Grabherr1">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karmali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Indermaur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mental own-body and body-part transformations in microgravity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vestibular Research</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18626138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Leone1">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipshits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gurfinkel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berthoz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Influence of graviceptives cues at different level of visual information processing: The effect of prolonged weightlessness</article-title>. <source>Acta Astronautica</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>751</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11541011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Matsakis1">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipshits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gurfinkel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berthoz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Effects of prolonged weightlessness on mental rotation of three-dimensional objects</article-title>. <source>Experimental brain research</source>
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8335070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Villard1">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia-Moreno</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Geometric visual illusions in microgravity during parabolic flight</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1395</fpage>–<lpage>1398</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16056146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Newberg1">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Newberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Changes in the central nervous system during long-duration space flight: implications for neuro-imaging</article-title>. <source>Advances in Space Research</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11541396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Baisch1">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baisch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karemaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arbeille</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaffney</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Head-down tilt bedrest. HDT'88–an international collaborative effort in integrated systems physiology</article-title>. <source>Acta physiologica scandinavica Supplementum</source>
<volume>604</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Ogawa1">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tank</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Brain magnetic resonance imaging with contrast dependent on blood oxygenation</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>9868</fpage>–<lpage>9872</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Ogawa2">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Oxygenation-sensitive contrast in magnetic resonance image of rodent brain at high magnetic fields</article-title>. <source>Magnetic resonance in medicine</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2161986</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Biswal1">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Biswal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zerrin Yetkin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haughton</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Functional connectivity in the motor cortex of resting human brain using echo-planar mri</article-title>. <source>Magnetic resonance in medicine</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Zou1">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zou Q, Ross TJ, Gu H, Geng X, Zuo XN, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) Intrinsic resting-state activity predicts working memory brain activation and behavioral performance. Human Brain Mapping: doi: 10.1002/hbm.22136.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Zang1">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regional homogeneity approach to fMRI data analysis</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Annett1">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Annett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>A classification of hand preference by association analysis</article-title>. <source>British journal of psychology</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5457503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Dalecki1">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dalecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mental rotation of letters, body parts and complex scenes: Separate or common mechanisms?</article-title>
<source>Human movement science</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1151</fpage>–<lpage>1160</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22244585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Yan1">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>DPARSF: a MATLAB toolbox for “pipeline” data analysis of resting-state fMRI</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in systems neuroscience</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20577591</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Song1">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>REST: a toolkit for resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging data processing</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e25031</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21949842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Power1">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlaggar</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Spurious but systematic correlations in functional connectivity MRI networks arise from subject motion</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>2142</fpage>–<lpage>2154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019881</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-VanDijk1">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sabuncu</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buckner</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The influence of head motion on intrinsic functional connectivity MRI</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Zuo1">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Toward reliable characterization of functional homogeneity in the human brain: preprocessing, scan duration, imaging resolution and computational space</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23085497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Liang1">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Regional homogeneity changes in patients with neuromyelitis optica revealed by resting-state functional MRI</article-title>. <source>Clinical Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20621555</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Kendall1">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kendall MG, Gibbons JD (1990) Rank correlation methods. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Talairach1">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Talairach J, Tournoux P (1988) Co-planar stereotaxic atlas of the human brain: 3-dimensional proportional system: an approach to cerebral imaging: Thieme.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-You1">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Altered regional homogeneity in motor cortices in patients with multiple system atrophy</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience letters</source>
<volume>502</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21798310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Qiu1">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Regional homogeneity changes in social anxiety disorder: a resting-state fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Research: Neuroimaging</source>
<volume>194</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21831605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Wang1">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Increased local synchronization of resting-state fMRI signal after episodic memory encoding reflects off-line memory consolidation</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Lin1">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Altered spontaneous activity in anisometropic amblyopia subjects: revealed by resting-state FMRI</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e43373</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22937041</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Ni1">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Altered regional homogeneity in the development of minimal hepatic encephalopathy: a resting-state functional MRI study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e42016</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22848692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Liu1">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiviniemi</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Using coherence to measure regional homogeneity of resting-state fMRI signal</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in systems neuroscience</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20589093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Liu2">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tie</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regional homogeneity within the default mode network in bipolar depression: a resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e48181</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23133615</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Kosslyn1">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kosslyn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Digirolamo</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Mental rotation of objects versus hands: Neural mechanisms revealed by positron emission tomography</article-title>. <source>Psychophysiology</source>
<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9529941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Vingerhoets1">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vingerhoets</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Lange</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vandemaele</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deblaere</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Achten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Motor imagery in mental rotation: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1623</fpage>–<lpage>1633</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12414300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Overney1">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Overney</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pegna</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cerebral processes in mental transformations of body parts: recognition prior to rotation</article-title>. <source>Cognitive brain research</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>734</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Benvenuti1">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benvenuti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bianchin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angrilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effects of simulated microgravity on brain plasticity: A startle reflex habituation study</article-title>. <source>Physiology &amp; behavior</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21627974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Pattyn1">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pattyn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Migeotte</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soetens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cluydts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Crew performance monitoring: Putting some feeling into it</article-title>. <source>Acta Astronautica</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Rau1">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pauli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elbert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Birbaumer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Baroreceptor stimulation alters cortical activity</article-title>. <source>Psychophysiology</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8497561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Vaitl1">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vaitl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gruppe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Possel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Simulated micro-gravity and cortical inhibition: a study of the hemodynamic-brain interaction</article-title>. <source>Biological psychology</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8770372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Aron1">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aron</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bullmore</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sahakian</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Stop-signal inhibition disrupted by damage to right inferior frontal gyrus in humans</article-title>. <source>Nature neuroscience</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12536210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Aron2">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aron</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poldrack</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Inhibition and the right inferior frontal cortex</article-title>. <source>Trends in cognitive sciences</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15050513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Dehaene1">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dehaene</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Artiges</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naccache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Viard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Conscious and subliminal conflicts in normal subjects and patients with schizophrenia: the role of the anterior cingulate</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>13722</fpage>–<lpage>13727</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Dosenbach1">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dosenbach</surname><given-names>NUF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fair</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miezin</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Distinct brain networks for adaptive and stable task control in humans</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>11073</fpage>–<lpage>11078</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576922</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Dosenbach2">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dosenbach</surname><given-names>NUF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miezin</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A core system for the implementation of task sets</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Horn1">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deakin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Response inhibition and impulsivity: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1959</fpage>–<lpage>1966</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14572528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Ridderinkhof1">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ridderinkhof</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ullsperger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crone</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nieuwenhuis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The role of the medial frontal cortex in cognitive control</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>306</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15486290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Rubia1">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rubia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brammer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Right inferior prefrontal cortex mediates response inhibition while mesial prefrontal cortex is responsible for error detection</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527595</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Seeley1">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schatzberg</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Dissociable intrinsic connectivity networks for salience processing and executive control</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2349</fpage>–<lpage>2356</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Martino1">
                <label>51</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabarrós</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juncadella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Acebes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Intrasurgical mapping of complex motor function in the superior frontal gyrus</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21277357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-McLellan1">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilcke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Sensitivity to posed and genuine displays of happiness and sadness: A fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience letters</source>
<volume>531</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23123788</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Slagter1">
                <label>53</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slagter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giesbrecht</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mangun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Brain regions activated by endogenous preparatory set shifting as revealed by fMRI</article-title>. <source>Cognitive, Affective, &amp; Behavioral Neuroscience</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Crone1">
                <label>54</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crone</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendelken</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donohue</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bunge</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Neural evidence for dissociable components of task-switching</article-title>. <source>Cerebral Cortex</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Cutini1">
                <label>55</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cutini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scatturin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisiacchi</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gamberini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Selective activation of the superior frontal gyrus in task-switching: an event-related fNIRS study</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>–<lpage>955</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18586525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Liao1">
                <label>56</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Altered baseline brain activity with 72 h of simulated microgravity- Initial evidence from resting-state fMRI</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e52558</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23285086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0064931-Zang2">
                <label>57</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Altered baseline brain activity in children with ADHD revealed by resting-state functional MRI</article-title>. <source>Brain &amp; development</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16919409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
