<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T18:03:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4470626" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4470626</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-06-29</datestamp>
        <setSpec>plosone</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4470626</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4470626</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4470626</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26083473</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26083473</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-09526</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Human Performance in a Realistic Instrument-Control Task during Short-Term Microgravity</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Instrument Control in Microgravity</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Steinberg</surname>
                    <given-names>Fabian</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kalicinski</surname>
                    <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dalecki</surname>
                    <given-names>Marc</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bock</surname>
                    <given-names>Otmar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff001">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Institute of Physiology and Anatomy, German Sport University, Cologne, Germany</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff002">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Institute of Sport Science, Johannes Gutenberg University, Mainz, Germany</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff003">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>School of Kinesiology and Health Science, Centre for Vision Research, York University, Toronto, Canada</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Reddy</surname>
                    <given-names>Sakamuri V.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role>Academic Editor</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="edit1">
                <addr-line>Charles P. Darby Children's Research Institute, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
                  <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
                  <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FS OB. Performed the experiments: FS MD. Analyzed the data: MK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FS MD MK OB. Wrote the paper: FS MK MD OB.</p>
                </fn>
                <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>Fabian.steinberg@uni-mainz.de</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <issue>6</issue>
              <elocation-id>e0128992</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2015 Steinberg et al</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Steinberg et al</copyright-holder>
                <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0128992.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <p>Previous studies have documented the detrimental effects of microgravity on human sensorimotor skills. While that work dealt with simple, laboratory-type skills, we now evaluate the effects of microgravity on a complex, realistic instrument-control skill. Twelve participants controlled a simulated power plant during the short-term microgravity intervals of parabolic flight as well as during level flight. To this end they watched multiple displays, made strategic decisions and used multiple actuators to maximize their virtual earnings from the power plant. We quantified <italic>control efficiency</italic> as the participants’ net earnings (revenue minus expenses), <italic>motor performance</italic> as hand kinematics and dynamics, and <italic>stress</italic> as cortisol level, self-assessed mood and self-assessed workload. We found that compared to normal gravity, control efficiency substantially decreased in microgravity, hand velocity slowed down, and cortisol level and perceived physical strain increased, but other stress and motor scores didn’t change. Furthermore, control efficiency was not correlated with motor and stress scores. From this we conclude that realistic instrument control was degraded in short-term microgravity. This degradation can’t be explained by the motor and/or stress indicators under study, and microgravity affected motor performance differently in our complex, realistic skill than in the simple, laboratory-type skills of earlier studies.</p>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <funding-statement>This work was funded by Deutsches Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt (grant number 50WB1224) (URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dlr.de">www.dlr.de</ext-link>); OB received the funding. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="4"/>
                <table-count count="3"/>
                <page-count count="11"/>
              </counts>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta id="data-availability">
                  <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
            <notes>
              <title>Data Availability</title>
              <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
            </notes>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The success of manned space missions depends critically on skilled human performance, such as spacecraft navigation and control of onboard scientific equipment. It therefore is disquieting that human skills were found to degrade in short- and long-term weightlessness: Pointing, tracking and grasping movements slowed down and/or became less accurate [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and their cognitive demand increased [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Although the above work dealt with simple, laboratory-type skills, it has been suggested that astronauts’ regular daily activities are degraded as well [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, such a generalization may be inadequate for two reasons. First, simple skills show different kinematics and dynamics when they are executed in a typical laboratory context versus in a more realistic context [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and are differently affected by microgravity [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Second, simple skills may be differently affected by microgravity than complex daily routines. We therefore decided to evaluate the influence of short-term microgravity not on simple, laboratory-type skills but rather on a complex skill that bears a resemblance to astronauts’ instrument control routines.</p>
              <p>The observed degradation of simple, laboratory-type skills in microgravity has been attributed not only to direct effects on the sensorimotor system [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], but also to indirect effects, mediated by stress [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Indeed, microgravity scenarios involve multiple stressors such as time pressure, ambient noise, lack of privacy, changed sleep pattern and imminent danger [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and raise the levels of neurovegetative, endocrine and psychological stress markers during space missions [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], as well as during parabolic flights [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Since increased stress has been associated with impaired motor skills on Earth [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], especially when tasks are complex [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], it is quite conceivable that increased stress in microgravity contributes towards the impairment of complex skills in microgravity as well. We therefore decided to assess not only instrument control and basic motor performance of our participants, but also their level of stress.</p>
              <p>Our working hypothesis was that instrument control is degraded in short-term microgravity, and that this deficit is mediated by motor impairments and/or by elevated stress.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
              <title>Material and Methods</title>
              <sec id="sec003">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>Twelve right-handed volunteers (7 males and 5 females) aged 28.8 ± 4.8 years participated. They had no prior experience in parabolic flight or sensorimotor research and no history of vestibular or sensorimotor deficits. Data were recorded during four parabolic flight campaigns held in Bordeaux (France) 2013 and 2014; each parabolic flight consisted of 30 intervals of 20 s duration under near-weightlessness (μG), each of them embedded in intervals of 20 s duration under increased weight (1.8G) and 30 intervals of 1–8 minutes duration under normal weight (1G). All participants underwent a clinical check prior to the study and received scopolamine (men received 0.7 mg and women 0.5 mg) approximately 1 hour before take-off to prevent motion sickness. The effects of Scopolamine start within an hour after intake and last for about eight hours [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]; since testing started about 90 minutes after intake and lasted for about four hours, we expected that possible effects of motion sickness and side effects of Scopolamine would influence subjects‘ performance evenly during the 1G and μG phases of our experiment. We nevertheless decided to guard against a differential influence by testing subjects in the order 1G - μG—μG- 1G (see below).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec004">
                <title>Ethics statement</title>
                <p>All volunteers were completely clarified about study procedure and aims and signed a written informed consent statement before participating in this study. The study involved human participants and was in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki, which was pre-approved by the local Ethics Committee of the German Sport University and by the French Ethics Committee administered through the University of Caen.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec005">
                <title>Setup</title>
                <p>Participants sat in front of a 17” screen with a built-in eye tracker system (Tobii T60, sampling rate: 60 Hz; Gaze data will be analyzed in a separate communication.) and were secured by a seatbelt in order to prevent free floating in μG. To the right of the screen was a control panel with four actuators (see <xref rid="pone.0128992.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A, 1B and 1C</xref>): A cylindrical rotatable knob of 35 mm diameter, one of 70 mm diameter, a rotary switch of 17 x 25 mm size which could be turned in six steps of 20°, and a standard flip switch of 17 mm length. These actuators were selected for similarity with actuators aboard the International Space Station (see <xref rid="pone.0128992.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>). Force sensors (ATI Nano 17) registered the grip forces at a sampling rate of 250 Hz and rotary encoders (RoHS RES20; 20Hz) registered the position of each actuator—except for the flip switch. Four Vicon Bonita cameras registered the positions of six infrared-light reflecting markers (6 mm in diameter), attached by double sided adhesive tape to the participants’ index fingertip, thumb and midpoint of the index finger’s metacarpal bone; the data were converted into 3D marker positions with a sampling rate of 240 Hz and an accuracy of 1 mm.</p>
                <fig id="pone.0128992.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.g001</object-id>
                  <label>Fig 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Experimental setup, control task and experimental timeline.</title>
                    <p><bold>a:</bold> Experimental setup for the use in parabolic flights. Shown is a participant sitting in a chair in front of the Eye tracker (incorporated in the screen) and the control panel within the metal frame, which serves as the construction for assembly into the parabolic flight plane. Four Bonita Vicon cameras for 3D hand motion capturing surround the participant. <bold>b:</bold> Screen of the simulated power plant with feedback displays regarding the requested power (top left), level of fuel rods (middle left), light button (top middle), temperature (bottom left), cooling tank (bottom middle) and earnings (right). The top left display element presents the inset for power requests. <bold>c</bold>: Enlargement of the control panel as shown in “a” with the small and big rotatable knobs, the rotary switch and the flip switch. The small rotatable knob controls the display element on the bottom left, the rotary switch the middle-left, the flip switch the light button and the big rotatable knob controls the top left element. <bold>d:</bold> Experimental time line for a participant during one flight day; shown are the points in time where the measurements were taken with respect to the flight profile along with the blocks of the control task. Cortisol stands for collection of saliva sample, the MoodMeter for mood assessment and the TLX for the NASA task load index.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0128992.g001"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec006">
                <title>Control task</title>
                <p>Participants were engaged in a game that simulates a complex real-life scenario, the control of a nuclear power plant. To this end, seven displays were presented on the screen (see <xref rid="pone.0128992.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). A bar on the right showed the momentary earnings in Euros of the power plant; this was the most important display element, since the aim of the game was to maximize those earnings. A circular display at the top left indicated the momentary power production and–as an inset–the requested power production. Participants could adjust the momentary production by rotating the larger knob to reduce the difference between momentary and requested production, and thus to increase the rate of earnings. To make this task more challenging, requested production changed every 5 to 10 s such that participants permanently had to monitor and adjust power production. All participants were given the same sequence of power requests.</p>
                <p>A circular display at the middle left indicated the momentary energy capacity of the fuel rod in use. This capacity decreased in proportion to the momentary power production and accordingly, a pointer rotated from the green to the red sector of the display. When it reached the red sector, participants had to insert a new rod such as to prevent a shutdown of the plant that would curtail their earnings. They inserted the rod by moving the rotary switch one step clockwise, which restored the pointer into the green sector and decremented the number of fuel rods in stock displayed in the center of the screen. After the last (sixth) rot was inserted, participants had to refill the stock by moving the rotary switch six steps counterclockwise. The refill incurred costs, i.e., the displayed earnings decreased.</p>
                <p>A circular display at the bottom left showed the core temperature. The temperature increased proportionally with power production and, when the pointer reached the end of the red sector, the plant shut down. Thus to prevent a loss of earnings, participants had to monitor the core temperature and, when necessary, refill the cooling tank displayed at the bottom center of the screen. They did so by rotating the smaller knob.</p>
                <p>Note that task complexity was augmented by the use of an incompatible actuator-display arrangement: the top knob controlled the bottom display, and vice versa. As another measure to increase task complexity, we simulated the night-day cycle by slowly darkening the screen over an interval of 11–20 s; by the end of that time, a beep and a light flash in the top middle of the screen prompted subjects to “turn on the lights’ by operating the flip switch. This happened once per episode, i.e., participants turned the light on by flipping the switch up in one episode, by flipping it down in the next, etc.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec007">
                <title>Stress assessments</title>
                <p>Subjective workload was assessed by a German translation of the NASA task load index (TLX), which consists of six items judged on a 20-point Likert scale. Mood was assessed by a modified version [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] of the Mood Meter [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], using 32 items rated on a 6-point Likert scale. Both questionnaires were administered in a paper-and-pencil form. To yield an objective measure of stress, saliva samples were taken to determine cortisol levels. This was done not only during the flight but also at the same times-of-day 24 hours later, to establish a baseline.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec008">
                <title>Experimental protocol</title>
                <p>One day before the flight, participants were familiarized with all procedures and practiced 13 episodes of the control task on the ground. Task difficulty (i.e. change of requested power scores) of training episodes was held at an equal level as in the experimental conditions; all participants reported to understand the task, which was additionally indicated by a positive earning (i.e. task success) and validated by subjective impression of investigators. On the day of flight, data were collected during level flight (1G) and during the near-weightlessness periods of parabolic flight (μG). The control task was subdivided into two blocks of 13 episodes of 20 s duration, such that each episode fitted into one μG interval. The first block was scheduled during 1G. All game settings and scores were then stored, the game was reset, and two further blocks were completed during μG. The stored game settings and scores were then re-instated, and a final block was given during 1G. <xref rid="pone.0128992.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref> summarizes this protocol along with the stress assessments.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec009">
                <title>Data analysis</title>
                <p>Kinematic and force data were reduced to a set of movement parameters by an interactive computer algorithm, as summarized under “motor performance” in <xref rid="pone.0128992.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Signal processing filtering was performed by an eight-point simple moving average (SMA). Peak hand velocity (PHV) was calculated based on the velocity (cm/s) profile (in xyz-direction) for the marker attached to the wrist for each hand movement. The computer algorithm plotted the velocity profile and indicated PHV by a marker in order that each movement could be inspected visually for correctness and changed manually if necessary. Peak grip aperture (PGA) was calculated as the maximum 3D distance between the two markers that were attached to the thumbs´ and index fingers´ tops for each movement to a knob. For both parameters (PHV and PGA) visual markers were only set at a time interval of 1500 ms before contact to a knob to avoid inclusion of movements not directed to a knob. Maximum force (F) was calculated (via the force sensors) by the maximum knob compression in all (xyz-) force directions acting at the knob’s surface for each manipulation phase. Knob contact time (CT) was calculated as the time for the first force registration above baseline values until below or equal baseline values. Number of knob contacts ((KC) i.e. grasping movements) for each knob and across knobs were calculated for each episode and added up for each condition (1G, μG). Less than 5% of kinematic data were lost due to marker obtrusion. Parameter means across both 1G blocks and the means across both μG blocks were used for further analyses. As an index of movement variability the coefficients of variation (CV) for the parameters of motor performance (i.e. PHV, PGA, CT and F) were calculated. Control efficiency was determined as the sum of each net earnings (revenue minus expenses) of each 26 episodes of the respective condition (μG and 1G). Thus, this score represented the displayed earnings in Euros at the end of the second 1G block, as well as at the end of the second μG block. MoodMeter ratings were expressed as perceived physical strain (PEPS), psychological strain (PSYCHO) and motivational state (MOT), as per the test manual, while TLX ratings gave an overall workload score. Saliva Cortisol levels were expressed as difference between inflight and baseline values. All data were submitted to analyses of variance (ANOVAs) with repeated measures on Gravity (1G, μG) or on testing Time (early, middle, late) or on Gravity (1G, μG) crossed with Knob type (small, large, rot). Significant differences were explored with Bonferroni post-hoc tests.</p>
                <table-wrap id="pone.0128992.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.t001</object-id>
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Summary and description of all test variables<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic id="pone.0128992.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0128992.t001"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Component</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abbreviation (unit)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">
                            <italic>Motor performance</italic>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Transport component of the hand</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHV</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak hand velocity while grasping a knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHVsmall (cm/s)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak hand velocity while grasping the small knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHVlarge (cm/s)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak hand velocity while grasping the large knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHVrot (cm/s)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak hand velocity while grasping the rotary switch</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Grasp component of the hand</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGA</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak Grip Aperture while grasping a knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGAsmall (mm)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak Grip Aperture while grasping the small knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGAlarge (mm)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak Grip Aperture while grasping the large knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGArot (mm)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak Grip Aperture while grasping the rotary switch</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Grip force</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak grip force while grasping a knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fsmall (N)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak grip force while grasping the small knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flarge (N)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak grip force while grasping the large knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frot (N)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak grip force while grasping the rotary switch</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Grip time</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knob contact time</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTsmall (s)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT for the small knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTlarge (s)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT for the large knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTrot (s)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT for the rotary switch</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Number of grasping movements</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="4" align="left" colspan="1">Knob contacts</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count of knob contacts</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KCsmall (quantity)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count of contacts of the small knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KClarge (quantity)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count of contacts of the large knob</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KCrot (quantity)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count of knob contacts of the rotary switch</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">
                            <italic>Stress</italic>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mood Meter</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEPS</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean of items for perceived physical strain</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSYCHO</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean of items for psychological strain</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOT</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean of items for motivational state</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva Cortisol</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cortisol (μg/dl)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cortisol level on flight minus on baseline day</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Task Load Index</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLX</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum of all items</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">
                            <italic>Operational efficiency</italic>
                          </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control efficiency</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efficiency (€)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Net final earnings in 1G and in μG</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t001fn001">
                      <p>*Shown in the left column are all analyzed parameters, in the middle column the respective acronyms and units, and in the right column short parameter descriptions.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t001fn002">
                      <p>Additional detailed parameter descriptions and signal processing is described in “Data analysis”.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>We also performed a stepwise multiple linear regression analysis, with the difference between 1G and μG scores of control efficiency as the dependent variable. As independent variables served the difference between 1G and μG scores of the motor parameters PHV, PGA, F and CT, and the difference between the first and last test scores of the Cortisol level, the TLX score and the MoodMeter scores for PEPS, PSYCHO and MOT. Effect sizes are reported only for significant results to avoid reporting negligible effect sizes. Effect sizes of ANOVAs were estimated as eta-squares (η<sup>2</sup>), where η<sup>2</sup> &gt; .01 indicates a small, η<sup>2</sup> &gt; .06 a medium and η<sup>2</sup> &gt;.14 a large effect [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Due to technical problems, some variables were only available from less than 12 participants, which is indicated in the respective analyses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec010">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec011">
                <title>Control task performance</title>
                <p>As depicted in <xref rid="pone.0128992.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, participants earned less money in μG compared to 1G. The difference between Gravity conditions (1G, μG) was statistically significant (<italic>F</italic> (1, 11) = 19.714, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .64) and it was substantial, amounting to 17.6% less earnings. <xref rid="pone.0128992.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref> illustrates all motor scores in μG and 1G, and <xref rid="pone.0128992.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the pertinent ANOVA outcome. Gravity had no significant effect on any motor parameter, the factor Knob (large, rotary and small knob) expectedly had significant effects on all parameters (PHV, PGA, F, CT, KC), and the interaction term (Knob x Gravity) was significant only for PHV. The latter finding reflects, according to <xref rid="pone.0128992.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, a reduction of hand velocity in μG for the small knob and the rotary switch (both <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05), but not for the large knob (<italic>p</italic> &gt; .05). The magnitude of this reduction averaged for the small knob 8.3% and for the rotary switch 4.8%. Movement variability was in an acceptable range for all parameters (between 0.13 und 0.67) and Gravity (1G, μG) had no significant effect on any variability parameter (ANOVAs for CVs of PHV, PGA, F and CT were all <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05).</p>
                <fig id="pone.0128992.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.g002</object-id>
                  <label>Fig 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Control efficiency.</title>
                    <p>Shown is the parameter control efficiency in normal (1G) and in microgravity (μG). 1G score is the total earned money across all 26 episodes of the control task performed in normal gravity; accordingly μG score represents the earnings of all 26 episodes of the control task in microgravity. Data are presented as means ± standard errors divided by 1000. *** = <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0128992.g002"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="pone.0128992.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.g003</object-id>
                  <label>Fig 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Motor performance.</title>
                    <p>Shown are the interaction plots of grasping parameters subdivided by their values of the three knobs (large, rotary and small knob) in normal (1G) and in microgravity (μG). PHV represents peak hand velocity, PGA the peak grip aperture, CT the knob contact time, F the maximum force applied to the knobs and KC the number of grasping movements performed in each condition and for each knob. Mean KC values for all knobs were above 50, which were acceptable for calculating means of motor performance. For all parameters, significant effects were found between the large, rotary and small knob (all <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). Significant interaction (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) emerged between Knob x Gravity for PHV with speed reduction of the small (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) and rotary knob (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) in microgravity, and no change for the big knob (<italic>p</italic> &gt; .05). All other ANOVA factors were not significant (<italic>p</italic> &gt; .05). Data are presented as means ± standard errors, additional statistics are summarized in <xref rid="pone.0128992.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0128992.g003"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="pone.0128992.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.t002</object-id>
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>ANOVA of motor parameters.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic id="pone.0128992.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0128992.t002"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters &amp; ANOVA factors</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>F</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>p</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">η<sup>2</sup>
</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHV</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 21.380</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; .001</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.704</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (1, 9) = .991</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob X Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 3.960</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">= .04</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.306</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGA</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 37.572</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; .001</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.807</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (1, 9) = .982</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob X Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 1.056</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 29.541</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; .001</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.766</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (1, 9) = .006</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob X Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 2.057</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 22.807</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; .001</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.717</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (1, 9) = .021</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob X Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 1.453</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 36.744</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; .001</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.803</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (1, 9) = 1.68</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Knob X Gravity</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> (2, 18) = 2.439</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec012">
                <title>Stress assessment</title>
                <p>Separate ANOVAs for three dimensions of mood assessment yielded a significant effect of Time (early, mid, late) for PEPS (<italic>F</italic> (2, 22) = 4.525, <italic>p</italic> = .02, η<sup>2</sup> = .29), but not for PSYCHO and MOT (both <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05). Post-hoc analysis of PEPS revealed significant differences only between early and middle (<italic>p</italic> = .02): only the middle phase of μG (i.e. after 15 parabolas including performance of 13 control task episodes) was considered to be physically more stressing, as illustrated in <xref rid="pone.0128992.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>. There was no significant effect of Time for TLX (<italic>F</italic> (2, 22) = .228, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05) but there was one for Cortisol (<italic>F</italic> (2, 20) = 4.093, <italic>p</italic> = .03, η<sup>2</sup> = .29). <xref rid="pone.0128992.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref> illustrates a continuous increase of Cortisol levels from early to middle to late time, but post-hoc decomposition revealed a significant difference only between early and late (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05).</p>
                <fig id="pone.0128992.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.g004</object-id>
                  <label>Fig 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Stress indicators.</title>
                    <p>Shown are the Cortisol levels and the three dimensions of the MoodMeter questionnaire. PEPS abbreviates the physical, PSYCHO the psychological and MOT the motivational mood dimension. One significant effect for the factor Time was found for PEPS (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) between early and mid (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05); all other ANOVA factors were not significant (<italic>p</italic> &gt; .05). Abbreviations of the x-axis indicate points in time corresponding to the flight profile, i.e. ‘early’ is taken before the 1G-1<sup>st</sup> block, ‘mid’ is after the μG-1<sup>st</sup> block and ‘late’ is before the 1G-2<sup>nd</sup> block (cf. <xref rid="pone.0128992.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1D</xref>). Data are presented as means ± standard errors.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0128992.g004"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Stepwise multiple linear regression with an inclusion criteria for each variable was set at F values = 1 or higher led to the inclusion of only two parameters, PHV and Cortisol, and didn't reach statistical significance (<italic>F</italic> (2, 7) = 2.26; R<sup>2</sup> = .39, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05, see <xref rid="pone.0128992.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>)."</p>
                <table-wrap id="pone.0128992.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128992.t003</object-id>
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Multiple stepwise regression of motor and stress changes on control efficiency change.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic id="pone.0128992.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0128992.t003"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                        <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>b</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>t</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>p</italic>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHV</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-12.07</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.85</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cortisol</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-882.29</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.32</td>
                          <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; .05</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec013">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The present study evaluated how human performance in a complex, realistic control task is affected by short-term microgravity, and whether changes of performance are associated with changes of basic motor functions and/or stress. We found no appreciable effects of microgravity on grasping kinematics and dynamics, except for reduced hand movement speed towards the smaller two actuators. This is in contrast to a variety of previous studies that observed an influence of μG on several grasping parameters during a simple laboratory-type task [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] as well as during a simple, everyday-like task [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. From this we conclude that grasping is not uniformly affected by μG: Elementary grasping acts are influenced more than grasping movements embedded in a realistic instrument control skill.</p>
              <p>We have observed before that μG may affect the kinematics of one task but not those of another task, and attributed this discrepancy to a differential allocation of the brain’s computational resources [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. A similar interpretation may hold for the discrepant data on grasping: Our control task was quite captivating, which possibly enticed participants to allocate extra resources to the motor system and thus keep motor responses unchanged in μG; the simple grasping acts of previous studies were possibly less effective in increasing the resource supply. This interpretation is in accordance with our stress data. Perceived physical strain and Cortisol (an indicator of psychological [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] as well as physical stress [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]) increased in μG while psychological strain, motivational state and task load were not affected; this pattern of findings has been reported before [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and it is consistent with the notion that physical but not psychological stress is elevated during parabolic flight as more resources are allocated to the motor system.</p>
              <p>Besides the above effects of μG on grasping and stress, we also observed a substantial degradation of control efficiency. Similarly, previous work has reported a degradation of surgical skills in μG: the number of completed tasks [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and their quality decreased [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The large drop of control efficiency is difficult to explain by the relatively subtle changes of grasping performance; however, it could well be related to the change of physical stress. In particular, the allocation of additional resources to motor control may have led to a shortage of resources for other task components, such as display monitoring and decision making. If so, changes of control efficiency in μG should be correlated with changes of stress, and less so with changes of grasping. However, multiple regression analysis revealed no substantial associations between the gravity-related changes of control efficiency, motor performance and stress. Thus, although stress influences the performance of complex motor tasks on Earth [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], we found no evidence that it mediates the change of control efficiency in microgravity.</p>
              <p>This is not to say that control efficiency in μG is completely immune to stress. Stressors such as imminent danger and lack of privacy exist on parabolic flights, but have not been assessed in our study. Likewise, stress indicators such as α-Amylase, Prolactin and Epinephrine are known to influence cognitive and motor functions [<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128992.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], but have not been registered in the present work. The possibility therefore remains that realistic working performance in μG is degraded because of aspects of stress that were not considered in our study. Likewise, it may be degraded because of motor deficits not captured in the present study. Alternatively, the degradation might reflect the effects of μG on mental functions such as affect, distributed attention, concentration, multitasking or decision-making.</p>
              <p>Our finding, that the performance of a realistic control task is degraded in short-term microgravity should be extended by research during long-term space missions; if it persists, it would have practical implications for the planning of space activities and for the preflight training of astronauts.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec014">
              <title>Supporting Information</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128992.s001">
                <label>S1 File</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Complete data of the study.</title>
                  <p>(SAV)</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="pone.0128992.s001.sav">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>The authors wish to thank B. Schulze, B. Baak, N. Bury, A. Brosel, N. Elting, M. Kraul, and S. Scherhag for their help by data recording and analyses; T. Kesnerus and O. Kopp for software development; M. Küsel, J. Geiermann, and H. Schink for technical support; the NOVESPACE team for organizing the parabolic flight campaign, especially A. Jaquemet, F. Gai and N. Courtroux, as well as Dr. U. Friedrich from the German Aerospace Center (DLR) and Vladimir Pletser from the European Space Agency (ESA).</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref001">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mescheriakov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molokanova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lechner-Steinleitner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seguer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozlovskaya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Pointing arm movements in short- and long-term spaceflights</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>68</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>787</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9293345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9293345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref002">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Money</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Accuracy of aimed arm movements in change gravity</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>63</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>998</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 1445164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1445164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref003">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Comfort</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Human sensorimotor coordination during spaceflight. An analysis of pointing and tracking responses during the "Neurolab" space shuttle mission</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>72</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>883</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11601550?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11601550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref004">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Papaxanthis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pozzo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Kinematic and dynamic processes for the control of pointing movements in humans revealed by short-term exposure to microgravity</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>135</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16125854?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16125854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref005">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Grasping of virtual objects in changed gravity</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source> (<volume>67</volume>): <fpage>1185</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8968487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8968487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref006">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abeele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eversheim</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Sensorimotor performance and computational demand during short-term exposure to microgravity</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>74</volume> (<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1256</fpage>–<lpage>1262</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14692468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14692468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref007">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jüngling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girgenrath</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Speed-accuracy trade-off of grasping movements during microgravity</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>73</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12014601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12014601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref008">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Manzey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schiewe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Dual-task performance in space. Results from a single-case study during a short-term space mission</article-title>. <source>Hum Factors</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8851772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8851772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref009">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kanas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manzey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <chapter-title>Space psychology and psychiatry</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Dondrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref010">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloomberg</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cognitive demand of human sensorimotor performance during an extended space mission. a dual-task study</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>81</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>824</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 20824987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20824987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref011">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bock O, Fowler B, Jüngling S, Comfort D (2003c) Visual-motor coordination during spaceflight. In: Bockey J, Homick J, editor. The Neurolab Space Mission: neuroscience research in space. Houston, Tx. pp. 83–89.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref012">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Manzey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Mental performance during short-term and long-term spaceflight</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Rev</source>
<volume>28</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9935307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9795225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref013">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rafiq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broderick</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doarn</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merrell</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Assessment of simulated surgical skills in parabolic microgravity</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>76</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15828640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15828640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref014">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Influence of cognitive function and behavioral context on grasping kinematics</article-title>. <source>Exp Brain Res</source>
<volume>225</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-012-3379-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23274646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23274646</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref015">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Züll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Characteristics of grasping movements in a laboratory and in an everyday-like context</article-title>. <source>Hum Mov Sci</source>
<volume>32</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humov.2012.12.009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23452944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23452944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref016">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Context dependence of manual grasping movements in near weightlessness</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>84</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref017">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Problems of sensorimotor coordination in weightlessness</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Rev</source>
<volume>28</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9935307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9795196</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref018">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kornilova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Orientation illusions in spaceflight</article-title>. <source>J Vestibular Res</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9397393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9397393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref019">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lackner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiZio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Motor function in microgravity. movement in weightlessness</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source>
<volume>6</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>744</fpage>–<lpage>750</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9000028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9000028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref020">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Comfort</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Is dual-task performance necessarily impaired in space</article-title>. <source>Hum Factors</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11022887?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11022887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref021">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Manzey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heuer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sangals</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Impairments of manual tracking performance during spaceflight. more converging evidence from a 20-day space mission</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>
<volume>43</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10877478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10877478</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref022">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De la Torre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Cognitive Neuroscience in Space</article-title>. <source>Life</source>
<volume>4</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life4030281</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25370373?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25370373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref023">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johannes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salnitski</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polyakov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Changes in the autonomic reactivity pattern to psychological load under long-term microgravity—twelve men during 6-month spaceflights</article-title>. <source>Aviakosmicheskaia i ekologicheskaia meditsina = Aerospace and environmental medicine Aviakosm Ekolog Med</source>
<volume>37</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12882030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref024">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Macho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koška</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kšinantová</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pacak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noskov</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The response of endocrine system to stress loads during space flight in human subject</article-title>. <source>Adv Space Res</source>
<volume>31</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1605</fpage>–<lpage>1610</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12971416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12971416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref025">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brümmer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kleinert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guardiera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The effect of parabolic flight on perceived physical, motivational and psychological state in men and women. Correlation with neuroendocrine stress parameters and electrocortical activity</article-title>. <source>Stress</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10253890802499175</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19006009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19006009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref026">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Verheyden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Spectral characteristics of heart rate fluctuations during parabolic flight</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>
<volume>95</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>568</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16235070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16235070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref027">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vasmatsidis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Human occupational and performance limits under stress. The thermal environment as a prototypical example</article-title>. <source>Ergonomics</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1169</fpage>–<lpage>1191</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9715675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9715675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref028">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Stress as a modulator of motor system function and pathology</article-title>. <source>Rev Neuroscience</source>
<volume>18</volume> (<issue>3–4</issue>): <fpage>2009</fpage>–<lpage>2222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref029">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Hockey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <chapter-title>Fatigue and complex decision making under prolonged isolation and confinement</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Bonting</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Advances in Space Biology and Medicine</source>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> pp. <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8814806?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref030">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Hockey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiethoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <chapter-title>Cognitive Fatigue In Complex Decision-Making Advances in Space Biology and Medicine</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Bonting</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Advances in Space Biology and Medicine</source>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> pp. <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref031">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hockey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Compensatory control in the regulation of human performance under stress and high workload. A cognitive-energetical framework</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychol</source>
<volume>45</volume> (<issue>1–3</issue>): <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9172711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9083645</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref032">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Motion sickness: review of causes and preventive strategies</article-title>. <source>J Travel Med</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12962599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12962599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref033">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kleinert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Adjektivliste zur Erfassung der wahrgenommenen körperlichen Verfassung (WKV). Skalenkonstruktion und erste psychometrische Befunde [Adjective list for assessing Perceived Physical State (PEPS). Scale construction and psychometric results]</article-title>. <source>Z SPORTPSYCHOL</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref034">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <chapter-title>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences (rev</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref035">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirschbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Human hypothalamus–pituitary–adrenal axis responses to acute psychosocial stress in laboratory settings</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav R</source>
<volume>35</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2010.01.010</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20109491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20109491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref036">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Kloet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joëls</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holsboer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Stress and the brain: from adaptation to disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>6</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>475</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15891777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15891777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0128992.ref037">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rafiq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hummel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavrentyev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merrell</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Microgravity effects on fine motor skills: tying surgical knots during parabolic flight</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Envir Md</source>
<volume>77</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16909881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16909881</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
