<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T18:06:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4013332" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4013332</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-05-15</datestamp>
        <setSpec>chinjcanc</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin J Cancer</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chin J Cancer</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CJC</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Chinese Journal of Cancer</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1000-467X</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1944-446X</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4013332</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4013332</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4013332</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098948</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098948</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cjc-30-12-842</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5732/cjc.011.10174</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Spaceflight alters the gene expression profile of cervical cancer cells</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhi-Jie</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tong</surname>
                    <given-names>Yong-Qing</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Jia-Jia</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>Cheng</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhou</surname>
                    <given-names>Guo-Hua</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Yue-Hui</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Xie</surname>
                    <given-names>Ping-Li</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hu</surname>
                    <given-names>Jin-Yue</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Guan-Cheng</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1">
                <addr-line><bold>Authors' Affiliation:</bold> Cancer Research Institute, Xiangya School of Medicine, Central South University, Changsha, Hunan 410078, P. R. China</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Guan-Cheng Li, Cancer Research Institute, Xiangya School of Medicine, Central South University, Changsha, Hunan 410078, P. R. China. Tel: <phone>+86-731-84805445</phone>; Fax: <fax>+86-731-82355042</fax>; Email: <email>libsun@163.com</email>.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2011</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>30</volume>
              <issue>12</issue>
              <fpage>842</fpage>
              <lpage>852</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>31</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2011</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Chinese Journal of Cancer</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
                <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License, which allows readers to alter, transform, or build upon the article and then distribute the resulting work under the same or similar license to this one. The work must be attributed back to the original author and commercial use is not permitted without specific permission.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>Our previous study revealed that spaceflight induced biological changes in human cervical carcinoma Caski cells. Here, we report that 48A9 cells, which were subcloned from Caski cells, experienced significant growth suppression and exhibited low tumorigenic ability after spaceflight. To further understand the potential mechanism at the transcriptional level, we compared gene expression between 48A9 cells and ground control Caski cells with suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH) and reverse Northern blotting methods, and analyzed the relative gene network and molecular functions with the Ingenuity Pathways Analysis (IPA) program. We found 5 genes, <italic>SUB1</italic>, <italic>SGEF</italic>, <italic>MALAT-1</italic>, <italic>MYL6</italic>, and <italic>MT-CO2</italic>, to be up-regulated and identified 3 new cDNAs, termed <italic>B4, B5</italic>, and <italic>C4</italic>, in 48A9 cells. In addition, we also identified the two most significant gene networks to indicate the function of these genes using the IPA program. To our knowledge, our results show for the first time that spaceflight can reduce the growth of tumor cells, and we also provide a new model for oncogenesis study.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Cervical carcinoma</kwd>
                <kwd>oncogenesis</kwd>
                <kwd>tumor suppressor</kwd>
                <kwd>subtractive cDNA libraries</kwd>
                <kwd>SSH</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>A complex environmental condition exsited during spaceflight in which several interacting factors such as cosmic radiation, microgravity, and space magnetic fields may provoke stress responses, jeopardize genome integrity, and induce various biological changes in cells<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>–<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Currently, a majority of studies on spaceflight focus on normal tissues and cells; however, little is known of the effects of spaceflight on abnormal cells such as cancer cells.</p>
            <p>To investigate potential effects of space environment exposure on cancer cells, we examined the biological changes in Caski cells that experienced spaceflight aboard the “Shen Zhou IV” spaceship<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. After seven days in space, surviving cells were subcloned into 1440 cell lines. Of these, four cell lines were screened with cell proliferation assays, flow Cytometry, soft agar assays, and tumor formation experiments in nude mice. The 44F10 and 17E3 cell lines were selected because of their increased cell proliferation and tumorigenesis, whereas the 48A9 and 31F2 cell lines had obvious slower cytological events. In particular, 48A9 cells showed significantly diminished growth ability and decreased tumorigenesis <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> compared with ground control Caski cells. To further investigate 48A9 cells at the Subcellular level, we examined the expression of 2747 tumor-associated genes in 48A9 Caski cells by DNA microarray analysis. The results indicated that genes differentially expressed in cells exposed to spaceflight were related to cell cycle, apoptosis, proliferation, and signal transduction.</p>
            <p>Microarray is a powerful technique with which to identify possible ectopic gene expression; however, it has some disadvantages. For example, microarray cannot be used to detect unknown transcripts or to discriminate variant transcripts from previously characterized transcripts. Moreover, with only 2747 tumor-associated probe sets used in the study, our analysis reflected only a part of the altered gene expression patterns. In order to further understand the biological changes in 48A9 cells at the transcriptional level, we used an improved suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH) method to selectively determine differentially expressed genes<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Using this method in 48A9 cells exposed to spaceflight, we successfully identified several genes to be significantly up-regulated, including Src homology 3 domain-containing guanine nucleotide exchange factor (<italic>SGEF</italic>), submergence-1 (<italic>SUB1</italic>), non-coding RNA metastasis-associated lung adenocarcinoma transcript 1 (<italic>MALAT-1</italic>), cytochrome c oxidase subunit 2 (<italic>MT-CO2</italic>), and myosin light chain 6 (<italic>MYL6</italic>), and identified three new putative genes. Furthermore, two most significant gene networks were identified using the Ingenuity Pathways Analysis (IPA) program. To our knowledge, our results show for the first time that spaceflight can reduce the growth of tumor cells, and we also provide a new model to study oncogenesis.</p>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <sec id="s2a">
                <title>Cell culture</title>
                <p>The human cervical carcinoma Caski cell strain was used as a ground control, and the 48A9 subclonal Caski cell strain<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> was used for testing the effects of spaceflight. Both cell lines were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (DMEM) (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) containing 10% FBS and antibiotics in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 95% air at 37°C.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2b">
                <title>Cellular mRNA isolation</title>
                <p>mRNA was directly extracted from ground control and 48A9 Caski cells and purified with the PolyATtract<sup>®</sup> mRNA isolation system kit (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA) according to manufacturer's instruction. mRNA integrity was analyzed by gel electrophoresis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2c">
                <title>SMART™ cDNA synthesis</title>
                <p>cDNAs were synthesized from 1 µg mRNA using super SMART™ polymerase chain reaction (PCR) cDNA synthesis kit (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) as described in the user manual. Briefly, a modified oligo (dT) primer primes the first-strand synthesis reaction. When reverse transcriptase (RT) reaches the 5′ end of the mRNA, the enzyme's terminal transferase activity adds a few additional nucleotides, primarily deoxycytidine, to the 3′ end of the cDNA. The SMART™ oligonucleotide which has an oligo(G) sequence at its 3′ end, base-pairs with the deoxycytidine stretch, creating an extended template. RT then switches templates and continues replicating to the end of the oligonucleotide. The smart anchor sequence and the poly A sequence serve as universal priming sites for end-to-end cDNA amplification by long-distance PCR with advantage 2 polymerase mix (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA). The PCR products, SMART™ cDNA, were purified with PCR purification kit (Qiagen, Shanghai, China) and used for the suppression subtractive hybridization experiment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2d">
                <title>SSH</title>
                <p>The PCR-selected cDNA subtraction kit was purchased from Clontech (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) and used according to the manufacturer's instructions. In brief, cDNA products were digested with <italic>Rsa</italic> I. The digested 48A9 cell cDNA was then ligated with adapters provided in the kit. Ligation efficiency was determined by PCR. Two rounds of hybridization were performed using 48A9 cell cDNA as the tester and ground control cell cDNA as the driver. An additional two rounds of subtractive PCR were performed to enrich differential fragments. To evaluate the subtractive efficiency, the relative amount of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (<italic>GAPDH</italic>) present in the subtracted and unsubtracted cDNA was determined by PCR amplification using the primers provided in the kit.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2e">
                <title>Construction of subtractive cDNA libraries</title>
                <p>The second round subtractive PCR products were cloned into the pMD19-T vector (TaKaRa, Dalian, China). Ligation products were subsequently transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5α competent cells (TaKaRa, Dalian, China), plated on prepared LB agar plates containing 200 µg/mL ampicillin, 625 µmol/L IPTG, and 0.005% X-gal. After 12 h in the 37°C incubator, the presence of cDNA inserts was verified by PCR amplification using nested PCR primers supplied in the PCR-selected cDNA subtraction kit.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2f">
                <title>Reverse Northern blotting and sequencing</title>
                <p>The differentially expressed genes were screened by reverse Northern blotting and identified by sequencing. Briefly, the recombinant clones including cDNA inserts were amplified by PCR using nested PCR primers with <italic>Pfu</italic> DNA polymerase (Promega, Madison, Wl, USA). A total of 192 PCR products (2 µg) were denatured in 0.4 mol/L NaOH and spotted onto a nylon membrane (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA) in duplicate. The cDNAs were cross-linked to the membrane by incubation at 80°C for 2 h. The membranes were hybridized in ExpressHyb™ solution (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) at 68°C for 18 h with equivalent specific activity of <sup>32</sup>P-labeled cDNA probes derived from 48A9 or ground control cells, followed by washing in a low stringency solution (2× SSC, 1% SDS; 3 times for 15 min) and then a high stringency solution (0.1× SSC, 0.5% SDS; 3 times for 15 min) at 68°C. Finally, the membranes were exposed to X-film (Pierce, Woburn, MA, USA) for 48 h at –70°C. After scanning, the intensity of the hybridization signals was determined with Image J software provided by National Institutes of Health (NIH). Differentially expressed clones that were screened by reverse Northern dot blotting were sequenced and analyzed for homology to known sequences in the National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) database.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2g">
                <title>Semi-quantitative RT-PCR</title>
                <p>To further confirm the SSH results, total RNA was extracted from 48A9 and ground control cells with TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the standard protocol. M-MuLV reverse transcriptase and oligo-dT primer (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) were used to synthesize cDNA. Finally, PCR amplification was performed using gene-specific primers. Semi-quantitative analysis of the mRNA level was achieved with 1% agarose gel electrophoresis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2h">
                <title>Network and function analysis</title>
                <p>The differentially expressed genes in 48A9 cells, which were identified by SSH and our previous microarray experiment<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, were further analyzed using the online IPA program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">http://www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>). Briefly, the up-regulated genes identified by SSH and up- and down-regulated genes identified by microarray were uploaded into IPA and were then mapped to the Ingenuity Pathways Knowledge base. The so-called focus genes were used for network generation and biological function and/or diseases analyses. Networks of these focus genes were algorithmically generated based on their connectivity. The functional analysis of a network identified the biological functions and/or diseases that were most significant to the genes in the network.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2i">
                <title>Statistical analyses</title>
                <p>All data are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Fisher's exact test was used to calculate a <italic>P</italic> value for the probability that each biological function and/or disease assigned to that network is due to chance alone. A value of <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s3a">
                <title>Cells, mRNA, and SMART™ cDNA analysis</title>
                <p>The growth status of ground control and 48A9 cells was the same as in our previous study<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Both the mRNA extracted from these cells and the cDNA generated were high quality according to typical band patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g001">Figure 1B and C</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="cjc-30-12-842-g001" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>The growth status of cells and the high quality mRNAs and cDNAs.</title>
                    <p>A, the images of ground control cells (a, c) and 48A9 cells (b, d). B, high integrity and purity of mRNAs. C, high quality cDNAs of ground control cells and 48A9 cells.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjc-30-12-842-g001"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3b">
                <title>PCR identification of SSH</title>
                <p>Though both the digested and undigested cDNA appeared smeared, the cDNA fragments generated by digestion with <italic>Rsa</italic> I were shorter than undigested cDNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Furthermore, comparing the intensity of PCR products amplified using one gene-specific primer (<italic>GAPDH</italic> 3′ primer) and PCR primer 1 with using two gene-specific primers (<italic>GAPDH</italic> 3′' primer and 5′ primer) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g002">Figure 2B</xref>), the ligation efficiency for the adaptors was greater than 50% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). Finally, the analysis of subtractive efficiency showed a reduction in the abundance of non-differentially expressed genes by SSH. <italic>GAPDH</italic> products could only be detected in the unsubtracted cDNA pool after 18 cycles of PCR amplification and in the subtracted cDNA pool after 28 cycles of PCR amplification, indicating a dramatic subtraction of commonly expressed genes in these samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g002">Figure 2C</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="cjc-30-12-842-g002" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Results of suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH).</title>
                    <p>A, analysis of <italic>Rsa</italic> I digestion. Lanes 1 and 3, SMART™ cDNA synthesis in ground control and 48A9 cells, respectively, before <italic>Rsa</italic> I digestion; lanes 2 and 4, SMART™ cDNA synthesis in ground control and 48A9 cells, respectively, after <italic>Rsa</italic> I digestion; M, DNA marker DL2000. B, reduction of <italic>GAPDH</italic> abundance by polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-select subtraction. PCR was performed on subtracted (18, 23, 28, 33 cycles) or unsubtracted (18, 23, 28, 33 cycles) secondary PCR products with the <italic>GAPDH</italic> 5′ and 3′ primers. Lane M, DNA marker DL2000. C and D, results of the ligation efficiency analysis. Lane 1, PCR products using Tester 1–1 (Adaptor 1–ligated) as the template and the <italic>GAPDH</italic> 3′ and 5′ primers. Lane 2, PCR products using Tester 1–1 (Adaptor 1–ligated) as the template, and the <italic>GAPDH</italic> 3′ primer and PCR primer 1. Lane 3, PCR products using Tester 1–2 (Adaptor 2R–ligated) as the template, and the <italic>GAPDH</italic> 3′ and 5′ primers. Lane 4, PCR products using Tester 1–2 (Adaptor 2R–ligated) as the template, and the <italic>GAPDH</italic> 3′ primer and PCR primer 1. Lane M, DNA marker DL2000.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjc-30-12-842-g002"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3c">
                <title>Construction and screen of a subtracted cDNA library</title>
                <p>Of thousands of colonies, 300 cDNA clones were randomly picked, and plasmids were isolated and amplified by PCR with nested primers. As a result, 288 positive clones had PCR products with a length from 200 to 1200 bp. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g003">Figure 3A</xref> shows cDNA fragments of different lengths amplified by PCR from the isolated clones. To eliminate the false positive cDNA clones, a total of 192 clones with inserts were analyzed by reverse Northern blotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g003">Figure 3B</xref>), and the differential cDNA clones were identified by calculating gray values of hybridization signals using NIH Image J software. The cDNA clones with ratio (gray value of 48A9 probe/ground control probe) &gt;2 were regarded as differentially expressed which represents the candidate genes up-regulated in 48A9 cells. At present, we have detected 12 cDNA clones expressed higher in 48A9 cells than in ground control cells.</p>
                <fig id="cjc-30-12-842-g003" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Construction and screening of a subtracted cDNA library.</title>
                    <p>A, cDNA fragments of different lengths from colonies amplified by PCR. Lanes, randomly selected clones; lane M, DNA marker DL2000. B, screening differentially expressed cDNA clones by reverse Northern blotting. cDNA clones randomly picked from the subtracted library were dotted onto two nylon membranes and hybridized separately with <sup>32</sup>P-labeled cDNA probes prepared from ground control cell cDNA (a, c) and from 48A9 cell cDNA (b, d). Differentially expressed clones were selected for sequence analysis</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjc-30-12-842-g003"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3d">
                <title>Sequencing, homology searching, and semi-quantitative PCR</title>
                <p>The genes identified in the 12 clones are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="cjc-30-12-842-t01">Table 1</xref>. Sequencing analysis revealed that 5 of the 12 clones matched known genes in the GenBank/EMBL database, and 3 were predicted genes. The other 4 clones did not match any entries in the GenBank/EMBL database and may represent novel genes. The results of semi-quantitative PCR further confirmed that expression of the 8 known and predicted genes was up-regulated in 48A9 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="cjc-30-12-842-t01" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Genes differentially expressed between 48A9 and ground control Caski cells by suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH)</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col width="66*" align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col width="71*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="114*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="114*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="114*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="114*" align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clone</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank number</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome location</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative ratio (48A9/control)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A2</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">762</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>SUB1</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM 006713.2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5p13.3</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A9</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>MT-C02</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_001807.4</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B1</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">580</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>MYL6</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_079423</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12q13.2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>MALAT-1</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR 002819.1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11q13.1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G6</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>SGEF</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_015595</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3q25.2</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B4</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New sequence</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT_005612.15</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B5</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1185</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New sequence</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RP11-96F15</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3p23</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C4</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">751</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New sequence</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RP11-95H14</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2q3</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="nt101">
                      <p>All Identified cDNA sequences are &gt;95% homologous to the known genes In the National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) blast search database.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="cjc-30-12-842-g004" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 4.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>The result of semi-quantitative PCR.</title>
                    <p>The lanes were <italic>GAPDH</italic> (internal control), <italic>MYL6</italic>, <italic>MT-CO2</italic>, <italic>B4</italic>, <italic>B5</italic>, <italic>SUB1</italic>, <italic>MALAT-1, C4</italic>, and SGEF genes, respectively. Compared to ground control cells, the expression levels of <italic>MYL6, MT-CO2, B4</italic>, <italic>B5</italic>, <italic>SUB1</italic>, <italic>MALAT-1</italic>, <italic>C4</italic>, and <italic>SGEF</italic> were up-regulated in 48A9 cells.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjc-30-12-842-g004"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3e">
                <title>Network and function analyses</title>
                <p>The IPA program was used to gain insight into the potential functional implications of the spaceflight-induced changes in gene translation profiles in 48A9 cells. Genes u p-regulated &gt;2.0 fold or down-regulated &lt;0.5 fold by microarray (<xref ref-type="table" rid="cjc-30-12-842-t02">Table 2</xref>) and up-regulated &gt;3.0 by SSH were chosen for analysis. Under these criteria, 37 molecules were eligible for generating networks, and 35 molecules were qualified for functional analyses. As summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="cjc-30-12-842-t03">Table 3</xref>, the two most significant networks identified by IPA were related to cancer, with a score of 64 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g005">Figure 5A</xref>), and cell morphology and cycle, with a score of 23 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). In addition, the top biological functions are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cjc-30-12-842-g005">Figure 5C</xref>. As expected for data derived from our previous study<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, the most represented functions in 48A9 cells were cell growth and proliferation (24 focus genes), cell morphology (13 focus genes), cell death (18 focus genes), and cancer (25 focus genes).</p>
                <table-wrap id="cjc-30-12-842-t02" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Genes differentially expressed between 48A9 and ground control Caski cells by microarray</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col width="48*" align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col width="186*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="60*" align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank accession</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cy5/Cy3 ratio</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001875</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens carbamoyl-phosphate synthetase 1, <italic>CPS1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0744</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006799</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens protease, serine 21, <italic>PRSS21</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0877</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005567</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens lectin, galactoside-binding, soluble, 3 binding protein, <italic>LGALS3BP</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1987</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002888</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens retinoic acid receptor responder 1, <italic>RARRES1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2108</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_080733</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens WAP four-disulfide core domain 2, <italic>WFDC2</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2673</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000636</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens superoxide dismutase 2, <italic>S0D2</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2963</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_003733</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens 2′-5′-oligoadenylate synthetase-like, <italic>OASL</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3394</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002447</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens macrophage stimulating 1 receptor, <italic>MST1R</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3663</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005564</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens lipocalin 2, <italic>LCN2</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3784</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_007192</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens suppressor of Ty 16 homolog, <italic>SUPT16H</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4219</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001252</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens tumor necrosis factor (ligand) superfamily, member 7, <italic>TNFSF7</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4314</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002213</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens integrin, beta 5, <italic>ITGB5</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4486</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_013282</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens ubiquitin-like, containing PHD and RING finger domains 1, <italic>UHRF1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4564</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001809</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens centromere protein A, <italic>CENPA</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4613</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006034</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens tumor protein p53 inducible protein 11</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4643</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006569</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens cell growth regulator with EF-hand domain 1, <italic>CGREF1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4747</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002466</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens v-myb myeloblastosis viral Oncogene homolog (avian)-like 2, <italic>MYBL2</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4835</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005956</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens formyltetrahydrofolate synthetase, <italic>MTHFD1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4939</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001254</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens CDC6 cell division cycle 6 homolog, <italic>CDC6</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4947</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002768</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens procollagen (type III) N-endopeptidase, <italic>PCOLN3</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0425</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002620</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens platelet factor 4 variant 1, <italic>PF4V1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0552</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002705</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens periplakin, <italic>PPL</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1058</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002414</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens CD99 antigen, <italic>MIC2</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1294</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_014599</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens melanoma antigen family D 2, <italic>MAGED2</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1429</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_003365</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens ubiquinol-cytochrome c reductase core protein I, <italic>UQCRC1</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1631</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000099</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens cystatin C, <italic>CST3</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1716</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000215</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens Janus kinase 3, <italic>JAK3</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1719</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_003982</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens solute carrier family 7 member 7, <italic>SLC7A7</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3386</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002051</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens GATA binding protein 3, <italic>GATA3</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4381</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000362</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens TIMP metallopeptidase inhibitor 3, <italic>TIMP3</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4918</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004103</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens PTK2B protein tyrosine kinase 2 beta, <italic>PTK2B</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4970</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001924</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible alpha, <italic>GADD45A</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6718</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_058242</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens keratin 6C, <italic>KRT6C</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0889</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001831</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens clusterin, <italic>CLU</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4840</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005009</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens non-metastatic cells 4, <italic>NME4</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7207</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000115</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homo sapiens endothelin receptor type B, <italic>EDNRB</italic></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1642</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="cjc-30-12-842-g005" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 5.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>The top-ranked networks and functions for 48A9 cells as defined by Ingenuity Pathways Analysis (IPA).</title>
                    <p>A, cancer network, with score 64. B, cell morphology and cycle network, with score 23. Red, up-regulated genes; green, down-regulated genes; white, genes for which no expression change was detected in 48A9 cells. C, the biological functions in 48A9 cells, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. ground control cells.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="cjc-30-12-842-g005"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="cjc-30-12-842-t03" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>The two most significant networks identified by the Ingenuity Pathways Analysis</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col width="17*" align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col width="253*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="38*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="53*" align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col width="110*" align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molecules In network</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of focus molecules</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Top functions</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr valign="top">
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Akt, CD70, CDC6, CHMP1A, CLU, CST3, Cyclin A, E2f, EDNRB, ERK, GADD45A, GATA3, hCG, Histoneh3, ITGB5, JAK3, Jnk, KRT6A, LCN2, MAGED2, MST1R, MTHFD1, MYBL2, NFkB, PDGFBB, PF4V1, PTK2B, RNA polymerase II, SLC7A7, SOD2, SUB1, SUPT16H, TCR, UHRF1, UQCRC1</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer, nephrosis, renal and urological disease</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr valign="top">
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OASL, PPL, PTPN11, RARRES1, RLN2, SGEF, SMPD1, TFAP2C, Timp, TIMP3, CTLA4, CTSH, ERBB2, HSD17B1, ICAM1, IFNG, IL1RN, LCN2, LGALS3BP, LRP8, MYBL2,NFkB, ACPP, ADAMTS5, ALDH1A7, C19ORF10, CD14, CENPA, CGREF1, COL5A1, COL6A1,Tnf receptor, TP53I11</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell morphology, cell cycle, embryonic development</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="nt102">
                      <p>All Identified cDNA sequences are &gt;95% homologous to the known genes In the National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) blast search database.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Here, we report that by using a sensitive subtraction method, we identified new spaceflight-inducible genes in cancer cells that were not identified by microarray. These genes included transcriptional co-activator <italic>SUB1, SGEF</italic>, <italic>MALAT-1</italic>, cytoskeleton relative gene <italic>MYL6</italic>, and mitochondrial metabolism gene <italic>MT-CO2</italic>, as well as three new putative genes with unknown function. Moreover, by utilizing the IPA program and combining our previous microarray data, we identified the two most significant functional networks impacted by spaceflight-induced gene changes—the cancer network and the cell morphology and cycle network. These networks, which include cell signaling pathways such as the stress-activated protein kinase/c-Jun NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal kinase (SAPK/JNK) pathway, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway, and Akt pathway, as well as cell signaling molecules such as nuclear factor–kappaB (NF-κB), interferon gamma (IFNG), histone H3, and intercellular adhesion molecule 1 (ICAM1), may play an important role in controlling cell growth and maintaining cell morphology in spaceflight. These results provide important clues for further study of the influence of spaceflight on gene expression and oncogenesis.</p>
              <sec id="s4a">
                <title><italic>SUB1</italic> and its potential functions in 48A9 cells</title>
                <p>The multifunctional human transcriptional co-activator SUB1 is a highly abundant nuclear protein that plays a key role in various cellular processes such as transcription, replication, chromatin organization, cellular transformation, and DNA damage repair<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>–<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Previously, studies showed that <italic>SUB1</italic> was involved in p53-dependent transcriptional regulation to repair DNA damage. Recently, SUB1 was found to play a direct role in the DNA double-stranded break (DSB) repair pathway through stimulation of DSB rejoining <italic>in vivo</italic><xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>,<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. High intensity ionizing radiation during spaceflight can damage DNA by directly interacting with DNA strands or indirectly promoting oxidative metabolism. Our study showed that SUB1 was highly expressed in 48A9 cells after spaceflight. Together, these findings suggest that <italic>SUB1</italic> may play an important role in maintaining cellular homeostasis in spaceflight.</p>
                <p>SUB1 maps to chromosome 5p13.3, a region frequently affected by loss of heterozygosity in bladder and lung tumors <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>,<xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. SUB1 can inhibit AP2 (activator protein 2) self-repression in a Ras-transformed cell line and act as a putative tumor suppressor<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Ras oncogene-transformed cell lines that stably expressed <italic>SUB1</italic> cDNA had a diminished growth rate and a loss of anchorage-independent growth ability, and they were also unable to induce tumor formation in nude mice. In addition, SUB1 acts as a unique activator of p53 by directly interacting with p53, activating p53-mediated DNA binding, and inducing p53-responsive gene expression<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>–<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Thereby, SUB1 plays an important role in the inhibition of tumorigenesis through interaction with p53. In our present study, <italic>SUB1</italic> was highly expressed in 48A9 cells compared with ground control cells, and thus, SUB1 may be an important molecule in the change of biological function of 48A9 cells.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4b">
                <title><italic>SGEF</italic> and its potential functions in 48A9 cells exposed to spaceflight</title>
                <p>SGEF is a Rho GEF with unclear function. It was initially discovered in a screening for androgen-responsive genes in human prostate, and two alternatively transcribed forms of <italic>SGEF</italic> gene were isolated. One encodes the full-length molecule of 871 amino acids, and the other encodes a splice-variant of 139 amino acids that contains only a small part of the pleckstrin homology (PH) domain and the entire SH3 domain<xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. In addition, using an affinity-purified antibody of SGEF, a research group recently observed a variable presence of smaller immunoreactive proteins (90, 80, and 75 kDa) in a number of cell lines<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. These smaller proteins probably reflect that <italic>SGEF</italic> RNA is alternatively spliced to produce protein isoforms of varying functionality as described for the closely related exchange factor Rho guanine nucleotide exchange factor 5 (ARHGEF5)<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p>
                <p>The Rho GEFs activate Rho GTPases by displacing GDP from GDP-bound Rho GTPases and allowing GTP binding. Then, the activated Rho GTPases interact with downstream molecules to play an important role in the regulation of several aspects of cellular function, including cytoskeletal organization, apoptosis, gene expression, cell cycle progression, and membrane trafficking<xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>–<xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. RhoG, a Rho GTPase, has been reported to play a key role in controlling cell survival and apoptosis by activating the Akt pathway and JNK pathway, respectively<xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, in addition to its common roles as a Rho GTPase. In a recent study, SGEF was found to activate RhoG <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic><xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. As a putative Rho GEF, we predict that SGEF influences cell morphology, cell apoptosis, and cell cycle through the regulation of RhoG.</p>
                <p>Interestingly, a group recently identified a pathway downstream from ICAM1 involving RhoG and its exchange factor SGEF that led to endothelial apical cup formation and promoted leukocyte trans-endothelial migration (TEM)<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. In that study, ICAM1 bound to the SH3 domain of SGEF through the proline-rich region inside the cell. This interaction was independent of SGEF activation because catalytically inactive mutants of SGEF that expressed the SH3 domain still bound ICAM1. However, engagement of ICAM1 increased the activation of SGEF, as judged by increased binding of SGEF to nucleotide-free RhoG. In addition, previous studies have identified that spaceflight influenced the expression and Spacial structure of ICAM1<xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>–<xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Together, all these findings suggest that the pathway of ICAM1, SGEF, and RhoG possibly plays a key role in controlling cell morphology, cell survival, cell cycle, and gene expression during spaceflight.</p>
                <p><italic>SGEF</italic> mRNA was expressed at low levels in some breast and prostate cancer cell lines detected by Northern blot analysis<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. In our study, <italic>SGEF</italic> mRNA expression was not detected in normal Caski cancer cells but was highly expressed in 48A9 subclonal Caski cells. Combined with the findings from our previous study<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, this discovery may suggest that SGEF plays an important role in inhibiting oncogenesis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4c">
                <title><italic>MALAT-1</italic> and its potential functions in 48A9 cells exposed to spaceflight</title>
                <p><italic>MALAT-1</italic>, a long non-coding RNA, is encoded by a gene locus located on human chromosome 11q13, where chromosomal aberrations associated with tumorigenesis and metastasis have long been observed. Moreover, some studies recently indicated that expression of the <italic>MALAT-1</italic> gene was increased in many human carcinomas and suggested a significant role for <italic>MALAT-1</italic> in the molecular events of oncogenesis <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>–<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. We found the expression level of <italic>MALAT-1</italic> was higher in 48A9 cells than in ground control cells. Therefore, further study should be undertaken to investigate whether <italic>MALAT-1</italic> acts as a tumor activator or tumor suppressor.</p>
                <p>Among three new cDNAs or ESTs of unknown function, <italic>B4</italic> and <italic>B5</italic> were located on chromosome 3 and <italic>C4</italic> was located on chromosome 2. All three were highly expressed in 48A9 cells but not in ground control cells. Previous studies have indicated that the deletion of chromosome 3p is a common event in many cancers, including lung cancer, nasopharyngeal carcinoma, bladder cancer, and esophageal squamous cell carcinoma, suggesting that multiple tumor suppressor genes are present on chromosome 3p<xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>–<xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. To date, many candidate tumor suppressor genes at 3p have been reported, including Von Hippel-Lindau 3 (<italic>VHL3</italic>) at 3p25, retinoic acid receptor-beta (<italic>RAR-β</italic>) at 3p24, fragile histidine triad (<italic>FHIT</italic>) at 3p14.2, and Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family member 1 (<italic>RASSF1A</italic>), calcium channel, voltage-dependent, alpha 2/delta subunit 2 (<italic>CACNA2D2</italic>), and deleted in liver cancer 1 (<italic>DLC1</italic>) at 3p21.3<xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>–<xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. These findings suggest that our new clone <italic>B5</italic> on 3p23 may be a novel tumor suppressor gene.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s5">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>The work described in the present study aimed to identify the causes of biological changes after spaceflight in cancer cells, expecting to find some new tumor suppressors. Though we have found genes and potential pathways impacted by spaceflight, there is a future challenge to establish their contributions to the associated biological changes. To our knowledge, our experiments are the first to show that spaceflight can reduce the growth of tumor cells and to provide a new model to study oncogenesis using a space environment.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>This project has been supported in part by grants from the National Nature Science Foundation of China (No. 30672352) and the 973 pre-major national basic research projects in China (No. CA04200).</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="conflict">
                <p><bold>Competing Interests:</bold> The authors of this study have no conflict of interest or any financial disclosures to make.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allen</surname>
                      <given-names>DL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bandstra</surname>
                      <given-names>ER</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harrison</surname>
                      <given-names>BC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of spaceflight on murine skeletal muscle gene expression [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Physiol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>106</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>582</fpage>
                  <lpage>895</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074574</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bascove</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huin-Schohn</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guéguinou</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spaceflight-associated changes in immunoglobulin VH gene expression in the amphibian Pleurodeles waltl [J]</article-title>
                  <source>FASEB J</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>1607</fpage>
                  <lpage>1615</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19141535</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gridley</surname>
                      <given-names>DS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Slater</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luo-Owen</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spaceflight effects on T lymphocyte distribution, function and gene expression [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Appl Physiol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>106</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <lpage>202</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18988762</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ou</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Long</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spaceflight induces both transient and heritable alterations in DNA methylation and gene expression in rice (Oryza sativa L.) [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mutat Res</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>662</volume>
                  <issue>1–2</issue>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135069</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salmi</surname>
                      <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roux</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gene expression changes induced by space flight in single-cells of the fern Ceratopteris richardii [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Planta</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>229</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <lpage>159</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18807069</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>ZJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of space flight exposure on cell growth, tumorigenicity and gene expression in cancer cells [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Space Res</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1898</fpage>
                  <lpage>1905</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hillmann</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dunne</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kenny</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>cDNA amplification by SMART-PCR and suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH)-PCR [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>496</volume>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <lpage>243</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18839114</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cao</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Epstein</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparing gene discovery from Affymetrix GeneChip microarrays and Clontech PCR-select cDNA subtraction: a case study [J]</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Genomics</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15113399</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diatchenko</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lukyanov</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>YF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Suppression subtractive hybridization: a versatile method for identifying differentially expressed genes [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Methods Enzymol</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>303</volume>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <lpage>380</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10349654</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Das</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hizume</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batta</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transcriptional coactivator PC4, a chromatin-associated protein, induces chromatin condensation [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>22</issue>
                  <fpage>8303</fpage>
                  <lpage>8315</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16982701</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>JY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarker</surname>
                      <given-names>AH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cooper</surname>
                      <given-names>PK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The single-strand DNA binding activity of human PC4 prevents mutagenesis and killing by oxidative DNA damage [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>13</issue>
                  <fpage>6084</fpage>
                  <lpage>6093</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15199162</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pan</surname>
                      <given-names>ZQ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ge</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amin</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transcription-positive cofactor 4 forms complexes with HSSB (RPA) on single-stranded DNA and influences HSSB-dependent enzymatic synthesis of simian virus 40 DNA [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>271</volume>
                  <issue>36</issue>
                  <fpage>22111</fpage>
                  <lpage>22116</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8703021</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ge</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roeder</surname>
                      <given-names>RG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Purification, cloning, and characterization of a human coactivator, PC4, that mediates transcriptional activation of class II genes [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Cell</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
                  <lpage>523</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8062391</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batta</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yokokawa</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takeyasu</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Human transcriptional coactivator PC4 stimulates DNA end joining and activates DSB repair activity [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Mol Biol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>385</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>788</fpage>
                  <lpage>799</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038270</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mortusewicz</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roth</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardoso</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recruitment of RNA polymerase II cofactor PC4 to DNA damage sites [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>183</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>769</fpage>
                  <lpage>776</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19047459</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohm</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirch</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otto</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Deletion analysis at the DEL-27, APC and MTS1 loci in bladder cancer: LOH at the DEL-27 locus on 5p13-12 is a prognostic marker of tumor progression [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Cancer</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>74</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <lpage>295</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9221807</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wieland</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohm</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arden</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Allelic deletion mapping on chromosome 5 in human carcinomas [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Oncogen</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <lpage>102</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kannan</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tainsky</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Coactivator PC4 mediates AP-2 transcriptional activity and suppresses ras-induced transformation dependent on AP-2 transcriptional interference [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>899</fpage>
                  <lpage>908</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858613</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kishore</surname>
                      <given-names>AH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batta</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Das</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>p53 regulates its own activator: transcriptional co-activator PC4, a new p53-responsive gene [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Biochem J</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>406</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
                  <lpage>444</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555406</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batta</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kundu</surname>
                      <given-names>TK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Activation of p53 function by human transcriptional coactivator PC4: role of protein-protein interaction, DNA bending, and Posttranslational modifications [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>21</issue>
                  <fpage>7603</fpage>
                  <lpage>7614</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17785449</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kundu</surname>
                      <given-names>TK</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>General transcriptional coactivator PC4 activates p53 function [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>2052</fpage>
                  <lpage>2062</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14966284</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qi</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fournier</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grenier</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Isolation of the novel human guanine nucleotide exchange factor Src homology 3 domain-containing guanine nucleotide exchange factor (SGEF) and of C-terminal SGEF, an N-terminally truncated form of SGEF, the expression of which is regulated by androgen in prostate cancer cells [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Endocrinology</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>144</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>1742</fpage>
                  <lpage>1752</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12697679</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ellerbroek</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wennerberg</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arthur</surname>
                      <given-names>WT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>SGEF, a RhoG guanine nucleotide exchange factor that stimulates macropinocytosis [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>3309</fpage>
                  <lpage>3319</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15133129</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Debily</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Camarca</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ciullo</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Expression and molecular characterization of alternative transcripts of the ARHGEF5/TIM Oncogene specific for human breast cancer [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <lpage>334</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662653</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahai</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marshall</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>RHO-GTPases and cancer [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <lpage>142</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12635176</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Etienne-Manneville</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hall</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rho GTPases in cell biology [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>420</volume>
                  <issue>6916</issue>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
                  <lpage>635</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12478284</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hall</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rho GTPases and the actin cytoskeleton [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>279</volume>
                  <issue>5350</issue>
                  <fpage>509</fpage>
                  <lpage>514</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9438836</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Aelst</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>D'Souza-Schorey</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rho GTPases and signaling networks [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Genes Dev</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>18</issue>
                  <fpage>2295</fpage>
                  <lpage>2322</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9308960</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Murga</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zohar</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teramoto</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rac1 and RhoG promote cell survival by the activation of PI3K and Akt, independently of their ability to stimulate JNK and NF-kappaB [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Oncogene</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <lpage>216</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11803464</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Buul</surname>
                      <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allingha</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samson</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>RhoG regulates endothelial apical cup assembly downstream from ICAM1 engagement and is involved in leukocyte trans-endothelial migration [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Cell Biol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>178</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1279</fpage>
                  <lpage>1293</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17875742</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buravkova</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Romanov</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rykova</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cell-to-cell interactions in changed gravity: ground-based and flight experiments [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Astronaut</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <issue>2–8</issue>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <lpage>74</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16010753</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>CK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chung</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>YY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Monocyte adhesion to endothelial cells increases with hind-limb unloading in rats [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Aviat Space Environ Med</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>76</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>720</fpage>
                  <lpage>725</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16110686</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mills</surname>
                      <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Perez</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adler</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of spaceflight on adrenergic receptors and agonists and cell adhesion molecule expression [J]</article-title>
                  <source>J Neuroimmunol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>132</volume>
                  <issue>1–2</issue>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <lpage>179</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417448</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b34">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maeda</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A large noncoding RNA is a marker for murine hepatocellular carcinomas and a spectrum of human carcinomas [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Oncogene</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>851</fpage>
                  <lpage>858</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16878148</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ji</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diederichs</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MALAT-1, a novel noncoding RNA, and thymosin beta4 predict metastasis and survival in early-stage non-small cell lung cancer [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Oncogene</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>39</issue>
                  <fpage>8031</fpage>
                  <lpage>8041</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970751</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamada</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kano</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsunoda</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Phenotypic characterization of endometrial stromal sarcoma of the uterus [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Cancer Sci</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <lpage>112</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16441420</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guo</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis of genetic alterations in primary nasopharyngeal carcinoma by comparative genomic hybridization [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <lpage>260</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11170282</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b38">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hurst</surname>
                      <given-names>CD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fiegler</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carr</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>High-resolution analysis of genomic copy number alterations in bladder cancer by microarray-based comparative genomic hybridization [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Oncogene</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>2250</fpage>
                  <lpage>2263</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14968109</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b39">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qin</surname>
                      <given-names>YR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sham</surname>
                      <given-names>PC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Single-nucleotide polymorphism-mass array reveals commonly deleted regions at 3p22 and 3p14.2 associate with poor clinical outcome in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Cancer</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>123</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>826</fpage>
                  <lpage>830</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18508313</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b40">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tai</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yan</surname>
                      <given-names>WS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recurrent chromosomal imbalances in nonsmall cell lung carcinoma: the association between 1q amplification and tumor recurrence [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Cancer</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>100</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1918</fpage>
                  <lpage>1927</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15112273</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b41">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daigo</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiwaki</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kawasoe</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Molecular cloning of a candidate tumor suppressor gene, DLC1, from chromosome 3p21.3 [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Cancer Res</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>59</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>1966</fpage>
                  <lpage>1972</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10213508</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b42">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dammann</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yoon</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epigenetic inactivation of a RAS association domain family protein from the lung tumour suppressor locus 3p21.3 [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Genet</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <lpage>319</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10888881</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b43">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>de The</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vivanco-Ruiz</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tiollais</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Identification of a retinoic acid responsive element in the retinoic acid receptor beta gene [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>343</volume>
                  <issue>6254</issue>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <lpage>180</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2153268</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b44">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ji</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishizaki</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Expression of several genes in the human chromosome 3p21.3 homozygous deletion region by an adenovirus vector results in tumor suppressor activities in vitro and in vivo [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Cancer Res</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>2715</fpage>
                  <lpage>2720</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11980673</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b45">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Latif</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tory</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gnarra</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Identification of the von Hippel-Lindau disease tumor suppressor gene [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>260</volume>
                  <issue>5112</issue>
                  <fpage>1317</fpage>
                  <lpage>1320</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8493574</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b46">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ohta</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inoue</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cotticelli</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The FHIT gene, spanning the chromosome 3p14.2 fragile site and renal carcinoma-associated t(3;8) breakpoint, is abnormal in digestive tract cancers [J]</article-title>
                  <source>Cell</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>84</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>587</fpage>
                  <lpage>597</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8598045</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
