<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T18:00:05Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5681589" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5681589</identifier>
        <datestamp>2017-11-16</datestamp>
        <setSpec>npjmicrogr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Microgravity</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Microgravity</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>NPJ Microgravity</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2373-8065</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5681589</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5681589</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5681589</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29147680</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">32</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41526-017-0032-x</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Coculture of meniscus cells and mesenchymal stem cells in simulated microgravity</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Weiss</surname>
                    <given-names>William M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mulet-Sierra</surname>
                    <given-names>Aillette</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kunze</surname>
                    <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jomha</surname>
                    <given-names>Nadr M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1798-6251</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Adesida</surname>
                    <given-names>Adetola B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <phone>+1 780 492 3219</phone>
                    <email>adesida@ualberta.ca</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17089.37</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Stem Cell Biology and Orthopaedic Tissue Engineering, Department of Surgery, </institution><institution>University of Alberta, Li Ka Shing Centre for Health Research Innovation, </institution></institution-wrap>Edmonton, AB Canada </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2179 3554</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.416992.1</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthopedic Surgery and Rehabilitation, Sports Medicine, Reconstruction and Trauma, </institution><institution>Texas Tech University Health Sciences Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Lubbock, TX USA </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2017</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2017</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2017</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>3</volume>
              <elocation-id>28</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>17</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="OpenAccess">
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <p id="Par1">Simulated microgravity has been shown to enhance cartilaginous matrix formation by chondrocytes and chondrogenesis of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs). Similarly, coculture of primary chondrocytes with MSCs has been shown as a strategy to simultaneously retain the differentiated phenotype of chondrocytes and enhance cartilaginous matrix formation. In this study, we investigated the effect of simulated microgravity on cocultures of primary human meniscus cells and adipose-derived MSCs. We used biochemical, qPCR, and immunofluorescence assays to conduct our investigation. Simulated microgravity significantly enhanced cartilaginous matrix formation in cocultures of primary meniscus cells and adipose-derived MSCs. The enhancement was accompanied by increased hypertrophic differentiation markers, <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>MMP-13</italic>, and suppression of hypertrophic differentiation inhibitor, gremlin 1 (<italic>GREM1</italic>).</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="LongSummary">
                <title>Cartilage: Simulated microgravity promotes cartilage matrix deposition</title>
                <p id="Par2">Co-culture of meniscal cartilage-forming cells with fat-derived stem cells can lead to enhanced cartilage matrix production when cultured under simulated microgravity. Adetola Adesida from the University of Alberta in Edmonton, Canada, and colleagues cultured two types of cells found together in the knee—cartilage-forming chondrocyte cells (taken from the meniscus) and mesenchymal stem cells (isolated from the infrapatellar fat pad)—in a rotary cell culture system designed to model weightlessness on Earth. Simulated microgravity enhanced the synergistic interaction between the two types of cells in culture, resulting in more matrix production, but it also prompted the cartilage-forming cells to differentiate towards bone-forming cells, as evidenced by gene expression analysis. These findings suggest that microgravity and simulated microgravity-based culture technologies could help bioengineers grow knee replacements for people with meniscus tears, but increased bone-directed differentiation could pose a possible problem for astronauts on prolonged missions.</p>
              </abstract>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par3">The menisci of the knee are a pair of fibrocartilaginous tissues.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> They primarily serve as mechanical load distributors within the knee joint.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> Traumatic tears in the avascular region of the tissue are common and do not heal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> Treatment options for these tears are currently limited to partial meniscectomy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> However, partial meniscectomy is a major risk factor for the early development of knee osteoarthritis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> Tissue engineering using cells presents a potential option to create functional tissues to replace damaged meniscus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> Primary meniscus cells (MC) are the ideal cell sources as they closely resemble the in vivo phenotype of MC and can form the biomechanically functional extracellular matrix (ECM) of the meniscus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> Obtaining sufficient numbers of primary MC for meniscus tissue engineering is often impossible and impractical.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> To circumvent this limitation, primary MC are expanded in in vitro culture. However, expanded MC suffer from dedifferentiation and loss of the functional matrix-forming phenotype of native MC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> Supplementation of primary MC through direct coculture with bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) has been demonstrated as a strategy to retain the differentiated phenotype of primary MC with the additional benefits of synergistic production of the functional matrix components of the meniscus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and downregulation of hypertrophic differentiation of MSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> However, the use of bone marrow MSCs potentially presents another anatomical site other than the knee for MSCs harvest. Supplementation of primary MC with knee infrapatellar fat pad derived MSCs may be a better anatomical option.</p>
              <p id="Par4">The differentiation of multiple types of MSCs is influenced by a wide range of biochemical,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> microenvironmental,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and mechanical factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> TGF-β1 and TGF-β3, members of the TGF-β superfamily, that promote fibro-chondrogenic differentiation of MSCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> and production of meniscus-like ECM. Diverse types of mechanical stimuli, including compressive load,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> simulated microgravity (SMG),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> low-intensity pulsed ultrasound,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> and hydrostatic pressure has been reported to induce or regulate the differentiation of MSCs through TGF-β signaling pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> Hypoxia stimulated chondrogenic differentiation of bone marrow-derived MSCs by induction of TGF-β1 gene expression and protein production.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>
</p>
              <p id="Par5">The rotary cell culture system (RCCS) bioreactor, developed by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), as a tool to simulate microgravity has been shown to provide a relatively well-defined fluid dynamic environment with efficient mass transfer for nutrients and gases and low shear stress for tissue growth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> RCCS has been reported to produce hydrodynamic forces supporting the development of tissue structures resembling cartilage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> and meniscus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> Simulated microgravity facilitated the retention of the differentiated phenotype of chondrocytes within 3D porous scaffolds.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> Moreover, RCCS synergistically enhanced TGF-β1-mediated chondrogenesis of human adipose-derived MSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> However, to the best of our knowledge, no studies has investigated the effect of SMG on TGF-β-mediated chondrogenesis in cocultures of primary human MC and infrapatellar fat pad-derived MSCs.</p>
              <p id="Par6">In the present study, primary human MC were cocultured with infrapatellar fat pad-derived MSCs on a 3D porous collagen scaffold in the presence of TGF-β3, and cultured under SMG using the RCCS bioreactor. The goals of the present study were (a) to investigate the effect of SMG on human MC, (b) to determine the effect of SMG on the interaction of MC and MSCs in coculture and (c) to assess the potential benefit of using SMG to tissue engineer meniscus constructs in 3D porous type I collagen scaffolds. We hypothesized that SMG will augment the synergistic interaction between primary human MC and MSCs, and result in increased matrix production with suppression of hypertrophic differentiation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Colony forming characteristics and immuno-phenotype of adipose stem cells (ASC)</title>
                <p id="Par7">A proportion of the seeded adipose tissue-derived mononucleated cells (MNCs) formed plastic adherent cell populations with distinct colonies. The developed colonies stained with crystal violet (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Microscopic visuals of the colonies revealed cells with fibroblastic morphologies characteristics of plastic adherent MSCs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). We determined the clonogenicity of the MNCs to be 10.65 ± 4.15% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). The adherent cell populations were positive for the panel of cell surface markers characteristic of MSCs;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> CD13, CD29, CD44, CD73, CD90, CD105, and CD151 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Their relative mean fluorescence intensities (MFI) ± SD are as in the parentheses: CD13 (29.26 ± 10.79), CD29 (2.83 ± 0.35), CD44 (6.40 ± 2.40), CD73 (8.63 ± 3.79), CD90 (113.62 ± 14.90), CD105 (1.87 ± 0.05), and CD151 (8.57 ± 0.16)—Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>. The proportion (%) of cells that were positive for these markers varied considerably; CD13 (99.67 ± 0.15), CD29 (93.18 ± 3.26), CD44 (98.06 ± 0.08), CD73 (99.67 ± 0.09), CD90 (90.97 ± 8.86), CD105 (57.94 ± 11.38), and CD151 (98.86 ± 0.16), an indication of heterogeneity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>). In contrast to the MFI associated with mesenchymal markers, the cells displayed lower MFIs for markers of hematopoietic lineage; CD34 (1.29 ± 0.02) and CD45 (1.92 ± 0.50). The proportion (%) of cells that were positive for CD34 and CD45 were 4.93 ± 0.39 and 3.16 ± 1.10, respectively. Interestingly, the cells had a low MFI (0.73 ± 0.52) for the C-X-C chemokine receptor type 4 (CXCR-4) also known as CD184, which has been reported to be expressed on synovial fluid-derived MSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> The proportion of CD184<sup>+</sup> cells was 1.29 ± 0.05%.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Colony-forming unit fibroblastic characteristic and surface marker phenotype of fat pad-derived cells following tissue culture plastic adherent culture expansion. <bold>a</bold> A digital photograph of a CFU-F assay Petri dish after staining with crystal violet. <bold>b</bold> Representative photomicrographs of adherent cells from a 40-year-old male at passage (P0). <bold>c</bold> Proportion (%) of total fat pad-derived MNCs seeded forming cell colonies (% clonogenicity). <bold>d</bold> Surface marker phenotype of fat pad-derived adherent cells following culture expansion until passage 2 (P2). For each CD marker tested, solid histograms show negative isotype control; open histograms show CD marker expression. <bold>e</bold> Represents the mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of two donors. <bold>f</bold> Proportion of positive (%) cells expressing tested CD markers</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e465"/></fig>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Fluorescent-labeled cells reveal coculture of primary MC and ASC</title>
                <p id="Par8">Pure ASC and pure MC were labeled successfully with cell membrane fluorescent dyes PKH26 (red; Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>) and PKH67 (green; Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), respectively. Pure ASC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>), pure MC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>), and cocultured cells at 25% MC and 75% ASC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>) retained their respective fluorescent dyes after 4 weeks of chondrogenic culture in type I collagen matrix scaffolds. This aspect of the study was performed only under static conditions.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Fluorescence photomicrographs of PKH26 and PKH67 labeled cells in monolayer and in three-dimensional (3D) porous scaffolds. <bold>a</bold> Representative fluorescence photomicrograph of passage 2 (P2) fat pad-derived plastic adherent cells labeled with PKH26 (red) cell membrane dye (male, 19 years old). Cells were labeled in suspension and imaged after 30 min of plating in monolayer. <bold>b</bold> Representative fluorescence photomicrograph of primary human meniscus cells labeled with PKH67 (green) cell membrane dye (male, 56 years old). Cells were labeled in suspension and imaged after 30 min of plating in monolayer. <bold>c</bold> Representative fluorescence photomicrograph of passage 2 (P2) fat pad-derived plastic adherent cells (<italic>ASC</italic>) labeled with PKH26 (red) cell membrane dye (male, 19 years old) after 3 weeks of chondrogenic culture in porous type I collagen scaffold. Cells were visualized after sectioning at 7 μm and additional staining with DAPI for cell nuclei identification. <bold>d</bold> Representative fluorescence photomicrograph of primary human meniscus cells (<italic>MC</italic>) labeled with PKH67 (green) cell membrane dye (male, 56 years old) after 3 weeks of chondrogenic culture in porous type I collagen scaffold under static condition. Cells were visualized after sectioning at 7 μm and additional staining with DAPI for cell nuclei identification. <bold>e</bold> Representative fluorescence photomicrograph of cocultured primary human meniscus cells (<italic>MC</italic>) labeled with PKH67 (green) and passage 2 (P2) fat pad-derived plastic adherent cells (<italic>ASC</italic>) labeled with PKH26 (red) after 3 weeks of chondrogenic culture in porous type I collagen scaffold under static conditions. The cells were premixed at a cell ratio of 25% MC and 75% ASC prior to seeding a total of 250,000 cells per type I collagen scaffold. Cells were visualized after sectioning at 7 μm and additional staining with DAPI for cell nuclei identification. Scale bars: A and B (200 μm) and C–E (100 μm)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e524"/></fig>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Chondro-induction is enhanced in SMG cocultures of primary MC and ASC</title>
                <p id="Par9">Cell-seeded scaffold constructs of pure MC, pure ASC, and cocultures of MC and ASC were cultured in serum-free chondrogenic media for up to 28 days in the presence of TGF-β3 under static or SMG conditions. Qualitative histological analysis of the constructs with safranin O staining demonstrated intense positive glycosaminoglycan (GAG) staining after the 28 days of culture under static and SMG conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). All groups were intensely positive for safranin O and nuclei content, an indication of significant synthesis and deposition of sulfated GAG matrix in the constructs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a–h</xref>). However, the deposition of GAG matrix appears to be more homogenously distributed in the constructs cultured under SMG (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e–h</xref>). Except for pure MC constructs, the characteristic phenotype of hypertrophic chondrocytes of enlarged size/lacunae was evident in groups containing ASC. Quantitative analysis for the GAG contents of the constructs via DMB assay demonstrated that GAG contents were higher in constructs containing cocultured cells regardless of whether the constructs were cultured under static or SMG conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). The constructs formed under static conditions from the coculture of 25% MC and 75% ASC had a measured GAG content of 195.25 ± 38.73 μg (mean ± SD) compared to an expected GAG content of 148.50 ± 38.36 μg. Wilcoxon signed rank pairwise comparison test between the measured and expected GAG quantities confirmed a significantly higher measured GAG content than the expected values (<italic>p</italic> = 0.003; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Similarly, there were significant differences between the measured and expected GAG content of cocultured constructs containing 25% MC and 75% ASC after culture under SMG. The SMG cultured constructs had a measured GAG content of 279.39 ± 124.09 μg relative to an expected GAG content of 167.78 ± 75.39 μg. Pairwise comparison test using Wilcoxon signed rank test revealed a significant difference between the measured and expected GAG values (<italic>p</italic> = 0.003; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). After static culture, the constructs containing 50% MC and 50% ASC had a measured GAG content of 190.53 ± 47.84 μg. The expected GAG values for these constructs were 172.21 ± 54.80 μg. However, there was no significant difference between the measured and expected GAG values as per Wilcoxon signed rank test (<italic>p</italic> = 0.109; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). In contrast, after SMG culture, the constructs containing 50% MC and 50% ASC measured a significantly different GAG content of 251.63 ± 121.92 μg compared to an expected GAG content of 173.04 ± 62.29. The <italic>p-</italic>value for the pairwise comparison was 0.026 as per Wilcoxon signed rank test (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Histological Safranin O staining after chondrogenic stimulation and differentiation of primary human meniscus cells and fat pad-derived adipose stem cells in porous type I collagen scaffolds. Representative safranin O staining of cell-scaffold constructs after 4 weeks of culture in a defined serum-free chondrogenic medium containing transforming growth factor-β3 (TGFβ3) and dexamethasone (DEX) under <italic>static</italic>
<bold>a–d</bold> and <italic>simulated microgravity</italic>
<bold>e–h</bold> conditions: <bold>a, e</bold> pure primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years); <bold>b, f</bold> Passage 2 (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years)<bold>; c, g</bold> Coculture of 75% (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years) with 25% primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years); <bold>d, h</bold> Coculture of 50% (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years) with 50% primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years). Scale bar 100 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e602"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The interaction between primary human meniscus cells and fat pad-derived adipose stem cells on type I collagen scaffold after chondrogenic stimulation under static and simulate microgravity (SMG) conditions. Values are mean ± SD of four independent experiments. Expected GAG values are indicated with an “Exp.” prefix. The following symbols: *, <sup>≠</sup> and <sup>¥</sup> indicates statistically significant differences between expected and measured GAG values of cocultured group MC/ASC. <bold>a</bold> *Exp. SMG 25%/75% vs. SMG 25%/75%, <sup>≠</sup>Exp. SMG 50%/50% vs. SMG 50%/50%, <sup>¥</sup>Exp. Static 25%/75% vs. Static 25%/75%. <bold>b</bold> Interaction index values were determined from the ratio of measured and expected GAG as per the definition in section “Materials and methods”. Symbols *and <sup>≠</sup> indicate Wilcoxon signed rank test determined significant differences between the interaction indices of static and simulated microgravity (SMG) cocultured groups; *SMG 25%/75% vs. Static 25%/75% and <sup>≠</sup>SMG 50%/50% vs. Static 50%/50%. <bold>c</bold> DNA contents of all groups after static and simulated microgravity culture conditions. Symbols * and <sup>¥</sup> indicate a paired one-tailed Student’s t-test (with unequal variance) statistically significant difference between the DNA contents of static and simulated microgravity (SMG) groups: *SMG 100% MC vs. static 100% MC, and <sup>¥</sup>SMG 50%/50% vs. static 50%/50%</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e646"/></fig>
</p>
                <p id="Par10">After calculating the interaction index as a ratio of the measured and expected GAG contents of the constructs containing cocultured cells, we confirmed that the interaction indices were greater than 1, signifying that chondro-induction had occurred (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Shapiro Wilk test for normality of data distribution proved positive. The Levene’s test was significant and lacked homogeneity of variances. For cocultured cells at 25% MC and 75% ASC, the interaction index was 1.35 ± 0.16 after culture under static conditions and 1.72 ± 0.39 after culture under SMG (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Paired one-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic> test (with unequal variance) comparison of the interaction indices revealed a significantly higher chondro-induction under SMG conditions (<italic>p</italic> = 0.006; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). For cocultured cells at 50% MC and 50% ASC ratio, the interaction index was 1.16 ± 0.14 after static culture and 1.49 ± 0.44 after SMG culture. Similarly, the level of chondro-induction after SMG culture conditions was significantly higher (<italic>p</italic> = 0.022; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Simulated microgravity increases DNA content in MC and cocultures</title>
                <p id="Par11">We next explored the possibility that cell proliferation may accompany the enhanced chondro-induction in cocultures of MC and ASCs after culture under SMG. Shapiro Wilk test for DNA content distribution proved to be normal. However, the Levene’s test for homogeneity of data variance proved negative. To that end, a paired one-tailed Student <italic>t</italic> test with unequal variance was used to assess differences between parallel static and SMG groups. First, we compared the DNA contents of constructs containing pure MC and pure ASC after static culture and SMG culture conditions. The DNA content of constructs containing pure MCs was 4.53 ± 0.81 µg after SMG culture compared to 3.73 ± 0.63 µg after static culture. These values were significantly different (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). In contrast, the DNA content of constructs containing pure ASCs after static culture and SMG culture approached significant difference (<italic>p</italic> = 0.05). The DNA contents of pure ASC containing constructs after static culture and SMG culture were 3.35 ± 0.56 µg and 2.67 ± 0.84 µg, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). The constructs containing 25%MC and 75% ASC had a DNA content of 5.46 ± 2.11 µg after SMG culture and 4.20 ± 0.57 µg after static culture. These values were not significantly different (<italic>p</italic> = 0.08) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). In contrast, constructs containing 50% MC and 50% ASC were significantly different (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03) in DNA contents after static culture and SMG culture. The constructs had a DNA content of 5.33 ± 1.49 µg after SMG culture and those after static culture had a DNA content of 4.06 ± 0.41 µg (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Effect of SMG on gene expression of chondrogenically stimulated MC, ASC, and cocultures of MC and ASCs</title>
                <p id="Par12">We used quantitative polymearse chain reaction (qPCR) to investigate the gene expression of chondrogenically stimulated MC, ASC and cocultures of MC and ASCs after static and SMG culture conditions. Data followed normal distribution as assessed by Shapiro Wilk test. However, the Levene’ assessment of error variance proved highly significant. To this end, pairwise comparison between gene expression data of static and SMG cultured constructs were performed using paired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test with unequal variance.</p>
                <p id="Par13">SMG enhanced the mRNA expression of <italic>ACAN</italic> by 1.9-fold in pure MCs (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0002; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). SMG increased the mRNA expression of <italic>ACAN</italic> by 2.2-fold in pure ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.036; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). SMG enhanced the expression of <italic>ACAN</italic> by 2.4-fold in cocultures of 25% MC and 75% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0001; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). Similarly, SMG enhanced the mRNA expression of <italic>ACAN</italic> by 3.6-fold in 50% MC and 50% ASC cocultures (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). In contrast, the mRNA expression of <italic>COL1A2</italic> remained unperturbed between static and SMG cultured groups; no fold changes in <italic>COL1A2</italic> expression were observed. The insignificant differences in the treatment groups were supported by <italic>p-</italic>values &gt; 0.05 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). SMG increased the expression of <italic>COL2A1</italic> in pure MC, pure ASC, and in the cocultures of these cells. However, the fold increase observed were not statistically significant; SMG increased <italic>COL2A1</italic> mRNA expression by: 1.2-fold in pure MC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.28), 1.7-fold in pure ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.16), 1.4-fold in cocultures of 25% MC and 75% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.06), and 1.2-fold in cocultures of 50% MC and 50% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.21). Qualitative immunofluorescence detection confirmed the translation of these collagen genes in the constructs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). All groups were positive for type I and II collagen. No notable differences were evident in the deposition of these collagens between static culture and SMG culture conditions. All constructs treated with secondary antibodies only proved negative for the type I and II collagen (data not shown).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Gene expression of primary human meniscus cells, fat pad-derived adipose mesenchymal stem cells and cocultured cells under static and simulated microgravity culture conditions. Symbols *, <sup>≠</sup>, <sup>¥</sup> and <sup>§</sup> indicate a paired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test (one-tailed; unequal variance) statistically significant differences between the interaction indices of static and simulated microgravity (SMG) cocultured groups; *SMG 100% MC vs. static 100% MC, <sup>≠</sup>SMG 100% ASC vs. static 100% ASC, <sup>¥</sup>SMG 25%/75% vs. static 25%/75% and <sup>§</sup>SMG 50%/50% vs. static 50%/50%. <bold>a</bold>
<italic>ACAN</italic>, <bold>b</bold>
<italic>COL1A2</italic>, <bold>c</bold>
<italic>COL2A1</italic>, <bold>d</bold>
<italic>SOX9</italic>, <bold>e</bold>
<italic>COL10A1</italic> and <bold>f</bold>
<italic>GREM1</italic>. <bold>g</bold> Relative gene expression of <italic>COL10A1</italic> was plotted against the relative gene expression of <italic>GREM1</italic>. Pearson correlation analysis was used to assess the relationship between <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>GREM1</italic>. <bold>h</bold>
<italic>MMP-13</italic>. <bold>i</bold> Relative gene expression of <italic>MMP-13</italic> was plotted against the relative gene expression of <italic>GREM1</italic>. Pearson correlation analysis was used to assess the relationship between <italic>MMP-13</italic> and <italic>GREM1</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e890"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Immunofluorescence of types I and II collagen after chondrogenic stimulation and differentiation of primary human meniscus cells and fat pad-derived adipose stem cells in porous type I collagen scaffolds. Representative immunofluorescence of cell-scaffold constructs after 4 weeks of culture in a defined serum-free chondrogenic medium containing transforming growth factor-β3 (TGFβ3) and dexamethasone (DEX) under <italic>static</italic>
<bold>a–d</bold> and <italic>simulated microgravity</italic>
<bold>e–h</bold> conditions: <bold>a, e</bold> pure primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years); <bold>b, f</bold> Passage 2 (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years)<bold>; c, g</bold> coculture of 75% (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years) with 25% primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years); <bold>d, h</bold> Coculture of 50% (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years) with 50% primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years). Scale bar 100 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e926"/></fig>
</p>
                <p id="Par14">Interestingly, SMG significantly downregulated the mRNA expression of <italic>SOX9</italic> in pure MCs by 3.3-fold (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>). Similarly, SMG downregulated the expression of <italic>SOX9</italic> in pure ASCs and in cocultures of 25% MC and 75% ASC but not in coculture of 50% cells where a moderate increase of 1.2-fold was observed. These modulations in <italic>SOX9</italic> gene expression were not statistically significant with <italic>p-</italic>values &gt;0.05.</p>
                <p id="Par15">SMG significantly enhanced the mRNA expression of the hypertrophic differentiation marker, <italic>COL10A1</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>). The increase was two-fold in pure MC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.008), 7.8-fold in pure ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03), 4.6-fold in cocultures of 25% MC and 75% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0009), and 2.7-fold in cocultures of 50% MC and 50% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01). We evaluated the gene expression of established inhibitor of hypertrophic differentiation, gremlin 1 (<italic>GREM1</italic>), to provide some mechanistic insight into the noted SMG-mediated upregulation of <italic>COL10A1</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>). SMG downregulated the mRNA level of <italic>GREM1</italic> by two-fold (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02) in pure MC but not significantly in pure ASC (1.4-fold; <italic>p</italic> = 0.17). SMG significantly downregulated <italic>GREM1</italic> expression by 3.9-fold in cocultures of 25% MC and 75% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.009), and by 12.4-fold in 50% MC and 50% ASC cocultures (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0001). Moreover, the mRNA expression of <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>GREM1</italic> inversely correlated as assessed by Pearson correlation coefficient (−0.166). The correlation was not statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> = 0.100; one-tailed; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g</xref>). In an analogous manner to collagen X, SMG increased the mRNA expression of <italic>MMP-13</italic>, another marker of hypertrophic differentiation of chondrocytes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5h</xref>). It significantly increased the expression of <italic>MMP-13</italic>: in pure MC by five-fold (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0001), in pure ASC by five-fold (<italic>p</italic> = 1.78548 × 10<sup>−6</sup>), 3.7-fold in cocultures of 25% MC and 75% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0003), and 2.1-fold in coculture of 50% MC and 50% ASC (<italic>p</italic> = 0.008). Pearson correlation demonstrated a highly significant inverse relationship between the expression of <italic>GREM1</italic> and <italic>MMP-13</italic> (<italic>r = </italic>−0.305; <italic>p</italic> = 0.006; one-tailed; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5i</xref>).</p>
                <p id="Par16">We used immunofluorescence to confirm the translation of collagen X in the constructs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Static culture of pure MC appears to have the least deposition of collagen X in the ECM (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). In contrast, the ECM of the pure MC after SMG culture appears to be more positive for type X collagen epitope (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7e</xref>). Similarly, SMG culture of pure ASC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7f</xref>) appears to be more positive for type X collagen epitope than its static culture counterpart (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). Interestingly, in the cocultured constructs containing MC and ASC, the epitope of type X collagen was strikingly evident around structures (indicated by white arrows) characterized by a hypertrophic phenotype due to their enlarged size and lacunae-like appearance (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c, d, g and h</xref>). These structures appear to be larger after SMG culture (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7g</xref>) relative to static culture (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>), when MC and ASC cocultures are at a ratio of 25–75%, respectively. However, it is interesting to note that the presence of type X collagen epitope around the lacunae-like structures appear to be less evident in SMG cocultures of 50% MC and 50% ASC, but more so in the extracellular space (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7h</xref>) compared to their static cocultured counterparts (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7d</xref>). All constructs treated with secondary antibodies only proved negative for the type I and II collagen (data not shown).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Immunofluorescence of type X collagen after chondrogenic stimulation and differentiation of primary human meniscus cells and fat pad-derived adipose stem cells in porous type I collagen scaffolds. Representative immunofluorescence of cell-scaffold constructs after 4 weeks of culture in a defined serum-free chondrogenic medium containing transforming growth factor-β3 (TGFβ3) and dexamethasone (DEX) under <italic>static</italic>
<bold>a–d</bold> and <italic>simulated microgravity</italic>
<bold>e–h</bold> conditions: <bold>a, e</bold> pure primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years); <bold>b, f</bold> Passage 2 (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years)<bold>; c, g</bold> coculture of 75% (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years) with 25% primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years); <bold>d, h</bold> coculture of 50% (P2) fat pad-derived adipose stem cells (ASC; male, 19 years) with 50% primary human meniscus cells (MCs; male, 56 years). Lacunae-like structures are indicated by white arrows. Scale bar 500 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1118"/></fig>
</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par17">The functional matrix of the knee meniscus is central to its biomechanical functionality within the joint. Generation of functional meniscus constructs, via tissue engineering and regenerative medicine strategies with a suitable cell source has the potential to revolutionize the treatment of avascular meniscus injuries, which do not heal. Avascular meniscus injuries account for most of meniscal lesions necessitating partial meniscectomies, which unfortunately predisposes the knee to early onset of osteoarthritis. Naturally, primary human MC are the optimal cell source for the generation of functional meniscal substitutes; however, limited availability from surgical specimen of partial meniscectomies is a drawback. Cell expansion strategies to increase numbers mitigate the expression of the functional matrix genes of the meniscus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> To this end, direct coculture of primary human MC with adult-derived MSCs has been explored,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> to emulate the synergistic synthesis (i.e. chondro-induction) of the functional matrix of cartilage after coculture of primary articular or nasal chondrocytes with bone marrow or adipose MSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> Simulated microgravity has been shown to synergistically enhance the synthesis of the functional matrix of articular cartilage in chondrocyte seeded polymeric scaffolds.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> Moreover, SMG synergistically enhanced the chondrogenic differentiation of adipose MSCs in the presence of TGFβ1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> These reported findings prompted us to ask the following question: can SMG further augment chondro-induction in direct cocultures of primary human MC and adipose MSCs? We hypothesized that SMG will further enhance chondro-induction in primary human MC and adipose MSCs in the presence of TGFβ.</p>
              <p id="Par18">To investigate the hypothesis, human cells: adipose-derived MSCs and MC were successfully isolated from knee fat pad and menisci, respectively. Direct coculture of these cells in a 3D porous type I collagen matrix scaffolds, as a mimic of the predominant ECM of the native meniscus, was successfully demonstrated using differential fluorescent cell labeling. After 4 weeks of chondrogenic culture in the presence of TGFβ3, both pure cells and cocultured cells synthesized cartilaginous ECM under static and SMG.</p>
              <p id="Par19">Our study findings supported our hypothesis with evidence of GAG and <italic>ACAN</italic> increase. Moreover, SMG increased the DNA content of constructs containing pure MCs and cocultured MCs and ASCs. This was not the case in constructs containing pure ASCs. This finding suggested that the mechanism underlying SMG enhanced chondro-induction may involve increased proliferation of MC. Increased proliferation of chondrocytes in coculture with MSCs has also been reported previously as a mechanistic component of chondro-induction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> An unexpected finding was the accompaniment of the microgravity enhanced chondro-induction with increased transcription of <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>MMP-13</italic>, markers for hypertrophic chondrocytes and hypertrophic differentiation of MSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> Previous work had demonstrated that direct coculture of primary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> or early passage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> human MC with MSCs suppressed hypertrophic differentiation of MSCs. The mechanism underlying this unexpected finding appears to be associated with the downregulation of <italic>GREM1</italic>, a known inhibitor/antagonist of hypertrophic differentiation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> Parametric Pearson’s correlation coefficient was used to determine the strength of the association between <italic>GREM1</italic> and two hypertrophic markers: <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>MMP-13</italic>. Our assessment revealed an inverse correlation (<italic>r</italic> = −0.166) between <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>GREM1</italic>, albeit with a non-significant <italic>p</italic> value. There was a highly significant inverse correlation (<italic>r</italic> = −0.305, <italic>p</italic> = 0.006) between the expression of <italic>MMP-13</italic> and <italic>GREM1</italic>. The potential of increased hypertrophic differentiation through <italic>GREM1</italic> downregulation suggests a potential risk for enhanced bone formation in vivo through endochondral ossification pathway; conditional deletion of <italic>GREM1</italic> caused a transient increase in bone formation and bone mass.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> With that in mind, it is unclear at this point if outer and inner MC will behave differently in their capacity to modulate the expression of <italic>GREM1</italic> under SMG. Our previous work demonstrated that outer primary human MC have a greater capacity to suppress <italic>COL10A1</italic> and <italic>MMP-13</italic> expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> However, the study was conducted under static conditions using the cell pellet model of in vitro chondrogenesis. One may speculate that the bulk of primary human MC in this study may have originated from the inner region of the meniscus, since the inner portion of the tissue accounts for two-thirds of the meniscus’ width.</p>
              <p id="Par20">Our finding of increased <italic>COL10A1</italic> expression in pure adipose-derived MSCs under SMG is consistent with the reports of Yu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> The authors demonstrated that SMG enhanced the in vitro chondrogenesis of adipose-derived MSCs in the presence of TGFβ1 but with increased <italic>COL10A1</italic> mRNA expression. They also demonstrated that SB203580, a highly specific and potent inhibitor of p38 mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPK) signaling pathway, significantly suppressed the mRNA expression of <italic>COL10A1</italic> during SMG culture conditions, suggesting that p38 MAPK was a significant player in the transduction of physical forces mediated by SMG. Thus, activation of p38 MAPK signaling may be an additional underlying mechanism contributing to the synergistic chondro-induction in our study under SMG. It is noteworthy that while Yu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> reported an increase in <italic>COL2A1</italic> and <italic>SOX9</italic> under SMG, we did not observe a significant increase in the expression of these genes under SMG. But our findings on <italic>ACAN</italic> and <italic>COL10A1</italic> transcriptional increase under SMG were consistent with the findings of Yu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>
</p>
              <p id="Par21">In summary, the present study demonstrated that SMG enhanced the chondro-induction in cocultures of primary human MC and adipose-derived mesenchymal stem but at the cost of increased hypertrophic differentiation that is concomitant with <italic>GREM1</italic> downregulation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Ethics statement</title>
                <p id="Par22">Approval of the Health Research Ethics Board-Biomedical Panel of the University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada was obtained for this study, and institutional safety and ethical guidelines were followed. Ethics committee waived the need for written informed consent of patients, as specimens used in the study were intended for discard in the normal course of the surgical procedure. Extensive precautions were taken to preserve the privacy of the participants donating specimens.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Isolation of primary human MC</title>
                <p id="Par23">Menisci were harvested from the knee joint of five donors: three males (14, 56, and 56) and two females (age 57 and 75), rinsed three times with sterile phosphate buffered saline (PBS), and finely minced. Donor information is documented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. MC were released from meniscus pieces by incubation for 16 hours at 37 °C in type II collagenase (0.15% w/v of 300 units/mg solid; Worthington, Lakewood, NJ, USA) in a standard medium, high glucose Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) 4.5 mg/ml <sc>d</sc>-glucose supplemented with 5% v/v fetal bovine serum (FBS), 100 units/ml penicillin and 100 units/ml streptomycin, with <sc>l</sc>-glutamine (2 mM) (Invitrogen, Mississauga, Ontario, Canada), then filtered through a 150-µm nylon mesh to remove cellular debris, as described previously. Isolated cells were plated in standard medium supplemented in 150 cm<sup>2</sup> tissue culture plastic (TCP) at 37 °C and 21% O<sub>2</sub> in a humidified incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After 48 h of recovery in standard medium, the cells were detached with 0.15% w/v trypsin-EDTA in Hank’s buffered saline solution (HBSS; Invitrogen) and counted prior to use.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Isolation of human adipose stem cells</title>
                <p id="Par24">Patellar fat pads were harvested from the knee joint of five donors undergoing routine orthopedic procedure; three males (age 17, 19 and 40) and two females (age 20 and 21). Donor information is documented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. The adipose tissue was rinsed three times with PBS, and finely minced before enzymatic digestion. Tissue was digested with type II collagenase (0.15% w/v of 300 units/mg solid; Worthington) in PBS at 37 °C using a water bath shaker at 150 rpm for 45 minutes. Nucleated cells were re-suspended in alpha modified Eagle’s medium (αMEM) supplemented with 10% v/v FBS, and 1% w/v antibiotic/antimycotic solution filtered through a 100 μm nylon mesh to remove cellular debris. The number of nucleated cells in the aspirates was determined by crystal violet nuclei staining with cell counting using a hemocytometer. Thereafter, 15 million mono-nucleated cells (MNCs) were seeded per 150 cm<sup>2</sup> TCP. The culture medium was αMEM supplemented with 10% v/v FBS, penicillin–streptomycin, 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethanesulfonic acid (HEPES), sodium pyruvate (all from Invitrogen) and 5 ng/ml basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF or FGF2; from Humanzyme, Medicorp Inc., Montreal, Quebec, Canada) to maintain multipotency.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> The cells were cultured until passage 2 (P2) at 37 °C under 95% humidity in an atmosphere of 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec13">
                <title>Colony-forming unit fibroblastic (CFU-F) assay</title>
                <p id="Par25">A CFU-F assay was performed to determine the proportion of plastic-adherent cells from adipose-derived MNCs. MNCs from each donor were plated in triplicates at 500 MNCs per 100 mm diameter sterile Petri dish (Becton Dickinson Canada Inc.) and cultured for expansion as described above at 37 °C under 95% humidity in an atmosphere of 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After the first week, the non-adherent cell population was removed by aspiration and culture media was replenished twice for another week. After the 2 weeks of culture, the culture media was aspirated and the Petri dish was washed with sterile PBS, then fixed with 10% w/v buffered formalin for 5 minutes. The formalin was aspirated and the Petri dish was washed twice with PBS, and stained with 0.25% w/v crystal violet solution (Sigma-Aldrich). Stained colonies were revealed after washing with a copious amount of distilled water. Each stained cell collection was assessed and considered to be a colony as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> The number of colonies developed from the total number of MNC seeded was used to calculate clonogenicity (%), with each colony representing a single cell-derived clone.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec14">
                <title>Flow cytometry analysis</title>
                <p id="Par26">All primary monoclonal antibodies used herein were directly conjugated antibodies to fluorescein isothiocynate (mAb-FITC) or to phycoerythrin (mAb-PE). Antibodies were either from BD Pharmingen or Invitrogen—see Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The cells were analyzed on a FACScan flow cytometer (Becton Dickinson) after detachment from culture flask by 0.05% w/v trypsin-EDTA (Invitrogen). Staining buffer was prepared with PBS containing 1% w/v BSA (Sigma). The cells were re-suspended in 4 °C cold staining buffer at 5 × 10<sup>6</sup>/ml. Thereafter, the cells were dispensed into sample tubes (12 × 75 mm polystyrene round-bottom tubes, Becton Dickinson) in 20 µl aliquots and incubated for15 minutes with the antibodies at 4 °C. All incubations were implemented in 5 ml dilution tubes at room temperature in the dark and all washing steps were performed by a combination of centrifugation (400 g, 5 minutes) and aspiration of supernatant. Staining buffer (200 µl) was then added to the tubes and cells were incubated for 10 additional minutes. After removal of the supernatant by centrifugation, cells were washed with PBS and kept cold before analysis by flow cytometry. Non-specific staining was assessed using relevant isotype controls. Single color immuno-fluorescence analysis for the different surface markers was performed with mAb-FITC and mAb-PE. Data acquisition was performed with Cellquest software (Becton Dickinson). FITC emission was measured at FL1 and PE at FL3. For each sample a region for live cells was defined, according to the Forward Scatter (FSC) and Side Scatter (SSC) signals, which excluded aggregated cells from the analysis. Data analysis was performed with Cyflogic version 1.2.1, Perthu Terho &amp; CyFlo Ltd., Finland. For each surface marker analyzed, percentage of positive cells and the level of marker expression were calculated. Percentage of positive cells was calculated as the percentage of cells having a measured fluorescence greater than that of 99.5% of the cells stained with each associated isotype control. Cells were considered positive for a surface marker when the percentage of positive cells for that surface marker was ≥6%. The level of expression of each marker was calculated as the ratio between geometric mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of samples and that of the isotype control.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Antibodies used to characterize infrapatellar fat pad mesenchymal stem cells</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Specificity</th><th>Isotype*</th><th>Cat.#/Flurochrome</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CD13 (aminopeptidase-n)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>sc-70529/PE</td><td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td></tr><tr><td>CD29</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>CD2901/FITC</td><td>Invitrogen</td></tr><tr><td>CD34</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>sc-19621/FITC</td><td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td></tr><tr><td>CD44 (Pgp-1, H-CAM, Ly 24)</td><td>mIgG2b</td><td>560977/FITC</td><td>BD Pharmingen</td></tr><tr><td>CD45 (2B11)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>Sc-20056/PE</td><td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td></tr><tr><td>CD73</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>550257/PE</td><td>BD Pharmingen</td></tr><tr><td>CD90 (Thy-1)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>55596/PE</td><td>BD Pharmingen</td></tr><tr><td>CD105 (endoglin)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>sc-71043/PE</td><td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td></tr><tr><td>CD151 (PETA-3)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>556057/PE</td><td>BD Pharmingen</td></tr><tr><td>CD184 (CXCR4)</td><td>mIgG2a</td><td>560937/PE-CyTM5</td><td>BD Pharmingen</td></tr><tr><td>Not specified (Isotype control)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>sc-2855/FITC</td><td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td></tr><tr><td>Not specified (Isotype control)</td><td>mIgG1</td><td>sc-2866/PE</td><td>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*m, mouse; r, rat</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Donor information of meniscal (MEN/ NMEN) and patellar fat pad (ASC) specimen</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Donor</th><th>Age (years)</th><th>Gender (M/F)</th><th>Weight (kg)</th><th>Height (cm)</th><th>Smoker? (Y/N)</th><th>Medical history/surgery reason</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>MEN155</td><td>56</td><td>M</td><td>140</td><td>186</td><td>N</td><td>Osteoarthritis</td></tr><tr><td>MEN159</td><td>75</td><td>F</td><td>93</td><td>155</td><td>N</td><td>No anticancer drug use/osteoarthritis</td></tr><tr><td>MEN161</td><td>56</td><td>M</td><td>66</td><td>168</td><td>Y</td><td>No anticancer drug use/osteoarthritis</td></tr><tr><td>MEN172</td><td>57</td><td>F</td><td>96</td><td>151</td><td>N</td><td>Osteoarthritis</td></tr><tr><td>NMEN190</td><td>14</td><td>M</td><td>65</td><td>175</td><td>N</td><td>Partial meniscectomy</td></tr><tr><td>ASC64</td><td>20</td><td>F</td><td>–</td><td>–</td><td>–</td><td>Mitral valve prolapse/knee injury</td></tr><tr><td>ASC68</td><td>19</td><td>M</td><td>69.5</td><td>173</td><td>–</td><td>Healthy/meniscal &amp; ACL repair</td></tr><tr><td>ASC67</td><td>17</td><td>M</td><td>79.5</td><td>185</td><td>N</td><td>Knee joint injury</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">ASC70</td><td rowspan="2">21</td><td rowspan="2">F</td><td rowspan="2">71</td><td rowspan="2">161</td><td rowspan="2">Y</td><td>Allergy to nickel, asthma</td></tr><tr><td>Knee repair</td></tr><tr><td>ASC97</td><td>40</td><td>M</td><td>88.9</td><td>180</td><td>Y</td><td>Multiple ligament &amp; knee injury</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec15">
                <title>Type I collagen scaffold constructs</title>
                <p id="Par27">Type I collagen matrix (Integra Lifesciences, PlainsBoro, NJ, USA; 10 cm × 12.5 cm; 3.5 mm total thickness collagen sponge with pore size of 115 ± 20 µm) was cut into 6 mm diameter disks using a sterile biopsy punch. To limit variability between batches of scaffolds, disks taken from the same batch of scaffolds were used for each experiment. The disks were placed in a 24-well plate for seeding with cells.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec16">
                <title>Co-culture of MCs and ASCs</title>
                <p id="Par28">Cells were co-cultured in 25%:75% and 50%:50% ratios of MCs to ASCs, in addition to controls of each cell type alone. MCs and ASCs were sex matched, but obtained from different donors. After counting, cells were combined in the required ratios, and were carefully seeded on the Type I collagen scaffold via a micropipette with a total of 250,000 cells suspended in 20 µl of a defined serum-free chondrogenic medium consisting of high glucose DMEM containing 0.1 mM non-essential amino acids, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 100 mM HEPES buffer, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 100 U/ml penicillin, 100 mg/ml streptomycin, 0.29 mg/ml <sc>l</sc>-glutamine (Invitrogen) supplemented with 0.1 mM ascorbic acid 2-phosphate, 40 mg/ml <sc>l</sc>-proline, 10<sup>−7</sup> M dexamethasone, 1 × ITS + 1 premix (Sigma-Aldrich, Oakville, Canada), 10 ng/ml TGF-β3 (Humanzyme-Medicorp Inc.). The seeded disks were transferred to a humidified incubator at 37 °C with 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 15 minutes to allow initial cell attachment. Thereafter, 100 µl of chondrogenic medium was gently added to the base of each well containing cell-seeded disks followed by a 30 minutes incubation period in a humidified incubator at 37 °C with 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After the incubation period, 700 µl of chondrogenic medium was added slowly to the base of each well until the entire seeded scaffolds were covered. The seeded scaffolds were then incubated at 37 °C with 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 7 days. Chondrogenic media exchange was performed twice per week.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec17">
                <title>Co-culture of fluorescently labeled MCs and ASCs</title>
                <p id="Par29">To demonstrate co-culture of MCs and ASCs, isolated MCs and ASCs were labeled with fluorescent dyes in suspension according to manufacturer’s labeling protocol. Pure MCs were labeled with PKH67 (green) and pure ASCs were labeled with PKH26 (red). The labeled cells were visualized in monolayer after plating in a T25 TCP flask using an Eclipse Ti–S microscope (Nikon Canada Mississauga, Canada) fitted with NIS Elements (version 4.20; Nikon Canada). PKH67 and PKH26 fluorescent cell linker kits were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Oakville, Canada). The labeled cells were seeded onto type I collagen matrix scaffolds as described above. Culture media, conditions, and duration were as described above but only static culture was implemented to demonstrate co-culture of labeled cells. Cells were mixed at a ratio of 25% MC and 75% ASC prior to seeding on type I collagen matrix scaffold. Cell-scaffold constructs were cultured in chondrogenic medium as before for 28 days. Thereafter, the cultured constructs were embedded in a VWR clear frozen section compound (VWR, Mississauga, ON, Canada). Engineered tissue sections were cut on a Leica Biosystems cryostat at 7 µm. Images were captured as before and assembled in Image J version 1.51k software (NIH, Bethesda, Maryland, USA).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec18">
                <title>Culture in SMG</title>
                <p id="Par30">After 7 days of culture, one set of cell co-culture on type I collagen scaffolds (MC alone, ASC alone, 1:3 MC to ASC, and 1:1 MC to ASC) were transferred to 10 mL vessels and inserted into a rotary bioreactor RCCS (Synthecon, Inc., Houston, TX). An identical set of co-cultures was used as a control, and continued to be incubated under static conditions. The rotary bioreactor was housed within the same incubator as the static controls, and both continued to be cultured in a humidified incubator at 37 °C with 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The rotation speed of the RCCS increased from 20 to 30 rpm over the course of 21 days of culture. This increase in rotation speed was required to keep the increasing mass of the scaffolds suspended under microgravity conditions. After 21 days of culture in the rotary bioreactor (28 days total from seeding of the scaffolds), the culture scaffolds were harvested and analyzed. Scaffolds were processed biochemically for GAG and DNA content, histologically and immunofluorescence for cartilage-specific matrix proteins, and at the molecular level by real time qPCR for gene expression analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec19">
                <title>Biochemical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par31">After culture, scaffolds were rinsed in PBS (Invitrogen), and frozen at −80 °C. For analysis, samples were digested in proteinase K (1 mg/ml in 50 mM Tris with 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM iodoacetamide and 10 mg/ml pepstatin A—all from Sigma-Aldrich) for 16 h at 56 °C. The sulphated GAG content was measured by 1,9 dimethylmethylene blue (DMB) binding (Sigma-Aldrich) using chondroitin sulfate (Sigma-Aldrich) as standard. The DNA content was determined using the CyQuant cell proliferation assay kit (Invitrogen) with supplied bacteriophage λ DNA as standard. Chondro-induction is defined as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> Based on experimentally measured GAG contents of pure MC seeded scaffolds (GAG<sub>100% MCs</sub>) and pure ASC seeded scaffolds (GAG<sub>100% ASC</sub>), the expected total GAG (GAG<sub>expected</sub>) in the coculture cell-seeded scaffolds was calculated as a linear function of the proportion (%) of MC using the following equation:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\mathrm{GAG}}_{{\rm{expected}}} = {\rm{GAG}}_{100{\rm{\% }}\,{\rm{MC}}} + \left( {{\rm{GAG}}_{100{\rm{\% }}\,{\rm{MC}}}-{\rm{GAG}}_{100{\rm{\% }}\,{\rm{ASC}}}} \right) \times {\rm{\% }}\,{\rm{MC}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GAG</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">expected</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GAG</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">MC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GAG</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">MC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GAG</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ASC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">MC</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41526_2017_32_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="Par32">The interaction index was then calculated as the ratio of the GAG measured in the cocultured cell-seeded scaffolds (GAG<sub>measured</sub>) to the GAG<sub>expected</sub>. When the interaction index is higher than 1, then chondro-induction is considered to have occurred.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec20">
                <title>Histology and immuno-histochemistry</title>
                <p id="Par33">Tissues generated from the scaffold-cell cultures were fixed in 4% v/v phosphate buffered formalin, processed into paraffin wax, sectioned at 5 µm and stained with safranin O and counterstained with fast green, to reveal sulfated proteoglycan (GAG) matrix depositions. Other sections were probed with antibodies raised against collagen types I and II. The distribution of types I and II collagen were evaluated using immunofluorescence imaging. Sections were deparaffinized and rehydrated. Antigen retrieval was conducted with Protease XXV (Thermo Scientific) for 30 minutes at room temperature and hyaluronidase (H6254, Sigma) for 30 min at 37 °C. Sections were then blocked with 5% w/v bovine serum albumin in PBS for 30 minutes at room temperature. Collagen I, II and X labeling was completed using rabbit anti-collagen I, 1:200 dilution (CL50111AP-1, Cedarlane Labs, Burlington, ON, Canada), mouse anti-collagen II, 1:200 dilution (II-II6B3, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, University of Iowa, USA) and rabbit anti-collagen X (ab58632, Abcam, UK) using a 1:100 dilution, respectively, and incubated overnight at 4 °C. Secondary labeling using goat anti-mouse IgG, Alexa Fluor 488, 1:200 (ab150117, Abcam) and goat anti-rabbit IgG, Alexa Fluor 594, 1:200 (ab150080, Abcam) incubated at room temperature for 1 hour. Slides were mounted using Everbrite Hardset Mounting Medium with DAPI (Biotium) and imaged using a Nikon Ti–S Microscope fitted with DS-U3/Fi2 Color CCD camera using FITC and Texas Red filters (Nikon Canada Mississauga, Canada) with NIS Elements software (version 4.20; Nikon Canada) and assembled in Image J version 1.51k software (NIH, Bethesda, Maryland, USA).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec21">
                <title>Gene expression analysis</title>
                <p id="Par34">Total RNA was extracted from MCs, ASCs, and scaffold cultures using Trizol (Invitrogen) after grinding with Molecular Grinding Resin (Geno Technology Inc., St Louis, USA) in combination with the use of RNeasy mini-kit (Qiagen, Mississauga, ON, Canada) and after removal of contaminating genomic DNA from the preparations with DNase treatment. Total RNA (100 ng) in a 40 µl reaction was reverse transcribed to cDNA using GoScript reverse transcriptase (Fisher Scientific, Whitby, Ontario, Canada) primed with random primer oligonucleotides. qPCR was performed either in a DNA Engine OpticonIContinuous Fluorescence Detection System (Bio-Rad) using hot start Taq and SYBR Green detection (Eurogentec North America Inc, San Diego, CA, USA) or in a Bio-Rad CFX connect real-time system (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Mississauga, ON, Canada). Primer sequences were either designed by Primer Express 3.0.1 (Applied Biosystems, ThermoFisher, ON, Canada) or taken from previously published work. All primers were obtained from Invitrogen, Mississauga, ON, Canada. Gene (mRNA) expression levels for each primer set were normalized to the expression level of human βactin, by the 2-<sup>ΔΔct</sup> method. Primer sequence are as follows: <italic>ACAN</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (Accession# M55172) forward: AGG GCG AGT GGA ATG ATG TT; <italic>ACAN</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> reverse: GGT GGC TGT GCC CTT TTT AC; <italic>ACTB</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (Accession# NM_001101) forward AAG CCA CCC CAC TTC TCT CTA A; <italic>ACTB</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> reverse AAT GCT ATC ACC TCC CCT GTG T; <italic>COL1A2</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (NM_000089) forward: TTG CCC AAA GTT GTC CTC TTC T; <italic>COL1A2</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> reverse: AGC TTC TGT GGA ACC ATG GAA; <italic>COL2A1</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (Accession# NM_033150) forward CTG CAA AAT AAA ATC TCG GTG TTC T; <italic>COL2A1</italic> reverse: GGG CAT TTG ACT CAC ACC AGT; <italic>COL10A1</italic> (Accession# X60382) forward: GAA GTT ATA ATT TAC ACT GAG GGT TTC AAA; <italic>COL10A1</italic> reverse: GAG GCA CAG CTT AAA AGT TTT AAA CA; <italic>GREM-1</italic> (Accession# NM_001191322.1) forward: CAT GTG ACG GAG CGC AAA TA; <italic>GREM-1</italic> reverse: GCT TAA GCG GCT GGG TTT T; <italic>MMP13</italic> (Accession# NM_002427) forward: CATCCAAAAACGCCAGACAA; <italic>MMP13</italic> reverse: CGGAGACTGGTAATGGCATCA; <italic>SOX9</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> (Accession# Z46629) forward: CTT TGG TTT GTG TTC GTG TTT TG; <italic>SOX9</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> reverse: AGA GAA AGA AAA AGG GAA AGG TAA GTT T.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec22">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par35">A total of five independent experiments were performed with five donor specimens for each cell type. Unless stated otherwise, numerical data distribution represents data from five donors and is presented as a boxplot of the minimum, first quartile, median, third quartile, and maximum values. Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS (version 23; IBM Canada Ltd, ON, Canada). Outliers were defined as values 1.5 interquartile ranges below the first quartile or above the third quartile. Data were assessed for normality using the Shapiro–Wilk test. Levene’s test was used to assess homogeneity of error variances. Statistical test choice was dependent on outcome of normality and homogeneity test. Paired comparisons between static and SMG groups was analyzed using either Wilcoxon signed rank test or paired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test depending on outcome of normality test. Pearson or Spearman correlation coefficient was used to assess correlation between genes. Statistical significance was considered when <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec23">
                <title>Data availability</title>
                <p id="Par36">All relevant data are available from the corresponding author.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Financial support was provided by Canadian Institutes for Health Research (CIHR MOP 125921), Canadian Foundation for Innovation (CFI 33786), University of Alberta Hospital Foundation (RES0028185) and Edmonton Orthopedic Research Committee (GS22000020). In-kind donation of type I collagen scaffolds was provided by Integra LifeSciences Inc., Plainsboro, NJ, USA.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>W.M.W. was involved in study design, performed cell culture, experimental assays, data acquisition, and initial manuscript writing. A.M.S. performed cell isolation, cell culture, experimental assays and data acquisition. M.K. performed gene expression assays and associated data analysis. N.M.J. was responsible for specimen procurement and was involved in manuscript writing. A.B.A. conceived the study, supervised the study, performed data and statistical analysis and was responsible for writing of the final manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
              <sec id="FPar1">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par37">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
              </sec>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makris</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hadidi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Athanasiou</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The knee meniscus: structure-function, pathophysiology, current repair techniques, and prospects for regeneration</article-title>
                  <source>Biomaterials</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>7411</fpage>
                  <lpage>7431</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2011.06.037</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21764438?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21764438</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andrews</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adesida</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abusara</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shrive</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Current concepts on structure-function relationships in the menisci</article-title>
                  <source>Connect. Tissue Res.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28267400?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28267400</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roos</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title><italic>Knee osteoarthritis after</italic> meniscectomy: Prevalence of radiographic changes after twenty-one years, compared with matched controls</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <fpage>687</fpage>
                  <lpage>693</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1529-0131(199804)41:4&lt;687::AID-ART16&gt;3.0.CO;2-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9550478?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9550478</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McDermott</surname>
                      <given-names>ID</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amis</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The consequences of meniscectomy</article-title>
                  <source>J. Bone Jt. Surg. Br.</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <fpage>1549</fpage>
                  <lpage>1556</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.88B12.18140</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sweigart</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Athanasiou</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Toward tissue engineering of the knee meniscus</article-title>
                  <source>Tissue Eng. JID - 9505538</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <lpage>129</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/107632701300062697</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buma</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramrattan</surname>
                      <given-names>NN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Tienen</surname>
                      <given-names>TG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veth</surname>
                      <given-names>RP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tissue engineering of the meniscus</article-title>
                  <source>Biomaterials</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>1523</fpage>
                  <lpage>1532</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0142-9612(03)00499-X</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 14697855?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14697855</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adams</surname>
                      <given-names>SB</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Randolph</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gill</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tissue engineering for meniscus repair</article-title>
                  <source>J. Knee Surg.</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1248154</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15742594?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15742594</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiari</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A tissue engineering approach to meniscus regeneration in a sheep model</article-title>
                  <source>Osteoarthritis Cartil.</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>1056</fpage>
                  <lpage>1065</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2006.04.007</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kon</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tissue engineering for total meniscal substitution: animal study in sheep model</article-title>
                  <source>Tissue Eng. Part A</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>1067</fpage>
                  <lpage>1080</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.tea.2007.0193</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18500918?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18500918</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stapleton</surname>
                      <given-names>TW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Development and characterization of an acellular porcine medial meniscus for use in tissue engineering</article-title>
                  <source>Tissue Eng. Part A</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>505</fpage>
                  <lpage>518</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/tea.2007.0233</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18370607?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18370607</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baker</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nathan</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huffman</surname>
                      <given-names>GR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mauck</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tissue engineering with meniscus cells derived from surgical debris</article-title>
                  <source>Osteoarthritis Cartil.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
                  <lpage>345</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2008.08.001</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zellner</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Role of mesenchymal stem cells in tissue engineering of meniscus</article-title>
                  <source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. A</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>94</volume>
                  <fpage>1150</fpage>
                  <lpage>1161</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20694982?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20694982</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kon</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tissue engineering for total meniscal substitution: animal study in sheep model-results at 12 months</article-title>
                  <source>Tissue Eng. Part A</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <fpage>1573</fpage>
                  <lpage>1582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.tea.2011.0572</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22500654?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500654</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cucchiarini</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Advances in combining gene therapy with cell and tissue engineering-based approaches to enhance healing of the meniscus</article-title>
                  <source>Osteoarthritis Cartil.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>1330</fpage>
                  <lpage>1339</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2016.03.018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">W. Niu, et al. Cell-based strategies for meniscus tissue engineering. <italic>Stem Cells Int</italic>. 2016, 4717184 (2016).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adams, M. E., Hukins, D. W. L. in <italic>Knee Meniscus: Basic and Clinical Foundations</italic> (eds Mow, V. C., Arnoczky, S. P., Jackson, D. W.) 15–28 (Raven Press Ltd, New York, 1992).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sanchez-Adams</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Athanasiou</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Biomechanics of meniscus cells: regional variation and comparison to articular chondrocytes and ligament cells</article-title>
                  <source>Biomech. Model. Mechanobiol.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>1047</fpage>
                  <lpage>1056</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10237-012-0372-0</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22231673?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22231673</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nakata, K. et al. Human meniscus cell: characterization of the primary culture and use for tissue engineering. <italic>Clin. Orthop. Relat. Res</italic>. <bold>391</bold>, S208–S218 (2001).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adesida</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grady</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>WS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hardingham</surname>
                      <given-names>TE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The matrix-forming phenotype of cultured human meniscus cells is enhanced after culture with fibroblast growth factor 2 and is further stimulated by hypoxia</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Res. Ther.</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>R61</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar1929</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16563175?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16563175</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matthies</surname>
                      <given-names>NF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mulet-Sierra</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jomha</surname>
                      <given-names>NM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adesida</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Matrix formation is enhanced in co-cultures of human meniscus cells with bone marrow stromal cells</article-title>
                  <source>J. Tissue Eng. Regen. Med.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>965</fpage>
                  <lpage>973</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/term.1489</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22473741?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22473741</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cui, X., Hasegawa, A., Lotz, M. &amp; D’Lima, D. Structured three-dimensional co-culture of mesenchymal stem cells with meniscus cells promotes meniscal phenotype without hypertrophy. <italic>Biotechnol. Bioeng.</italic><bold>109</bold>, 2369–2380 (2012).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saliken</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mulet-Sierra</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jomha</surname>
                      <given-names>NM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adesida</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Decreased hypertrophic differentiation accompanies enhanced matrix formation in co-cultures of outer meniscus cells with bone marrow mesenchymal stromal cells</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Res. Ther.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>R153</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar3889</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22726892?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22726892</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aung, A., Gupta, G., Majid, G. &amp; Varghese, S. Osteoarthritic chondrocyte-secreted morphogens induce chondrogenic differentiation of human mesenschymal stem cells. <italic>Arthritis Rheum.</italic><bold>63</bold>, 148–158 (2011).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnstone</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hering</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caplan</surname>
                      <given-names>AI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldberg</surname>
                      <given-names>VM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yoo</surname>
                      <given-names>JU</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>In vitro chondrogenesis of bone marrow-derived mesenchymal progenitor cells</article-title>
                  <source>Exp. Cell Res.</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>238</volume>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <lpage>272</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/excr.1997.3858</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9457080?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9457080</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adesida</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mulet-Sierra</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jomha</surname>
                      <given-names>NM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hypoxia mediated isolation and expansion enhances the chondrogenic capacity of bone marrow mesenchymal stromal cells</article-title>
                  <source>Stem Cell Res. Ther.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/scrt100</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22385573?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22385573</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kupcsik</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alini</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stoddart</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mechanical load modulates chondrogenesis of human mesenchymal stem cells through the TGF-beta pathway</article-title>
                  <source>J. Cell. Mol. Med.</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>1338</fpage>
                  <lpage>1346</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2009.00780.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19432813?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19432813</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Min</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Low-intensity ultrasound (LIUS) as an innovative tool for chondrogenesis of mesenchymalstem cells (MSCs)</article-title>
                  <source>Organogenesis</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <lpage>78</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/org.3.2.4943</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19279704?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279704</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schumann</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Treatment of human mesenchymal stem cells with pulsed low intensity ultrasound enhances the chondrogenic phenotype in vitro</article-title>
                  <source>Biorheology</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <fpage>431</fpage>
                  <lpage>443</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16912415?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912415</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verdonk</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>V.</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Almqvist</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veys</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verbruggen</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fibrochondrogenic differentiation of human mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>
                  <source>J. Orthop.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <lpage>71</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yu, B. et al. Simulated microgravity using a rotary cell culture system promotes chondrogenesis of human adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells via the p38 MAPK pathway. <italic>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</italic><bold>414</bold>, 412–418 (2011).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>JW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mechanical stimulation by ultrasound enhances chondrogenic differentiation of mesenchymal stem cells in a fibrin-hyaluronic acid hydrogel</article-title>
                  <source>Artif. Organs</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>648</fpage>
                  <lpage>655</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aor.12041</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23495957?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23495957</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sakao</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Induction of chondrogenic phenotype in synovium-derived progenitor cells by intermittent hydrostatic pressure</article-title>
                  <source>Osteoarthritis Cartil.</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>805</fpage>
                  <lpage>814</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2007.10.021</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsano</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spontaneous in vivo chondrogenesis of bone marrow-derived mesenchymal progenitor cells by blocking vascular endothelial growth factor signaling</article-title>
                  <source>Stem Cells Transl. Med.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27460852?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27460852</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Unsworth</surname>
                      <given-names>BR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lelkes</surname>
                      <given-names>PI</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Growing tissues in microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Med.</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>901</fpage>
                  <lpage>907</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0898-901</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9701241?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9701241</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freed</surname>
                      <given-names>LE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vunjak-Novakovic</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microgravity tissue engineering</article-title>
                  <source>In Vitro Cell. Dev. Biol. Anim.</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <lpage>385</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11626-997-0009-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9196897?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9196897</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freed</surname>
                      <given-names>LE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vunjak-Novakovic</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cultivation of cell-polymer tissue constructs in simulated microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>Biotechnol. Bioeng.</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>306</fpage>
                  <lpage>313</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.260460403</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18623317?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18623317</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsano</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Use of hydrodynamic forces to engineer cartilaginous tissues resembling the non-uniform structure and function of meniscus</article-title>
                  <source>Biomaterials</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>5927</fpage>
                  <lpage>5934</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2006.08.020</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16949667?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16949667</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dominici</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Minimal criteria for defining multipotent mesenchymal stromal cells. The International Society for Cellular Therapy position statement</article-title>
                  <source>Cytotherapy</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <lpage>317</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14653240600855905</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16923606?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16923606</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Horwitz</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clarification of the nomenclature for MSC: The International Society for Cellular Therapy position statement</article-title>
                  <source>Cytotherapy</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
                  <lpage>395</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14653240500319234</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16236628?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236628</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krawetz</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Synovial fluid progenitors expressing CD90+ from normal but not osteoarthritic joints undergo chondrogenic differentiation without micro-mass culture</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>e43616</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043616</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22952721?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22952721</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acharya</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Enhanced chondrocyte proliferation and mesenchymal stromal cells chondrogenesis in coculture pellets mediate improved cartilage formation</article-title>
                  <source>J. Cell. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>227</volume>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <lpage>97</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.22706</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22025108?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025108</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freed</surname>
                      <given-names>LE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Langer</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pellis</surname>
                      <given-names>NR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vunjak-Novakovic</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tissue engineering of cartilage in space</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>94</volume>
                  <fpage>13885</fpage>
                  <lpage>13890</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.25.13885</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9391122?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9391122</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mueller</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hypertrophy in mesenchymal stem cell chondrogenesis: effect of TGF-beta isoforms and chondrogenic conditioning</article-title>
                  <source>Cells Tissues Organs</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>192</volume>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <lpage>166</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000313399</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20407224?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20407224</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Steinert</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hypertrophy is induced during the in vitro chondrogenic differentiation of human mesenchymal stem cells by bone morphogenetic protein-2 and bone morphogenetic protein-4 gene transfer</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Res. Ther.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>R148</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar2822</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19799789?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19799789</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mueller</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tuan</surname>
                      <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Functional characterization of hypertrophy in chondrogenesis of human mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <fpage>1377</fpage>
                  <lpage>1388</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.23370</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18438858?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438858</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>von der Mark</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Type X collagen synthesis in human osteoarthritic cartilage. Indication of chondrocyte hypertrophy</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>806</fpage>
                  <lpage>811</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.1780350715</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1622419?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1622419</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van der Kraan</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Berg</surname>
                      <given-names>WB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Chondrocyte hypertrophy and osteoarthritis: role in initiation and progression of cartilage degeneration?</article-title>
                  <source>Osteoarthritis Cartil.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <lpage>232</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2011.12.003</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>D’Angelo</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MMP-13 is induced during chondrocyte hypertrophy</article-title>
                  <source>J. Cell Biochem.</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>77</volume>
                  <fpage>678</fpage>
                  <lpage>693</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4644(20000615)77:4&lt;678::AID-JCB15&gt;3.0.CO;2-P</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10771523?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10771523</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR49">
                <label>49.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leijten</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gremlin 1, frizzled-related protein, and Dkk-1 are key regulators of human articular cartilage homeostasis</article-title>
                  <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>64</volume>
                  <fpage>3302</fpage>
                  <lpage>3312</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.34535</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22576962?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22576962</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR50">
                <label>50.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gazzerro</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Conditional deletion of gremlin causes a transient increase in bone formation and bone mass</article-title>
                  <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>282</volume>
                  <fpage>31549</fpage>
                  <lpage>31557</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M701317200</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17785465?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17785465</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR51">
                <label>51.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muraglia</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campanile</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cancedda</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quarto</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor-2 supports ex vivo expansion and maintenance of osteogenic precursors from human bone marrow</article-title>
                  <source>Endocrinology</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <fpage>4456</fpage>
                  <lpage>4462</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endo.138.10.5425</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9322963?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9322963</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR52">
                <label>52.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bianchi</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ex vivo enrichment of mesenchymal cell progenitors by fibroblast growth factor 2</article-title>
                  <source>Exp. Cell Res.</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>287</volume>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <lpage>105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-4827(03)00138-1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12799186?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12799186</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR53">
                <label>53.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Solchaga</surname>
                      <given-names>LA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Penick</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldberg</surname>
                      <given-names>VM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caplan</surname>
                      <given-names>AI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Welter</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor-2 enhances proliferation and delays loss of chondrogenic potential in human adult bone-marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>
                  <source>Tissue Eng. Part A</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>1009</fpage>
                  <lpage>1019</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.tea.2009.0100</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19842915?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19842915</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR54">
                <label>54.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Di Maggio</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor-2 maintains a niche-dependent population of self-renewing highly potent non-adherent mesenchymal progenitors through FGFR2c</article-title>
                  <source>Stem Cells</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>1455</fpage>
                  <lpage>1464</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1106</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22495904?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495904</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR55">
                <label>55.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bornes</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jomha</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mulet-Sierra</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adesida</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hypoxic culture of bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stromal stem cells differentially enhances in vitro chondrogenesis within cell-seeded collagen and hyaluronic acid porous scaffolds</article-title>
                  <source>Stem Cell Res. Ther.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13287-015-0075-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25900045?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25900045</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
