<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:59:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6791064" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6791064</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-04-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>celljournal</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell J</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Royan Institute</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Cell Journal (Yakhteh)</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2228-5806</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2228-5814</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Royan Institute</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6791064</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6791064</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6791064</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31606974</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31606974</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">Cell-J-22-106</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22074/cellj.2020.6537</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Genetic</subject>
                    <subject>Cancer</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Alteration of Cytoskeleton Morphology and Gene Expression in
Human Breast Cancer Cells under Simulated Microgravity</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Strube</surname>
                    <given-names>Florian</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Infanger</surname>
                    <given-names>Manfred</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wehland</surname>
                    <given-names>Markus</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>Ph.D.</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Delvinioti</surname>
                    <given-names>Xenia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Romswinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>B.Sc.</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dietz</surname>
                    <given-names>Carlo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>B.Sc.</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kraus</surname>
                    <given-names>Armin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="A1">Department of Plastic, Aesthetic and Hand Surgery, Otto-von-Guericke-University, Magdeburg, Germany</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*Corresponding Address:</label><addr-line>Department of Plastic</addr-line><addr-line>Aesthetic and Hand Surgery</addr-line><institution>Otto-von-Guericke-University</institution><addr-line>Magdeburg</addr-line><country>Germany</country>
Email:<email>arminkraus@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <season>Spring</season>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>22</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>106</fpage>
              <lpage>114</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>9</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>The Cell Journal (Yakhteh) is an open access journal
which means the articles are freely available online for any individual author
to download and use the providing address. The journal is licensed under
a Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial 3.0 Unported License which
allows the author(s) to hold the copyright without restrictions that is
permitting unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium
provided the original work is properly cited.</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.
</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p> Weightlessness simulation due to the simulated microgravity has been shown to considerably affect
behavior of tumor cells. It is aim of this study to evaluate characteristics of human breast cancer cells in this scaffold-
free 3D culture model.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Materials and Methods</title>
                  <p> In this experimental study, the cells were exposed to simulated microgravity in a random-
positioning machine (RPM) for five days. Morphology was observed under phase-contrast and confocal microscopy.
Cytofilament staining was performed and changes in expression level of cytofilament genes, proliferation/differentiation
genes, oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes were detected by quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain
reaction (qRT-PCR), followed by western blot confirmation.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p> After five days, distinct spheroid formation was observed. Rearrangement of the cytoskeleton into spherical
shape was visible. <italic>VIM</italic> gene expression was significantly up-regulated for adherent cells and spheroids (3.3x and 3.6x
respectively, P&lt;0.05 each). <italic>RHOA</italic> also showed significant gene up-regulation for adherent cells and spheroids (3.2x
and 3.9x respectively, P&lt;0.05 each). <italic>BRCA</italic> showed significant gene up-regulation in adherent cells and spheroids (2.1x
and 4.1x respectively, P&lt;0.05 each). <italic>ERBB2</italic> showed significant gene up-regulation (2.4x, P&lt;0.05) in the spheroids, but
not in the adherent cells. <italic>RAB27A</italic> showed no significant alteration in gene expression. <italic>MAPK</italic>) showed significant gene
up-regulation in adherent cells and spheroids (3.2x, 3.0x, P&lt;0.05 each). <italic>VEGF</italic> gene expression was down-regulated
under simulated microgravity, without significance. Alterations of gene expressions could be confirmed on protein level
for vimentin and MAPK1. Protein production was not increased for BRCA1, human epidermal growth factor receptor 2
(HER2) and VEGF. Contradictory changes were determined for <italic>RHOA</italic> and its related protein.
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Microgravity provides an easy-to handle, scaffold-free 3D-culture model for human breast cancer cells.
There were considerable changes in morphology, cytoskeleton shape and gene expressions. Identification of the
underlying mechanisms could provide new therapeutic options.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Breast Neoplasms</kwd>
                <kwd>Cytoskeleton</kwd>
                <kwd>Proto-Oncogenes</kwd>
                <kwd>Tumor Suppressor Genes</kwd>
                <kwd>Weightlessness Simulation</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>Citation</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>Strube F, Infanger M, Wehland M, Delvinioti X, Romswinkel A, Dietz C, Kraus A. Alteration of cytoskeleton morphology and gene expression in
human breast cancer cells under simulated microgravity. Cell J. 2020; 22(1): 106-114. doi: 10.22074/cellj.2020.6537.</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Breast neoplasms are still a major cause of morbidity and
mortality in the western world. To identify new mechanisms
that could provide therapeutic targets, experiments in 
2-dimensional (2D) cell culture struggle with various 
limitations. Phenotype alteration and loss in 2D cultures has 
been described for several cell types. It has been described 
for somatic cells such as tenocytes (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) and mesenchymal 
stem cells (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Space flights have shown to impose significant 
alterations on human and animal organisms, as well as cell 
cultures. On the organism, various effects such as loss of bone 
mineralization or changes in blood pressure regulation are 
well known. </p>
              <p>In different cell types, loss of attachment from the otherwise
indispensable culture surface and transition to a state of
3-dimensional (3D) formations, so-called “spheroids“, has been reported. This was observed during flights beyond theearth atmosphere (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), during parabolic flight maneuvers (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>),
in addition to the simulated microgravity on earth. Hereby,
2D rotating clinostats or 3D rotating random positioningmachines (RPM) are in use. In both, simulated microgravity on
earth and during space flights, several effects of microgravity 
on breast cancer cells have been reported, especially with 
regards to invasion, adhesion and metastasis formation (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). </p>
              <p>Microgravity has also been reported to induce mitochondrial 
activity in breast cancer cells as a reaction to oxidative stress 
(<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Further studies by our group have shown alterations 
particularly with regard to the cytoskeleton arrangement (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). 
Microgravity therefore seems to be an attractive 3D cell culture 
model to study migration and invasiveness in breast cancer. 
We performed experiments where we exposed breast cancer 
cells to simulated microgravity. We studied cytoskeleton 
morphology as well as gene and protein expression levels 
related to tumor differentiation, proliferation and invasion. 
In this study, we aimed to provide new insights into these 
mechanisms in order to identify potential targets for new 
therapeutic strategies. </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials-methods">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <p>The present work was designed as an experimental 
laboratory study (level of evidence V). </p>
              <sec>
                <title>Cell culture</title>
                <p>Human breast cancer cells (adenocarcinoma, CRL2351) 
were obtained from ATCC<sup>©</sup> (Wesel, Germany). 
All experiments were performed on this commercially 
available cell line, so no Ethical Committee approval was 
necessary. The cell line is negative estrogen receptor and it 
overexpresses the HER2/neu oncogene. The cells were firstly 
expanded under 2D-conditions in T125 flasks (Sarstedt, 
USA). Ham´s F12-media (Gibco, Germany) supplemented 
with 5% fetal calf serum (FCS, Biochrom AG, Germany) 
and 1% penicillin/streptomycin (Biochrom, Germany) was 
used. The medium was changed three times per week. For 
this experiment, 1×10<sup>6</sup> cells were counted by hemocytometer 
and added to six T125 flasks, as the experimental group in the 
RPM, and to the same number of flasks for the control group 
under 1g conditions. For cytoskeleton staining, the cells were 
seeded with a density of 1×10<sup>5</sup> per cm<sup>2</sup> to slide flasks (Thermo 
Scientific, Germany). </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Random positioning machine</title>
                <p>Weitghtlessness simulation was generated using an 
RPM. The RPM (developed by University of Applied 
Sciences, Northwestern Switzerland) was run with a 
commercially available incubator at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. 
The device was operated in a random walk modus using 
an angular velocity of 60°/seconds. The method was 
intensively investigated and published earlier (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Six 
flasks of T125 cm<sup>2</sup> were attached as much as possible to 
the center of RPM machine, and the samples were rotated 
for the selected time period (five days). Static, non-
rotated controls were exposed to the same environmental 
conditions nearby the device. The RPM machine was 
rebooted once per 24 hours to ensure proper operation. 
Interruption was kept as short as possible every time. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Phase contrast microscopy </title>
                <p>Phase contrast microscopy was performed for visual 
observation of viability and morphology of the cells, and 
for detection of potential spheroids. A Leica microscope 
(Leica Microsystems GmbH, Germany) was used. 
Pictures were taken with a Canon EOS 60D (Canon 
GmbH, Germany). </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Cytoskeleton staining</title>
                <p>In terms of cytoskeleton analysis, the cells exposed to 
simulated microgravity in the RPM for five days were 
investigated in the slide flasks. Filamentous actin (F-actin) 
was analyzed by visualization of phalloidin-stained cells 
(PromoKine, USA). Both adherent cells and spheroids 
were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 10 minutes 
and permeabilized with 1% Triton-X for 5 minutes. 
Nonspecific binding was blocked by incubation with 1% 
bovine serum albumin (BSA). Staining was performed 
by incubation of the slides with 6.6 µM solution of a 
phalloidin/Alexa Fluor 488 conjugate (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Germany) for 30 minutes at room temperature, 
followed by thorough washing with phosphate buffere 
saline (PBS) solution. Nuclei were counterstained with 
4',6-diamidine-2-phenylindol (DAPI, Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Germany) at 0.1 µg/ml concentration for 1 
minute. The samples were mounted with Vectashield 
mounting medium (Vector Laboratories, USA).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Confocal microscopy </title>
                <p>Confocal microscopy of the slides stained for F-actin 
was performed with a Zeiss 510 META inverted confocal 
laser scanning microscope (Zeiss, Germany). Excitation 
and emission wavelengths were 485 nm/560 nm, 
respectively.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>RNA and protein isolations, quantitative reverse 
transcription polymerase chain reaction and western 
blot </title>
                <sec>
                  <title>RNA isolation </title>
                  <p>An aliquot of cells was frozen in liquid nitrogen for
subsequent lysis and protein isolation as described further
below. RNA isolation and quantitative reverse transcription 
polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) were done according 
to standard protocols following the manufacturer’s manual. 
RNA isolation was performed with the AllPrep DNA/RNA/ 
Protein Mini<sup>©</sup> Kit (Qiagen, Germany) according to the
manual. The cells were brought into suspension from the
culture plate surfaces by adding 0.025% trypsin (Sigma-
Aldrich, Germany). The cell suspension was spun down 
in an RNase-free tube for five minutes at 300 g. Next, 350 
µl of the lysis buffer RLT was added to the pellet to induce 
cell lysis. Remaining RNases were inactivated by 1% 
ß-mercaptoethanol addition. The lysate was vortexed for 
1 minute to obtain a homogenous lysate. Thereafter, it was 
stabilized by adding 100% ethanol in an equal volume to the 
lysate. The liquid was then transferred to an RNeasy Spin 
Column and centrifuged in a micro-centrifuge at 10,000 rpm 
for 15 seconds. The flow-through was put aside for further 
protein isolation as described below. Afterwards, 700 µl of the 
buffer RW1 (washing buffer) was given to the spin column, 
followed by centrifugation at 10,000 rpm for 15 seconds. The 
flow-through was discarded again. The washing buffer RPE<sup>©</sup> 
was added to the spin column at a volume of 500 µl and the 
column was centrifuged at 10,000 rpm for 15 seconds. This 
step was repeated after discarding the flow-through. The 
RNA was then eluted into an RNase-free collection tube by 
centrifugation with 30 µl of RNase-free water. The RNA was 
quantified photometrically by measuring the absorbance at 260 
nm with a SpectraMax M2 device (Molecular Devices, USA). </p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Reverse transcription</title>
                <p>Reverse transcription was done using the First Strand 
cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific, USA) according 
to the manual. Briefly, for each sample, 3 µg total RNA, 
random hexamer primers and nuclease-free water were 
mixed together to an overall volume of 11 µl. To this volume, 
reaction buffer, RNase inhibitor, oligonucleotides and reverse 
transcriptase were added to a total volume of 20 µl. All steps 
were performed under refrigeration on ice. The mix was kept
for five minutes at 25°C, followed by 60 minutes at 42°C. The 
reaction was stopped by incubation at 70°C for five minutes. 
The complementary DNA (cDNA) was stored at -20°C for 
less than one week before performing further experiments. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain 
reaction </title>
                <p>qRT-PCR was utilized to determine relative expression 
of the target genes, such as proto-oncogenes and tumor 
suppressor genes, as shown in Table 1. The SYBR® Green 
PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Germany) and 
the 7500 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, 
Germany) were used. 10 µl master mix, 1 µl of each forward 
and reverse primers at the concentration of 400 nM and 1-8 µl 
cDNA and RNase free water, in relation to the input-amount 
of RNA, were mixed together. Cycling steps were executed 
as follows after activation of uracil-DNA glycosylase (50°C 
for two minutes) and DNA polymerase (95°C for 2 minutes): 
95°C for 15 seconds and 60°C for 1 minute (40 cycles). 
Absence of primer dimers was confirmed by checking 
dissociation curves. cDNA-selective primers were collected 
from Harvard primer database (<uri xlink:href="https://pga.mgh.harvard.edu/">https://pga.mgh.harvard.edu/ </uri>
primerbank) and were supplied by TIB Molbiol (Germany). 
All samples were measured as triplicates. 18S rRNA was 
used as housekeeping gene. The comparative C<sub>T</sub> (ΔΔC<sub>T</sub>) 
method was used to calculate relative transcription levels of 
the target genes. The control group was defined as 100%. 
Primer sequences are as shown in Table 1. The experiments 
were performed in five replicates. </p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction(qRT-PCR) primer sequences. All primers were obtained from Harvardprimer bank (<uri xlink:href="https://pga.mgh.harvard.edu/primerbank/">https://pga.mgh.harvard.edu/primerbank/</uri>)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence (5ˊ-3ˊ)</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>VIM</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: GACGCCATCAACACCGAGTT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: CTTTGTCGTTGGTTAGCTGGT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>RHOA</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: CTCGCTCAGTGCGAAGACAA </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: CATTCTCTGACGACATTTTCCCT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>BRCA1</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: GCTCGTGGAAGATTTCGGTGT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: TCATCAATCACGGACGTATCATC</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>ERBB2</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: CCTCTGACGTCC ATCGTCTC</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: CGGATCTTCTGCTGC CGTCG</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>RAB27A</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: GCTTTGGGAGACTCTGGTGTA</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: TCAATGCCCACTGTTGTGATAAA </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>MAPK1</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: TACACCAACCTCTCGTACATCG</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: CATGTCTGAAGCGCAGTAAGATT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>VEGF</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: AGGGCAGAATCATCACGAAGT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: AGGGTCTCGATTGGATGGCA</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>18S rRNA</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: ATGGCGGCGTCTGTATTAAAC</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: AGAACCATATCGCTCCTGGTAT</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Western blotting</title>
                <p>Protein and RNA isolations were simultaneously 
performed using the AllPrep DNA/RNA/Protein Mini<sup>©</sup>
Kit, as described above. The flow-through preserved 
from the respective elution step, described above, was 
mixed with an equal volume of the buffer APP<sup>©</sup> from the 
extraction kit and kept for 10 minutes at room temperature 
after meticulous mixing for protein precipitation. The 
suspension was centrifuged for 10 minutes at maximum 
speed and the supernatant was carefully pipetted off 
to obtain a protein pellet. The pellet was dried at room 
temperature for 10 minutes. The pellet was next dissolved 
again in 100 µl of the buffer ALO<sup>©</sup> 
and heated to 95°C for 
this purpose. The solution was centrifuged again at full 
speed for one minute to remove remaining precipitates 
and debris. The protein solution was frozen at -20°C 
until further use. Gel electrophoresis, transblotting and 
densitometry were performed according to the standard 
protocols. Isolated protein was incubated for 10 minutes 
with sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)-gel loading buffer 
(consisting of 1 M Tris base, pH=6.8, 1% clycerol, 
10% SDS, 0.1% bromophenol blue freshly added to 
0.05% ß-mercaptoethanol and 1% protease inhibitors, 
all purchased from Roche, Germany). The sampleswere denatured at 95°C for five minutes. Afterwards, 
the probes were loaded together with the prestained 
page rule (Thermo Scientific, USA) onto a 10% SDSpolyacrylamide 
gel followed by electrophoresis and 
semi-dry blotting onto 0.45 µm nitrocellulose membranes 
(Whatman, Germany). Primary antibodies were used 
in blocking reagent with following dilutions: rabbit 
polyclonal anti-vimentin (1:2000), rabbit polyclonal antiRhoA(1:500), rabbit polyclonal anti-Her2 (1:1000), rabbit 
polyclonal anti-RAB27A (1:1000), rabbit polyclonal antiMAPK1 
(1:1000), all obtained from Origene, USA, as 
well as rabbit polyclonal anti-BRCA1 (1:10000, Milipore, 
USA), rabbit polyclonal anti VEGF-A (1:1000, Thermo 
Fisher, USA). All antibodies were certified for western 
blot reactivity in human specimens by the suppliers. </p>
                <p>The secondary antibody was included in the “BM 
Chemiluminescence Western Blotting Kit mouse/rabbit” 
(Roche, Germany). The blots were stripped at 50°C for 
30 minutes with stripping buffer (Restore Western blot 
stripping buffer, Thermo scientific, USA), washed and 
re-incubated with anti-GAPDH antibody (1:1000, Cell 
Signaling, Germany). Blots were analyzed by the Alpha-
Ease® FC Imaging System (Alpha Innotech, Germany). 
The experiments were performed in three replicates. </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>All statistical analyses were done using SPSS 21.0 (SPSS, 
Inc., USA, 2012). The groups were tested with the Mann-
Whitney U test. The data are shown as means ± standard 
deviation (SD). A P&lt;0.05 was considered significant. </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>A simulated average gravity value as low as 0.003 g was 
calculated by the RPM software.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Light microscopy</title>
                <p>After 24 hours, formation of smaller spheroids, consisting 
of approximately 10-20 cells, was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig .1A</xref>). After 
five days, a considerable number of cells had detached 
from the culture surface, forming cluster shaped spheroids 
consisting of 30-50 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig .1B</xref>). Breast cancer cells 
showed rounded morphology with no obvious signs of 
impaired viability, according to preliminary trypan blue 
staining. This shows good cell viability without significant 
difference between the cells at 1g and those under simulated 
microgravity (data not shown). In the control group, under 
1g conditions, the cells showed typical flat morphology with 
rectangular to hexagonal borders, attached to the culture 
surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig .1C</xref>). </p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Confocal microscopy</title>
                <p>After five days, the breast cancer cells showed under 
microgravity spherical rearrangement of actin filaments 
with accentuation of the filaments in the region of cell 
membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig .2A</xref>). In the adherent cells under simulated 
microgravity, a tendency towards spherical orientation of 
the actin filaments could be observed, while that is less 
pronounced than spheroids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig .2B</xref>). Under the condition 
of 1 g, actin filaments were arranged in a longitudinal 
manner with more uniform distribution of the filaments 
inside the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig .2C</xref>). </p>
                <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig.1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Analysis of spheroid formation of breast cancer cells under simulated microgravity (0.003 g) after one and five days, under light microscopy. A. 
Formation of small spheroids can be observed after 24 hours, B. After 5 days, size of the cluster to tubular shaped spheroids increased, while part of the 
cells remained attached to the culture flask surface, and C. In the control group under 1 g conditions, the cells showed typical shape with flat morphology 
and rectangular to hexagonal borders (scale bar: 50 µm). 
</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="Cell-J-22-106-g01"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig.2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Actin staining of breast cancer cells. <bold>A.</bold> In the spheroids under simulated microgravity, actin filaments arranged in a spherical shape with accentuation 
in the area of the cell membrane, <bold>B.</bold> In the adherent cells under simulated microgravity, spherical orientation beginning of the actin filaments was 
observed, and <bold>C.</bold> In the 1 g control group, actin filaments were arranged in a longitudinal manner with uniform distribution among the cytoplasm (scale 
bar: 25 µm). </p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="Cell-J-22-106-g02"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain 
reaction</title>
                <p>After five days, <italic>VIM</italic> as a component of the 
cytoskeleton showed significantly up-regulated gene 
expression in the both attached cells and spheroids 
(3.3x and 3.6x respectively, P&lt;0.05 each, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig .3A</xref>). 
Correspondingly, <italic>RHOA</italic>, as a marker of cytoskeleton 
differentiation, also showed significant up-regulation 
in the both attached cells and spheroids under 
simulated microgravity (3.2x and 3.9x respectively, 
P&lt;0.05 each, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig .3B</xref>). <italic>BRCA1</italic> gene showed 
significant up-regulation in the both adherent cells 
and spheroids, compared to the control with 1 g 
(2.1x and 4.1x respectively, P&lt;0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig .3C</xref>). <italic>ERBB2</italic> 
showed no significant up-regulation in the adherent
cells under microgravity, while it was significantly 
up-regulated in the spheroids (2.4x, P&lt;0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig .4A</xref>). 
<italic>RAB27A</italic>, as a KRAS-related control gene, showed no
significant up-regulation in the both attached cells
and spheroids under microgravity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig .4B</xref>). <italic>MAPK1</italic>, 
as a marker of proliferation and differentiation,
showed significant up-regulation in the both adherent
cells and spheroids under microgravity (3.2x and 
3.0x respectively, P&lt;0.05 each, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig .5A</xref>). <italic>VEGF</italic>
showed down-regulation in the both adherent cells
(under simulated microgravity) and spheroids (0.67x 
and 0.60x respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig .5B</xref>), while it was not 
significant different (P=0.056 each). </p>
                <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig.3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Alteration in gene expression and protein production under simulated microgravity. <bold>A.</bold>
<italic>VIM</italic> as a component of the cytoskeleton showed significantly up-regulation in the 
both attached cells and spheroids, after five days (3.3x and 3.6x respectively, *P&lt;0.05 each). <italic>VIM</italic> up-regulation was accompanied by increased vimentin protein production, 
<bold>B.</bold>
<italic>RHOA</italic> also showed significant up-regulation in the both adherent cells and spheroids, under simulated microgravity (3.2x and 3.9x respectively, *P&lt;0.05 each). In contrast,
RhoA protein content was not increased under simulated microgravity, and <bold>C.</bold>
<italic>BRCA1</italic> showed significant up-regulation in the both adherent cells and spheroids (2.1x and 4.1x 
respectively, *P&lt;0.05 each). BRCA1 protein content was not significantly increased, as shown by western blot.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="Cell-J-22-106-g03"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig.4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Alteration in gene expression and protein production under simulated microgravity. <bold>A.</bold>
<italic>ERBB2</italic> showed significant gene up-regulation (2.4x, *P&lt;0.05) in 
the spheroids, compared to the 1 g control group, while the corresponding protein production was not increased under microgravity and <bold>B.</bold>
<italic>RAB27A</italic> showed no 
significant change in gene expression of the both adherent cells simulated under microgravity and spheroids. There was no change in Rab-27a protein content. 
</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="Cell-J-22-106-g04"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig.5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Alteration in gene expression and protein production under simulated microgravity. <bold>A.</bold> After five days, <italic>MAPK1</italic> showed significant up-regulation 
in the both adherent cells and spheroids under simulated microgravity (3.2x and 3.0 respectively, *P&lt;0.05 each). Gene up-regulation was confirmed on 
protein level by western blot and <bold>B.</bold>
<italic>VEGF</italic> was down-regulated under simulated microgravity in both gene expression and protein levels, but the values 
were not statistically significant.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="Cell-J-22-106-g05"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Western blots</title>
                <p>In line with <italic>VIM</italic> gene overexpression, analysis of 
western blot showed up-regulation of vimentin protein 
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig .3A</xref>). In the case of <italic>RHOA</italic>, protein expression level was 
attenuated under simulated microgravity gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig .3B</xref>). 
Although <italic>BRCA1</italic> gene expression was significantly up-
regulated in the adherent cells and spheroids, western blot 
analyses showed approximately similar protein levels 
for adherent cells, spheroids and the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig .3C</xref>). 
<italic>ERBB2</italic> gene expression was significantly up-regulated in 
the spheroids, while the respective protein bands showed 
approximately equal intensities for all groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig .4A</xref>). 
Rab-27a showed no changes in protein levels of the three 
groups, similar to the related gene expressions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig .4B</xref>). 
MAPK1 showed increased protein levels in the two 
simulated microgravity groups, which was consistent to 
the respective up-regulated gene expressions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig .5A</xref>). 
VEGF protein was decreased in both groups under 
simulated microgravity, compared to the control group 
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig .5B</xref>). </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Breast neoplasms are common malignancies. Thus, 
in terms of developing new treatments, researches on 
the cell culture level could be a valuable tool. It is well 
known that the cells tend to change their morphology, 
behavior and phenotype after being released from their 
<italic>in vivo</italic> environment and put into a 2D culture condition. 
By applying simulated microgravity, we could observe 
considerable changes in morphology, cytoskeleton 
arrangement, gene expression and protein synthesis
compared to the 2D environment. For this study, five 
days investigation was selected, due to the following 
reason: preliminary experiments had shown that CRL2351 
cell line was relatively fast-growing and needed 
medium renewal after five days, according to the both 
vendor´s recommendations and our own observations. 
Furthermore, the cells showed almost complete confluence 
and the necessity of passaging after five days. We aimed 
to avoid medium change, because this maneuver would 
interrupt simulated microgravity and disturb its effects 
to particular degree. Therefore, five days was the longest 
period that this cell line could continuously be exposed to 
interruption-free simulated microgravity. </p>
              <p>Compared to the several other studies utilizing 2D 
rotating clinostats, we used an RPM in this experiment, 
as a device simulating microgravity by 3D movements in 
space. Experiments, comparing the effects of simulated 
microgravity on an RPM with the space outside of earth 
atmosphere on cell cultures, have shown very good 
correlation between these two systems (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Furthermore, 
we examined a cell line with unique characteristics 
which has not been exposed to microgravity so far, to our 
knowledge. In comparison with the MCF-7 cells, used 
in most of the studies dealing with breast cancer cells 
under simulated microgravity (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), the evaluated 
biologic features of CRL-2351 cell line in this study 
are controversial from many aspects: CRL-2351 cells 
are negative estrogen receptor, so the pathways usually 
associated with estrogen receptor signaling, like MAP 
kinase, will be influenced in a unique, hitherto unknown 
manner. Furthermore, HER2/neu is overexpressed in 
CRL-2351 cells, in contrast to MCF-7 cells, particularly 
giving us the option to evaluate the effects of simulated 
microgravity on this important prognostic factor. Using 
light microscope, observations showed 3D constitution, 
round to tubular-shaped formations -known as spheroids- 
and reported already from various tumor and somatic cell 
types, such as from tenocytes (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), chondrocytes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), or 
thyroid cancer cells (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) .</p>
              <p>Another group of the cells under simulated microgravity 
remained adherent to the culture surface, but they showed 
various changes in morphology, gene expression and 
protein production. These cells could either represent a 
transitional state before spheroid formation, or remain in 
this adherent state for reasons still needing to be elucidated. 
In the MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cell line, Masiello et 
al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) could observe spheroid formation after 24 and 72 
hours. In other studies, significant deceleration of breast 
cancer cell proliferation, while they are accumulated in 
the G2 phase, was reported under simulated microgravity 
(<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In the cytoskeleton, we observed a change from the 
longitudinal shape of actin filaments towards spherical 
distribution, accentuated in the region of cell membrane. 
This is in accordance with the results of Kopp <italic>et al</italic>. who 
reported similar findings for another line of breast cancer 
cells under simulated microgravity (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), and consistent to 
the results of Masiello et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) cited above. To explain 
this phenomenon, a "gravity sensor" has been proposed 
inherited in the cytoskeleton, which is responsive to 
external forces (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Particularly for the tumor cells, it 
has been reported that their metastatic potential is related 
to actin skeleton arrangement and remodeling (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). 
In addition, to investigate cytoskeleton changes in the 
molecular level, we examined gene expression of <italic>VIM</italic> 
and <italic>RHOA</italic>. </p>
              <p>Vimentin is a cytoskeleton compound playing important 
role in the migration and invasion of breast cancer cells. 
Similar to the finding obtained in this experiment, an 
increased expression of <italic>VIM</italic> has been described as a 
epithelial to mesenchymal transition marker, leading to 
the enhanced invasion and metastasis in breast cancer 
cells. This may be one of the reasons why increased 
expression of <italic>VIM</italic> in breast cancer contributes to 
chemoresistance and poor prognosis (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). It is required to 
be furher elucidated whether <italic>VIM</italic> overexpression, under 
simulated microgravity, is indeed a marker of increased 
invasiveness. Thus metastatic potential is increased, or 
it rather reflects loss of surface attachment and spheroid 
formation without changes in metastatic ability. However, 
targeted and selective cytoskeleton derangement in cancer 
cells (e.g. by RNA-interference) could be a potential tool 
in future tumor therapy. As a therapeutic approach in 
this field, microRNA targeting against <italic>VIM</italic> was shown 
to decrease breast cancer invasion in animal studies (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). 
RhoA is another small GTPase with several functions, 
and it is known to be a key effector in the polymerization 
of actin filaments (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Hence, we also examined <italic>RhoA</italic> 
gene and protein expressions. </p>
              <p>In addition to these changes related to the cytoskeleton,
we observed further various alterations in gene 
expression and corresponding protein synthesis. Firstly, 
we normalized qRT-PCR data to 18s rRNA and western 
blot data to GAPDH expression. Although it is not exactly 
known which gene or protein undergoes the least changes 
under simulated microgravity, the indicated housekeeping 
genes look the best option in this experiment, due to 
several reasons: 18s rRNA is known to be very stably 
expressed under many different circumstances and it 
has been used as a housekeeping gene in simulated 
microgravity research by the other groups before (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). 
GAPDH has also been previously used for normalization 
of western blot data in microgravity research by the other 
groups (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Indeed, the corresponding bands of GAPDH 
protein showed very similar intensity in our experiments. 
In the endeavor to obtain information whether the
breast cancer cells transform towards a more or less
malignant phenotype under simulated microgravity, we 
measured a variety of genes known as proto-oncogenes, 
tumor suppressor genes, or those which are related to 
cell proliferation and differentiation. <italic>BRCA1</italic>, with no 
mutation and with normal function, is a well-known gene
counteracting genome instability and acting as a tumor
suppressor gene (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). </p>
              <p>We observed significant overexpression of <italic>BRCA1</italic>, 
at least on the gene level, in the spheroids. This could 
be indicative of a transformation towards a phenotype 
with improved genomic repair and stability. Further 
experiments are required to evaluate this question in more 
detail. <italic>BRCA1</italic> gene expression was even higher in the 
spheroids than adherent cells, while this is not observed in 
the protein level. It is proposed that adherent cells under 
simulated microgravity might be a precursor of spheroids, 
turning into spheroids later. However, the adherent 
cells also could be an own entity for reasons unknown 
hitherto, remaining them adherent for a long period of 
time or even permanently. In a study, mouse embryonic 
stem cells (mESCs) were exposed to microgravity during 
spaceflight for 15 days. Analysis of this study showed 
down-regulation of <italic>BRCA1</italic> gene (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), Although it still 
need to evaluate whether BRCA1 mimics similar tasks 
in mESCs and the breast cancer cells we examined. On 
the other hand, we observed significant up-regulation of 
<italic>ERBB2</italic> gene, but not HER2 protein, particularly in the 
spheroids. The cell line we used overexpresses HER2 
anyway from the beginning. HER2 proteins consist 
of trans-membrane growth factor receptors activating 
intracellular signaling pathways. HER2 has been shown 
to play an important role in the pathogenesis of human 
breast cancer, and overexpression of this protein in human 
breast cancer cells is usually related to more aggressive 
behavior. Measurement of <italic>ERBB2</italic>/HER2 expression 
therefore seems of great interest to us, as this could give 
a hint towards transformation into a more aggressive 
phenotype induced by simulated microgravity. </p>
              <p>As spheroid formation is associated with detachment 
of cells from a confluent 2D state, it is proposed that 
similar mechanisms to metastasis formation from a solid 
tumor come into action. We therefore measured <italic>RAB27A</italic> 
gene expression and Rab-27a protein production, 
as it is known to play a crucial role not only in breast 
gland development, but also in breast cancer pathology, 
particularly in modulation of metastatic potential (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). 
As a small GTPase, Rab-27a controls various steps of 
exosome release, and exosome-mediated intercellular 
communication plays a crucial role in the above described 
processes. In our experiments, we could not detect any 
significant alteration in this gene and protein. The reasons 
still have to be elucidated, but a different exposure time to 
simulated microgravity possibly could show expression 
changes in future studies. To our knowledge, we chose 
a negative estrogen receptor cell line in our experiments 
and exposed it to simulated microgravity for the first. 
MAPK1/MAPK1 therefore seem particularly interesting 
measurement targets, as MAPK1 is one of the effectors in 
breast cancer cell estrogen signaling (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p>
              <p>We observed significant up-regulation of <italic>MAPK1</italic>/ 
MAPK1 on both gene and protein levels under simulated 
microgravity. It has been shown that inhibition of MAP 
kinase pathway can lead to conversion of negative estrogen 
receptor breast cancer cells, as with our experiments, to a 
positive estrogen receptor phenotype (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Up-regulation 
of that could therefore be either interpreted in the sense 
of the negative estrogen receptor preservation, potentially 
more malignant phenotype, or the MAP kinase pathway 
take over further tasks in the microgravity setting which 
still needs to be elucidated. Despite not obtaining statistical 
significance, down-regulation of <italic>VEGF</italic> gene expression 
and protein production under simulated microgravity 
is another interesting finding. VEGF is known to be a 
potent endothelial growth factor regulating vascular 
permeability. Particularly, high VEGF expression is 
known to be associated with tumor progression and poor 
prognosis of breast neoplasms in the clinical setting (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). 
So that, <italic>VEGF</italic> gene and protein expression levels seem to 
be further important targets to evaluate. Anti-VEGF drugs 
(such as bevacizumab) are already administered in cancer 
therapy, and identification of the mechanisms responsible 
for <italic>VEGF</italic> down-regulation could help pave the way for 
new therapeutic strategies in this area.</p>
              <p>Overall, we observed a variety of changes in gene and 
protein expressions. Most of these changes, particularly 
regarding the cytoskeleton, were indicative of a more 
invasive and aggressive phenotype. Up-regulation of 
<italic>BRCA1</italic>, as a tumor-suppressor gene in the non-mutated 
state, is contradictory to these findings to some extent, 
and significance of that needs to be further investigated. 
Utilizing western blot, a strong correlation was determined 
between alterations of gene expression and corresponding 
protein content in <italic>VIM</italic>/Vimentin, <italic>RAB27A</italic>/Rab-27a 
and <italic>MAPK1</italic>/MAPK1. BRCA1 and HER2 showed 
no detectable increase in protein content, despite up-
regulation in gene expression level under microgravity. 
Surprisingly, there was decreased protein level of RhoA 
under simulated microgravity, despite up-regulation of 
gene expression. There are several possible explanations
for this observation. One potential reason is the existence 
of several post-translational modifications. Different half-
lives of proteins could be the other potential explanation. 
Rapid degradation of mRNA or delayed protein synthesis 
could also be conceived. RhoA protein, in particular, has 
been reported to undergo significant optional alteration 
in its half-life by post-translational methylation (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). 
Similar reasons my also account for the differences that 
we detected between western blot and qRT-PCR results 
for <italic>BRCA1</italic>/BRCA1 and <italic>ERBB2</italic>/HER2.</p>
              <p>Interestingly, another study reported a general decrease 
of protein synthesis under microgravity for the yet 
unknown reasons (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Simulated microgravity appears 
as an easy-to use and interesting 3D culture model for 
in vitro studies of breast cancer cells. Elongated shape 
of the spheroids resembles natural tumor structure better 
than conventional <italic>in vitro</italic> culture. Besides, both tumor-
suppressor genes and proto-oncogenes were altered in 
their expressions. Better understanding of the underlying 
mechanisms could help develop new tools to selectively 
influence proliferation, differentiation and invasion of 
breast cancer cells and pave the way for new therapeutic 
options.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p>Simulated microgravity induces spheroid formation in 
human breast cancer cells. Here we observed substantial 
changes in cytoskeleton morphology, cytoskeleton related 
gene and protein expression. We also determined change 
in gene and protein expression levels of proto-oncogenes 
and tumor suppressor genes. Our experiments could be a 
step towards a versatile, easy-to handle 3D culture model 
of human breast cancer. It could provide new insights in 
the molecular mechanisms of breast cancer pathogenesis 
paving the way to new therapeutic strategies. </p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>We are thankful to Andrea Kroeber and Sandra Vorwerk 
for technical assistance. The authors have no financial or 
other conflict of interest to disclose.</p>
            </ack>
            <bio id="d35e866">
              <title>Author’s Contributions </title>
              <p>F.S.; Conducted experiments and data evaluation. M.I.; 
Study design and draft evaluation. A.R., C.D.; Cell 
culture maintenance, draft evaluation. A.K.; Study design, 
draft preparation, study responsibility. M.W.; Study 
conception, critical review of he manuscript, conduction 
of part of the experiments. X.D.; Cell culture maintenance, 
critical review of the manuscript. The authors read and 
approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </bio>
            <ref-list>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bestwick</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bestwick</surname>
                      <given-names>LA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maffulli</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aspden</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Phenotypic drift in human tenocyte culture</article-title>
                  <source>Tissue Eng</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1843</fpage>
                  <lpage>1849</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16889514</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bu</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bao</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Senescence of mesenchymal stem cells (Review)</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Mol Med</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>775</fpage>
                  <lpage>782</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28290609</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pietsch</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gass</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nebuloni</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Echegoyen</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riwaldt</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baake</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Three-dimensional growth of human endothelial cells in an automated cell culture experiment container during the SpaceX CRS-8 ISS space mission - The SPHEROIDS project</article-title>
                  <source>Biomaterials</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>124</volume>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <lpage>156</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28199884</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wehland</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aleshcheva</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schulz</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saar</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hubner</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hemmersbach</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Differential gene expression of human chondrocytes cultured under short-term altered gravity conditions during parabolic flight maneuvers</article-title>
                  <source>Cell Commun Signal</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25889719</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qian</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xie</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weng</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Simulated weightlessness alters biological characteristics of human breast cancer cell line MCF</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Astronaut</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>63</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>947</fpage>
                  <lpage>958</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jiang</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yue</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Expression of estrogen receptor a in human breast cancer cells regulates mitochondrial oxidative stress under simulated microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Space Res</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1432</fpage>
                  <lpage>1440</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kopp</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahana</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Islam</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petersen</surname>
                      <given-names>AG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bauer</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Corydon</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>et</surname>
                      <given-names>al</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of NFkB in spheroid formation of human breast cancer cells cultured on the Random Positioning Machine</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Rep</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>921</fpage>
                  <lpage>921</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29343717</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wuest</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richard</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kopp</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grimm</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egli</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Simulated micro- gravity: critical review on the use of random positioning machines for mammalian cell culture</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>2015</volume>
                  <fpage>971474</fpage>
                  <lpage>971474</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25649075</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ulbrich</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wehland</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pietsch</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aleshcheva</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wise</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Loon</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of simulated and real microgravity on bone cells and mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>2014</volume>
                  <fpage>928507</fpage>
                  <lpage>928507</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25110709</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kopp</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Slumstrup</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Corydon</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahana</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aleshcheva</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Islam</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Identifications of novel mechanisms in breast cancer cells involving duct-like multicellular spheroid formation after exposure to the Random Positioning Machine</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Rep</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>26887</fpage>
                  <lpage>26887</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27230828</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coinu</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiaviello</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galleri</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Franconi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crescenzi</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palumbo</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Exposure to modeled microgravity induces metabolic idleness in malignant human MCF-7 and normal murine VSMC cells</article-title>
                  <source>FEBS Lett</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>580</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>2465</fpage>
                  <lpage>2470</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16638572</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraus</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luetzenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abuagela</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hollenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Infanger</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spheroid formation and modulation of tenocyte-specific gene expression under simulated microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>Muscles Ligaments Tendons J</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>411</fpage>
                  <lpage>417</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29387633</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aleshcheva</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahana</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hauslage</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hemmersbach</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egli</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Changes in morphology, gene expression and protein content in chondrocytes cultured on a random positioning machine</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>e79057</fpage>
                  <lpage>e79057</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24244418</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Warnke</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pietsch</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wehland</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bauer</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Infanger</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gorog</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>et</surname>
                      <given-names>al</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spheroid formation of human thyroid cancer cells under simulated microgravity: a possible role of CTGF and CAV1</article-title>
                  <source>Cell Com- mun Signal</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masiello</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cucina</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Proietti</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palombo</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coluccia</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>D‘Anselmi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Phenotypic switch induced by simulated micro- gravity on MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>2014</volume>
                  <fpage>652434</fpage>
                  <lpage>652434</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25215287</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vorselen</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roos</surname>
                      <given-names>WH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacKintosh</surname>
                      <given-names>FC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wuite</surname>
                      <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Loon</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of the cytoskeleton in sensing changes in gravity by non- specialized cells</article-title>
                  <source>FASEB J</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>536</fpage>
                  <lpage>547</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24249634</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mezencev</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McDonald</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sulchek</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cell stiffness is a biomarker of the metastatic potential of ovarian cancer cells</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>e46609</fpage>
                  <lpage>e46609</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23056368</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>LZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xia</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>p62/SQSTM1 interacts with vimentin to enhance breast cancer metastasis</article-title>
                  <source>Carcinogenesis</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>1092</fpage>
                  <lpage>1103</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28968743</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bockhorn</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yee</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chang</surname>
                      <given-names>YF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prat</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huo</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nwachukwu</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MicroRNA-30c targets cytoskeleton genes involved in breast cancer cell invasion</article-title>
                  <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>137</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <lpage>382</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23224145</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>O‘Connor</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dynamic functions of RhoA in tumor cell migration and invasion</article-title>
                  <source>Small GTPases</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <lpage>147</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24025634</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cirelli</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Domenico</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Botti</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Massoud</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geremia</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grimaldi</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of microgravity on aromatase expression in sertoli cells</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Rep</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>3469</fpage>
                  <lpage>3469</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28615629</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paul</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paul</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The breast cancer susceptibility genes (BRCA) in breast and ovarian cancers</article-title>
                  <source>Front Biosci (Landmark Ed)</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>605</fpage>
                  <lpage>618</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24389207</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blaber</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Finkelstein</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dvorochkin</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sato</surname>
                      <given-names>KY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yousuf</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burns</surname>
                      <given-names>BP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microgravity reduces the differentiation and regenerative potential of embryonic stem cells</article-title>
                  <source>Stem Cells Dev</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>22</issue>
                  <fpage>2605</fpage>
                  <lpage>2621</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414276</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hendrix</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hume</surname>
                      <given-names>AN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Exosome signaling in mammary gland development and cancer</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Dev Biol</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>55</volume>
                  <issue>7-9</issue>
                  <fpage>879</fpage>
                  <lpage>887</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22161843</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maniyar</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suriano</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ethanol enhances estrogen mediated angiogenesis in breast cancer</article-title>
                  <source>J Cancer</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>21</issue>
                  <fpage>3874</fpage>
                  <lpage>3885</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30410590</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bayliss</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hilger</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vishnu</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diehl</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El-Ashry</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reversal of the estrogen receptor negative phenotype in breast cancer and restoration of antiestrogen response</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>23</issue>
                  <fpage>7029</fpage>
                  <lpage>7036</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18056179</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meng</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Increased levels of LAPTM4B, VEGF and survivin are correlated with tumor progression and poor prognosis in breast cancer patients</article-title>
                  <source>Oncotarget</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>25</issue>
                  <fpage>41282</fpage>
                  <lpage>41293</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28476037</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <collab>Backlund PS Jr</collab>
                  <article-title>Post-translational processing of RhoA.carboxyl methylation of the carboxyl-terminal prenylcysteine increases the half-life of Rhoa</article-title>
                  <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>272</volume>
                  <issue>52</issue>
                  <fpage>33175</fpage>
                  <lpage>33180</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9407105</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feger</surname>
                      <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>JW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dubois</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kommaddi</surname>
                      <given-names>RP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Foster</surname>
                      <given-names>MW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Microgravity induces proteomics changes involved in endoplasmic reticulum stress and mitochondrial protection</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Rep</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>34091</fpage>
                  <lpage>34091</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27670941</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
