<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:56:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7606465" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7606465</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-04</datestamp>
        <setSpec>npjmicrogr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Microgravity</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Microgravity</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>NPJ Microgravity</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2373-8065</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7606465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7606465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7606465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33298968</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">121</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41526-020-00121-9</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Next-generation sequencing analysis of circulating micro-RNA expression in response to parabolic flight as a spaceflight analogue</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jirak</surname>
                    <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wernly</surname>
                    <given-names>Bernhard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0755-7955</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lichtenauer</surname>
                    <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Franz</surname>
                    <given-names>Marcus</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Knost</surname>
                    <given-names>Thorben</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Abusamrah</surname>
                    <given-names>Thaer</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kelm</surname>
                    <given-names>Malte</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bimpong-Buta</surname>
                    <given-names>Nana-Yaw</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8325-250X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jung</surname>
                    <given-names>Christian</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>christian.jung@med.uni-duesseldorf.de</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.21604.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0523 5263</institution-id><institution>Clinic of Internal Medicine II, Department of Cardiology, </institution><institution>Paracelsus Medical University of Salzburg, </institution></institution-wrap>Salzburg, Austria </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9613.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1939 2794</institution-id><institution>Department of Internal Medicine I, Jena University Hospital, </institution><institution>Friedrich Schiller University Jena, </institution></institution-wrap>Jena, Germany </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411327.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2176 9917</institution-id><institution>Division of Cardiology, Pulmonology, and Vascular Medicine, Medical Faculty, </institution><institution>University Duesseldorf, </institution></institution-wrap>Duesseldorf, Germany </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>2</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>2</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>6</volume>
              <elocation-id>31</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="OpenAccess">
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <p id="Par1">Understanding physiologic reactions to weightlessness is an indispensable requirement for safe human space missions. This study aims to analyse changes in the expression of circulating miRNAs following exposure to gravitational changes. Eight healthy volunteers (age: 24.5 years, male: 4, female: 4) were included. Each subject underwent 31 short-term phases of weightlessness and hypergravity induced by parabolic flight as a spaceflight analogue. At baseline, 1 and 24 h after parabolic flight, venous blood was withdrawn. Analysis of circulating miRNAs in serum was conducted by means of next generation sequencing. In total, 213 miRNAs were robustly detected (TPM &gt; 5) by small RNA sequencing in all 24 samples. Four miRNAs evidenced a significant change in expression after adjusting for multiple testing. Only miR-223-3p showed a consistent significant decrease 24 h after parabolic flight compared to baseline values and values at 1 h after parabolic flight. miR-941 and miR-24-3p showed a significant decrease 24 h after parabolic flight compared to 1 h after parabolic flight but not to baseline values. miR-486-5p showed a significant increase 24 h after parabolic flight compared to 1 h after parabolic flight but not to baseline values. A target network analysis identified genes of the p53 signaling pathway and the cell cycle highly enriched among the targets of the four microRNAs. Our findings suggest cellular adaption to gravitational changes at the post-transcriptional level. Based on our results, we suggest a change in cell cycle regulation as potential explanation for adaptational changes observed in space missions.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
                <title>Subject terms</title>
                <kwd>Molecular medicine</kwd>
                <kwd>Translational research</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100002946</institution-id>
                      <institution>Deutsches Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt (German Centre for Air and Space Travel)</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2020</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par2">Human space missions regained international focus in the last years. Besides an established Mars program by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) and a manned mission to the moon planned by both the Chinese space agency and NASA, space flights are also entering the private sector. Therefore space medicine, representing an indispensable requirement for save and successful missions, gained major awareness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par3">The adaptation of human organ systems following exposure to microgravity has been investigated in former studies. The most important changes comprise an increase in cardiac output and pulmonary flow as well as changes of the baroreceptor reflex and the cerebrovascular autoregulatory system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Long term changes commonly affect bones and muscles atrophy. Additionally, an impairment of lung function and liver function as well as a dysregulation of the immune system have been described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. A decrease in hemoglobin and an increase in glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and levels of myoglobin were reported by our study group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. While adaptive responses have been described recently, the molecular background of these adaptations, necessary to understand the changes in physiology, remains topic to ongoing investigations. First studies showing an alteration of miRNA expression in T-cell activation as well as a change in miRNA signature potentially influencing TGF-Beta response, and fibroblast growth suggest a weightlessness induced change in microRNA (miRNA) expression patterns as a potential explanation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par4">miRNAs are small, single stranded noncoding RNAs, usually between 19 and 24 nucleotides long<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. They are found in both, plants and animals and probably represent a well-preserved system of gene regulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. miRNAs originate from precursor molecules known as primary miRNAs (pri-miRNAs), which can span up to several hundred bases and undergo sequential processing via the ribonuclease III complexes “Drosha” and “Dicer” in the nucleus and cytoplasm, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. After the processing, mature miRNAs bind to the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Via a complementary sequence also known as the seed region (6–8 nucleotides long), the miRNA can guide the RISC to a target messenger RNA (mRNA), leading to translational repression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, a mechanism referred to as RNA interference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Accordingly, miRNA expression levels represent a key factor in the regulation of gene expression on the posttranscriptional level, influencing cell function and differentiation as well as autoregulation of protein formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Of note, individual miRNAs can target a huge number of different genes and thus regulate the whole gene expression patterns instead of only one specific gene. Apart from their intracellular role, miRNAs are also present in a cell-free and circulating form<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. While cell-free miRNAs can be found in different body fluids (e.g., saliva, spine fluid) circulating miRNAs are only found in the blood. Besides a passive leakage following apoptosis, necrosis, and inflammatory processes, the majority of circulating miRNAs depends on different carriers for active secretion to avoid degradation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Such carriers comprise protein complexes, lipoproteins as well as extracellular vesicles such as exosomes and microvesicles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. However, the exact distribution across the carriers mentioned above and their potential influence on the mode of action of the respective miRNAs is still topic to investigation. Circulating miRNAs can be disseminated as autocrine, paracrine, and endocrine signaling molecules within the body<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Studies have shown that circulating miRNAs are fully functional at their recipient cells, with a similar effect on gene silencing as observed for cellular miRNAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Accordingly, circulating miRNAs represent an important mode of intercellular communication, with the possibility of donor cells being able to influence the gene expression and the microenvironment of distant recipient cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Several studies have shown that miRNA transcription is cell-type specific and highly dynamic, with transcriptional changes occurring within minutes following a stimulus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. However, while the mode of action of circulating miRNAs appears similar to that of cellular miRNAs, their secretion patterns can differ considerably. This fact must be considered when interpreting findings made for circulating miRNAs.</p>
              <p id="Par5">Considering the different physical requirements in microgravity, an involvement of miRNAs in weightlessness-induced changes is assumed and was already described in small studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. However, further analysis on the influence of space travel on miRNA regulation is needed to better understand the involved adaptational processes on a post-transcriptional level. In the present study, we hypothesized that exposure to gravitational changes might lead to rapid changes in intracellular miRNA profiles in various cell types, which would alter miRNA release from cells. Accordingly, we aimed for an analysis of circulating miRNA expression following exposure to gravitational changes induced by parabolic flight as a spaceflight analog.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Baseline characteristics</title>
                <p id="Par6">In total, eight study participants were included in the study, four male and four females. The median age was 24.5 years. Baseline characteristics are depicted in Tables <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics + laboratory parameters and miRNA levels at baseline/1 h after parabolic flight/24 h after parabolic flight.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parameter</th><th>Timepoint</th><th>Median</th><th>IQR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Male/female sex <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>4 (50)/4 (50)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Age (years)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>24.5</td><td>12.5</td></tr><tr><td>Weight (kg)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>80.5</td><td>27</td></tr><tr><td>Height (cm)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>177.5</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>Creatinine (µmol/l)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>72.93</td><td>7.52</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>66.3</td><td>8.18</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>67.63</td><td>13.26</td></tr><tr><td>GFR (ml/min/1,73 m²)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>93.95</td><td>26.4</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>106.3</td><td>34.45</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>106.15</td><td>16.35</td></tr><tr><td>CRP (mg/l)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>2</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>1.5</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>1.5</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td>BNP (pg/ml)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>9.5</td><td>2.75</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>10</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>9</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>CK (U/l)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>113</td><td>130.75</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>120</td><td>121.5</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>141</td><td>125.5</td></tr><tr><td>Myoglobin (µg/l)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>33.5</td><td>24.6</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>40.35</td><td>43.7</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>30.3</td><td>47.2</td></tr><tr><td>mir-486-3p (TPM)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>807.113.74</td><td>600.797.18</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>503.349.41</td><td>331.243.28</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>1.067.561.35</td><td>629.299.14</td></tr><tr><td>mir-24-3p (TPM)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>414.17</td><td>180.57</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>554.23</td><td>211.55</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>318.63</td><td>99.47</td></tr><tr><td>mir-223-3p (TPM)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>705.58</td><td>972.14</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>665.82</td><td>1082.92</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>182.72</td><td>170.26</td></tr><tr><td>mir-941 (TPM)</td><td>Baseline</td><td>953.54</td><td>447.29</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1 h after parabolic flight</td><td>884.13</td><td>702.23</td></tr><tr><td/><td>24 h after parabolic flight</td><td>546.08</td><td>350.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>µmol/l</italic> micromole/liter, <italic>ml/min/1.73</italic> <italic>m</italic>²: milliliter/minute/1.73 square meters, <italic>mg/l</italic> milligram/liter, <italic>pg/ml</italic> picogram/milliliter, <italic>U/l</italic> units/litre, <italic>µg/l</italic> microgram/liter, <italic>TPM</italic> tags per million.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics + baseline laboratory parameters of each individual study subject.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Study subject</th><th>sex (m/f)</th><th>age (years)</th><th>weight (kg)</th><th>height (cm)</th><th>Creatinine (µmol/l)</th><th>GFR (ml/min/1.73 m²)</th><th>CRP (mg/l)</th><th>BNP (pg/ml)</th><th>CK (U/l)</th><th>Myoglobin (µg/l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>P1</td><td>m</td><td>40</td><td>93</td><td>176</td><td>70.7</td><td>108</td><td>1</td><td>9</td><td>65</td><td>24.8</td></tr><tr><td>P3</td><td>m</td><td>22</td><td>86</td><td>188</td><td>78.7</td><td>107.8</td><td>1</td><td>9</td><td>96</td><td>38.7</td></tr><tr><td>P5</td><td>m</td><td>23</td><td>95</td><td>193</td><td>73.4</td><td>116</td><td>2</td><td>9</td><td>209</td><td>26.7</td></tr><tr><td>P7</td><td>f</td><td>23</td><td>54</td><td>164</td><td>65.4</td><td>98.3</td><td>1</td><td>12</td><td>91</td><td>24.8</td></tr><tr><td>P8</td><td>f</td><td>25</td><td>75</td><td>172</td><td>69.8</td><td>89.6</td><td>3</td><td>16</td><td>182</td><td>53.6</td></tr><tr><td>P12</td><td>f</td><td>24</td><td>64</td><td>174</td><td>72.5</td><td>86.5</td><td>2</td><td>11</td><td>130</td><td>38.3</td></tr><tr><td>P14</td><td>f</td><td>31</td><td>69</td><td>179</td><td>74.3</td><td>79.9</td><td>5.2</td><td>10</td><td>56</td><td>28.7</td></tr><tr><td>P15</td><td>m</td><td>37</td><td>90</td><td>190</td><td>98.1</td><td>75.3</td><td>2</td><td>9</td><td>304</td><td>86.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>µmol/l</italic> micromole/liter, <italic>ml/min/1.73</italic> <italic>m</italic>² milliliter/minute/1.73 square meters, <italic>mg/l</italic> milligram/liter, <italic>pg/ml</italic> picogram/milliliter, <italic>U/l</italic> units/litre, <italic>µg/l</italic> microgram/liter.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Assessment of hemolysis</title>
                <p id="Par7">The degree of hemolysis in serum samples was determined using two different methods: spectrophotometric analysis of free hemoglobin (414 nm) and quantification of the level of miR-451a relative to the level of miR-23a (hemolysis ratio (ΔCq) = CqmiR-23a – CqmiR-451a), as reported by Blondal et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In our studies both methods were applied. Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a</xref> presents levels for RNA spike-in and cDNA spike-in determined by RT-qPCR. The data indicate homogenous RNA extraction efficiency across all 24 samples and absence of enzyme inhibition. Next the hemolysis miRNA ratio was determined (Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1b</xref>). None of the 24 samples showed a ratio above the report threshold of ΔCq &gt; 7. Next, OD 414 was determined in all samples. Only one sample exceeded an absorbance of 0.3 but did not show a noticeable increase in the hemolysis miRNA ratio (Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1c</xref>). As potential explanation, lipid contaminants but not hemolysis might have increased the OD414 in this sample. Finally, we compared the levels of miR-23a-3p, miR-451a, the hemolysis ratio and OD414 across the three groups (Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1d</xref>). We did not observe a significant difference in the levels of these biomarker and indicators of hemolysis between the respective groups. Interestingly, a trend towards an increase in miR-23a-3p (not responsive to hemolysis) after 24 h was observed. Together, these results demonstrate that the quality of all 24 serum samples was not impaired by hemolysis and adequate for miRNA profiling by next-generation sequencing.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Expression-analysis</title>
                <p id="Par8">Regarding miRNA analysis, 213 miRNAs were robustly (tags per million (TPM) &gt; 5) detected in all eight subjects for each time point. RNA spike-in recovery was assessed by NGS to confirm homogenous RNA extraction efficiency (Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2a</xref>). A summary of sequencing quality data and RNA classification tables are provided in Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3a–g</xref>.</p>
                <p id="Par9">As depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref> (principal component analysis, PCA), a change in the distribution of miRNA expression patterns for each respective timepoint was observed following exposure to gravitational changes. Besides, also donor-dependent differences between individuals were observed, as shown in the expression heatmap (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>), where samples collected at baseline and 1 h cluster for several subjects (P3, P5, P7, P15, and P8). Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref> depicts the same heatmap ordered according to the donor number and time point to better illustrate donor-specific changes in miRNA patterns at 1 and 24 h compared to baseline.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Unsupervised data analysis.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Principal component analysis (PCA) highlights microRNA patterns observed in subjects at baseline (BL), 1 and 24 h after parabolic flight. Data from 213 circulating microRNAs detected in all 24 samples by small RNAseq was used (regularized log tags per million data). The first and second principal component explain 20 and 14% of the variance, respectively. <bold>b</bold> Expression heatmap with unit variance scaling applied to rows (microRNAs). Both rows and columns are clustered using correlation distance and average linkage. Pearson correlation was used as correlation distance. <bold>c</bold> Expression heatmap with unit variance scaling applied to rows (microRNAs). Only rows are clustered using Pearson correlation as measure of distance and average linkage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e1287"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par10">Using the EdgeR GLM model, a significant alteration in miRNA expression (false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.05) was observed for 4 of the 213 miRNAs screened in our analysis 24 h after exposure to gravitational changes compared to baseline values and/or to levels 1 h after parabolic flight (miR-941, miR-24-3p, miR-486-5p, and miR-223-3p; Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, no significant differences in miRNA expression were observed between baseline values and levels 1 h after parabolic flight after adjusting for multiple testing (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Volcano plot illustrating the effect of gravitational changes on serum levels of 213 miRNAs detected and quantified by next-generation sequencing.</title><p>Plot depicts the relation between unadjusted <italic>p</italic>-value (<italic>y</italic>-axis, −log10 transformed) and effect size (<italic>x</italic>-axis, log<sub>2</sub> transformed fold change) for serum microRNA of subjects at 1 h compared to baseline. MicroRNAs with a log<sub>2</sub> fold change &gt; 0.57 (1.5 fold linear change) are indicated in green. MicroRNAs with an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value (FDR) of &lt; 0.05 are highlighted in red. FDR false discovery rate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e1328"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Volcano plot illustrating the effect of gravitational changes on serum levels of 213 miRNAs detected and quantified by next-generation sequencing.</title><p>Plot depicts the relation between unadjusted <italic>p</italic>-value (<italic>y</italic>-axis, −log10 transformed) and effect size (<italic>x</italic>-axis, log<sub>2</sub> transformed fold change) for serum microRNA of subjects at 24 h compared to baseline. MicroRNAs with a log<sub>2</sub> fold change &gt; 0.57 (1.5 fold linear change) are indicated in green. MicroRNAs with an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value (FDR) of &lt; 0.05 are highlighted in red. FDR false discovery rate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e1358"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Volcano plot illustrating the effect of gravitational changes on serum levels of 213 miRNAs detected and quantified by next-generation sequencing.</title><p>Plot depicts the relation between unadjusted <italic>p</italic>-value (<italic>y</italic>-axis, −log10 transformed) and effect size (<italic>x</italic>-axis, log<sub>2</sub> transformed fold change) for serum microRNA of subjects at 24 h compared to 1h. MicroRNAs with a log<sub>2</sub> fold change &gt; 0.57 (1.5 fold linear change) are indicated in green. MicroRNAs with an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value (FDR) of &lt; 0.05 are highlighted in red. FDR false discovery rate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig4_HTML" id="d30e1388"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par11">As depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, after adjusting for multiple testing, miR-223-3p was the only miRNA to show a consistent significant change by means of a decrease 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at baseline and 1 h after parabolic flight. miR-24-3p and miR-941 showed a significant decrease at 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at 1 h after parabolic flight but not to baseline values. Inversely, miR-486-5p evidenced a significant increase at 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at 1 h after parabolic flight but again not to baseline levels. The detailed results of the EdgeR GLM method together with Benjamini–Hochberg adjustment for multiple testing are depicted in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. A list of all miRNAs with TPM &gt; 5 that were identified at each time point for each sample is depicted in Supplement Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Levels of miRNAs with significant changes after 24 h compared to baseline or 1 h.</title><p>EdgeR GLM method together with Benjamini–Hochberg adjustment for multiple testing. *adj-<italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05, **adj-<italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig5_HTML" id="d30e1419"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>miRNA expression analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Abundance</th><th colspan="3">1 h vs. Baseline</th><th colspan="3">24 h vs. Baseline</th><th colspan="3">24 h vs. 1 h</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>microRNA ID</td><td>Avg TPM</td><td>logFC</td><td><italic>p</italic> value</td><td>FDR</td><td>logFC</td><td><italic>p</italic> value</td><td>FDR</td><td>logFC</td><td><italic>p</italic> value</td><td>FDR</td></tr><tr><td>hsa-miR-223-3p</td><td>563</td><td>0,61</td><td>0.18</td><td>0.98</td><td>−1.86</td><td>&lt;0.01</td><td>0.02</td><td>−2.47</td><td>&lt;0.01</td><td>&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td>hsa-miR-24-3p</td><td>364</td><td>0.31</td><td>0.21</td><td>0.98</td><td>−0.52</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.62</td><td>−0.83</td><td>&lt;0.01</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>hsa-miR-486-5p</td><td>698.389</td><td>−0.69</td><td>0.01</td><td>0.98</td><td>0.42</td><td>0.13</td><td>0.78</td><td>1.11</td><td>&lt;0.01</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td>hsa-miR-941</td><td>686</td><td>0.24</td><td>0.37</td><td>0.98</td><td>−0.68</td><td>0.01</td><td>0.58</td><td>−0.92</td><td>&lt;0.01</td><td>0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Avg TPM</italic> average tags per million, <italic>logFC</italic> log fold change, <italic>FDR</italic> false discovery rate.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par12">In order to provide further evidence for the robustness of the NGS data, we have repeated the analysis of four miRNAs with significant (FDR &lt; 0.05) change by RT-qPCR (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Again, miR223-3p was the only miRNA to show a consistent significant change with a decrease at 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at baseline and 1 h after parabolic flight. miR-941 evidenced a significant decrease at 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at 1 h after parabolic flight but not to baseline values. miR-486-5p evidenced a significant increase 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at 1 h after parabolic flight but not to baseline levels. In contrast, no significant change but only a trend towards a decrease was observed for miR-24-3p at 24 h after parabolic flight compared to levels at 1 h after parabolic flight.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Technical verification of NGS results by RT-qPCR. Three miRNAs were selected for RT-qPCR analysis.</title><p>Normalized delta Cq-values (ΔCq) values to the RNA spike-in as internal standard are shown. *adj-<italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05, **adj-<italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig6_HTML" id="d30e1664"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Correlation analysis</title>
                <p id="Par13">In a correlation analysis on baseline characteristics, we found no relevant correlations between miRNA expression and gender, age, or body mass index (BMI). Additionally, no relevant correlations were observed regarding miRNA expression and laboratory parameters. The detailed correlation analysis is given in the supplement Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> (miR-486-5p), 3 (miR-24-3p), 4 (miR-223-3p), and 5 (miR-941).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Target network analysis</title>
                <p id="Par14">We performed a target network analysis for the four differentially regulated miRNAs using miRNet. We identified that genes from two KEGG pathways, the p53 signaling pathway (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and the cell cycle (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) were highly enriched (hypergeometric test and empirical sampling) among the targets of the four microRNAs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and Supplement table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). We observed that TP53 and E2F1 (miR-223-3p and miR-24-3p), and CDK4 (miR-24-3p and miR-486-5p) were targeted by two of the four miRNAs. All other genes were only targeted by one miRNA. miR-24-3p was found to be the most important regulator of both pathways. A detailed list of genes regulated by at least one of the four miRNAs is given in the Supplement Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref><xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">a</xref> (p53) and 7b (cell cycle).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Target network analysis.</title><p>Target network analysis for the four differentially regulated miRNAs—p53 signaling pathway (blue), cell cycle (green).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41526_2020_121_Fig7_HTML" id="d30e1706"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par15">In this study, we present an analysis of the expression profile of circulating miRNAs following exposure to gravitational changes induced by parabolic flight as a space-flight analog. Exposure to weightlessness induces adaptations in autoregulatory mechanisms and functions of virtually all organs, with the cardiovascular system being responsible for most severe complications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Adaptations to microgravity have been reported in previous studies especially in the cardiovascular field. First studies showing an alteration of miRNA expression in T-cell activation as well as a change in miRNA signature potentially influencing TGF-Beta response and fibroblast growth suggest a weightlessness induced change in micro-RNA expression patterns as a potential explanation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par16">In contrast to recent research targeting miRNA expression following spaceflight and exposure to gravitational changes, our study aimed for the analysis of circulating miRNAs from serum. Accordingly, our results reflect the secretion of circulating miRNAs following exposure to gravitational changes but limited conclusion can be drawn with regards to definite intracellular processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Thus, also direct comparability of our results with former projects is limited<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par17">In our study, four miRNAs, miR-941, miR-24-3p, miR-486-5p, and miR-223-3p evidenced a significant change following exposure to gravitational changes after adjusting for multiple testing. Of note, only miR-223-3p showed a consistent significant decrease 24 h after parabolic flight compared to both baseline levels and levels 1 h after parabolic flight. For the rest of the miRNAs, significant changes were only observed between 1 and 24 h. Accordingly, the effect of these changes is assumed to be lower compared to miR-223-3p. However, the results of the RT-qPCR analyses in our study point emphasize the consistency of our results. Of note, hemolysis was ruled out as a potential confounder by spectrophotometric analysis of free hemoglobin (414 nm) as well as by quantification of the level of miR-451a relative to the level of miR-23a in our samples. Hence, the possibility of our findings being not a directional biological effect, but the product of noise variability is highly unlikely. Thus, given the hypothesis generating design, the miRNAs identified in our analysis might provide important hints towards adaptational processes despite their low dynamic.</p>
              <p id="Par18">Since different timepoints were defined for miRNA analysis, an influence by means of a circadian dynamic of miRNA expression must be considered. For two of the biomarkers mentioned above, a diurnal secretion pattern has been reported, miR-223-3p and miR-24-3p. For miR-223-3p peak-levels were observed at 11:38 a.m., for miR-24-3p peak levels were observed at 12:23 according to Heegaard et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. However, with regards to a diurnal secretion, it is important to note that the reported circadian changes in miRNA expression are low, and are by far surpassed by the changes observed following exposure to parabolic flight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Thus, changes in miRNA expression during 24 h in normal conditions are unlikely as a relevant confounder<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Accordingly, the influence on the other two miRNAs miR-941 and miR-486-5p, which were not included in previous studies on diurnal expression changes is assumed to be negligible.</p>
              <p id="Par19">With regards to previous studies, miR-223-3p is known to be involved in myocardial injury and positively correlates with cardiac apoptosis and oxidative stress through interaction with krüppel-like factor 15 (KLF-15). Furthermore, an inverse correlation of miR-223-3p with an improved cell viability, prevention of cardiomyocyte apoptosis as well as with inhibition of reactive oxygen species and lipid peroxidation was shown in a former study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Similar, elevated levels of miR-223-3p were reported under simulated microgravity in rats with an inhibitory effect on hepatocyte proliferation trough a cyclin dependent kinase 2/Cullin1 (CDK2/CUL1) signaling pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par20">For miR-941, a significant upregulation in acute coronary syndrome was reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. As miR-941 is associated with metabolic processes, inflammation and cell proliferation through its role in insulin-activated, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)—and T-cell receptor signaling, a connection with atherosclerosis was suggested as a potential explanation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Additionally an involvement in proliferative processes and cell migration was reported in recent studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. miR-941 expression levels have been shown to be elevated in cancer-derived cell lines and human embryonic stem cells and might also be involved in neuronal development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. A balancing effect of tumor suppressing P73 antisense RNA 1 T (TP73-AS1) by means of a miR-941 sponge was observed, emphasizing its proliferative aspect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par21">miR-24-3p is known to be involved in cell proliferation and migration as well as inhibition of apoptosis in several malignancies such as lung cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma, and colon cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Accordingly, miR-24-3p acts as a regulator of cell proliferation and apoptosis. Another study investigated the role of miR-24-3p in a murine cardiac ischemia-reperfusion model. A cardioprotective effect of miR-24-3p through an inhibition of receptor-interacting serine/threonine-protein kinase 1 (RIPK1) is suspected, correlating with a significant reduction in infarct size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the same study showed an inverse correlation of miR-24-3p with the rate of apoptosis and the levels of Fas and tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par22">miR-486-5p was investigated in various malignant diseases and mostly acts as a regulator of tumor-suppressor-genes. Negative regulations of NIMA-related kinase 2 (NEK2) in hepatocellular carcinoma and a repression of GRB2-associated-binding protein 2 (GAB2) in nonsmall cell lung cancer have been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Besides its role in malignant processes, miR-486-5p was investigated in ischemic kidney injury and seems to attenuate ischemic effects in the kidney by targeting the phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN) and the Akt pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par23">Regarding potential pathways involved in our findings discussed above, a target network analysis identified that genes from two KEGG pathways, the p53 signaling pathway and the cell cycle were highly enriched among the targets of the four microRNAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. We observed that TP53 and E2F1 (miR-223-3p and miR-24-3p), and CDK4 (miR-24-3p and miR-486-5p) were targeted by two miRNAs. All other genes were targeted by only one miRNA. Accordingly, the interaction between the four miRNAs in the regulation of the p53 signaling pathway and the cell cycle are considered to be low. However, despite the high enrichment it must be pointed out that both pathways mentioned above are highly studied and annotated. Thus, they have a high likelihood of being linked with a selected group of miRNAs.</p>
              <p id="Par24">Interestingly, the findings of our study are in part consistent with former findings of a reduction in cell proliferation and a higher rate of apoptosis of in vitro and in vivo studies on changes in miRNA expression following exposure to microgravity. In vitro an altered expression pattern of miRNAs in human peripheral blood lymphocytes was shown to increase apoptosis and decrease cell proliferation following exposure to microgravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. A recent study reported a decrease in TGF-Beta response and a change in miRNA signature as potential regulators of weightlessness induced changes in rodents. Above all, a reduction in cell proliferation and a higher rate of apoptosis was reported, matching prior in vitro studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Furthermore, an upregulation of miR-21 was reported to limit immune-response through a regulation of T-cell activation in microgravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. A change in the expression pattern of immune-related miRNAs was also reported as a potential link to skeletal muscle atrophy in another investigation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Of note, all studies mentioned above were conducted in cellular miRNAs.</p>
              <p id="Par25">Considering the novelty but also the hypothesis generating character of our study, we can only speculate about the potential adaptational processes following exposure to gravitational changes due to the hypothesis generating design of our study. Despite limited comparability with former studies, our results suggest an involvement in cardioprotective mechanisms as well as myocardial strain and the susceptibility for ischemic damage. Furthermore, cell-proliferation and apoptosis and possibly also the immune-system might be influenced by gravitational changes. As a rationale, a change in activation of DNA-repair mechanisms, a change in apoptotic processes and in the regulation of cell cycle progression and cell fate decision can be taken into consideration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Potential implications of our findings are to be further validated and elucidated. However, analysis of the expression of circulating miRNAs might prove of further relevance for space medicine in the future, similar to the application of miRNA expression patterns in other extreme situations as for example in intensive care patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par26">With regards to the limitations of the present study, the hypothesis generating character must be emphasized. While parabolic flight was reported as a suitable space flight analog, the respective effects of microgravity and hypergravity cannot be distinguished properly in this study. Additionally, as we focused on circulating miRNAs, comparability with former studies conducted on cellular miRNAs is limited. Therefore, the results obtained must be interpreted with care. Additionally, a large part of research on miRNAs focuses on malignancies, thus complicating the interpretation of our results. On the other hand, the strength of the study is its novelty in a unique setting.</p>
              <p id="Par27">In conclusion, the present data indicate an alteration of expression patterns of circulating miRNAs following exposure to gravitational changes. We identified that genes from two KEGG pathways, the p53 signaling pathway and the cell cycle were highly enriched among the targets of the four microRNAs. This might suggest a change in cell cycle regulation as a potential explanation for weightlessness induced changes observed in former studies. Together, these findings point towards an adaption to gravitational changes already at the post-transcriptional level even after short term exposure, providing an important framework for future studies in this area.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p id="Par28">Eight healthy participants were enrolled in this study. All voluntary participants were recruited and included at the University Clinic Düsseldorf after written informed consent. The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. The study protocol was approved by the German Ethics Committee (Medical Faculty of the University Hospital Duesseldorf, Germany) and by the French Ethics Committee (Medical Faculty of the University of Caen). The inclusion criteria were defined as: age &gt;18 years; airworthiness; cardiorespiratory health; spontaneous circulation; signed informed consent. The exclusion criteria were defined as: history of primary cardiovascular and respiratory diseases or regular intake of medication except for oral contraceptives, missing or withdrawal of informed consent, insufficient requirements for airworthiness and pregnancy. Further details have been published in a study-outline paper<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Parabolic flight</title>
                <p id="Par29">The term “Parabolic flight” denominates a special aerial manoeuvre, in which the aircraft follows the trajectory of a parabola. By means of this manoeuvre, short phases of weightlessness and hypergravity can be induced. After starting at steady flight (1 g), an up to 47° ascent initiates a phase of hypergravity (1.8 g). After the climb, the plane is decelerated and directed into descent to follow the trajectory. In this state, a phase of weightlessness is achieved (0 g). With the plane tilting forward, an up to 45° descent is initiated, again inducing a phase of hypergravity (1.8 g), before re-entering the steady flight (1 g)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Each of these phases averages 20–25 s, respectively.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Set-up</title>
                <p id="Par30">The present study was performed in the course of the 31st Parabolic Flight Campaign (PFC) of the German space agency (Deutsches Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt - DLR) conducted by the company NoveSpace, which took place from February 26th to March 11th 2018, in Bordeaux, France. The aircraft used in this campaign was a modified Airbus A-310. The PFC consisted of four flight days, with 31 parabolic flight manoeuvres per flight day. Each study subject participated in one complete flight day. In all participants serum samples were withdrawn before entering the plane 1 h prior parabolic flight (baseline 08:00 ± 0.75 h), 1 h after parabolic flight (13:00 ± 1.0 h) and 24 h after parabolic flight 08:00 ± 0.75 h). At each of the time points, serum samples were collected with individual punctures. For each blood withdraw, the following materials were used: BD vacutainer tubes (Becton Dickinson, Mountain View, CA), 3 SST tubes (Reference # 367957, Tube size: 75 × 13 mm, draw volume: 3.5 ml), 1 SST tube (Reference # 367955, Tube size: 100 × 13 mm, Draw volume: 5 ml. After completion of each blood-draw, blood was stored at room-temperature for 3 min. Afterwards, centrifugation at 2000×<italic>g</italic> for 7 min was conducted. Following centrifugation, serum samples aliquots were frozen and stored at −80 °C until further analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec13">
                <title>Total RNA extraction</title>
                <p id="Par31">Serum samples were thawed at room temperature followed by centrifugation at 12,000×<italic>g</italic> for 5 min at 4 °C to remove any cellular debris. Extraction was conducted by use of the miRNA easy QIAgen kit. For homogenization, 200 µl of serum were mixed with 1000 µl Qiazol and 1 µl of a mix of three synthetic spike-in controls (Qiagen, Germany). After a 10-min incubation at room temperature, 200 µl chloroform were added to the lysates followed by cooled centrifugation at 12,000×<italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4 °C. Precisely 650 µl of the upper aqueous phase were mixed with 7 µl glycogen (50 mg/ml) to enhance precipitation. Samples were transferred to a miRNeasy mini column, and RNA was precipitated with 750 µl ethanol followed by automated washing with RPE and RWT buffer in a QiaCube liquid handling robot. Finally, total RNA was eluted in 30 µl nuclease free water and stored at −80 °C until further analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec14">
                <title>Small RNA sequencing</title>
                <p id="Par32">Equal volumes of total RNA (2 µl) were used for small RNA library preparation using the CleanTag smallRNA library preparation kit (TriLink Biotechnologies, US). Homogeneity of RNA extraction efficiencies across all samples was confirmed by RT-qPCR (Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2B</xref>). Adapter-ligated libraries were amplified using barcoded Illumina reverse primers in combination with the Illumina forward primer. Twenty-four PCR cycles were used for library preparation according to the manufacturers recommendation for low RNA input samples. A pool consisting of all 24 sequencing libraries was prepared by mixing samples at equimolar rates on the basis of a DNA-1000 high-sensitivity bioanalyzer results (Agilent, CA). The DNA library pool was gel-purified to enrich for microRNAs with an insert size of 18–24 nt, corresponding to a library size of approximately 145 bp (Supplement Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2B</xref>).</p>
                <p id="Par33">Sequencing was performed on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 with 50 bp single-end runs. Overall quality of the next-generation sequencing data was evaluated automatically and manually with fastQC v0.11.8<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> and multiQC v1.7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Reads from all passing samples were adapter trimmed and quality filtered using cutadapt v2.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> and filtered for a minimum length of 17 nt. Mapping steps were performed with bowtie v1.2.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> and miRDeep2 v2.0.1.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, whereas reads were mapped first against the genomic reference GRCh38.p12 provided by Ensembl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> allowing for two mismatches. Those reads showing a genome alignment were subsequently mapped against miRbase v22.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, filtered for miRNAs of hsa only, allowing for one mismatch. For a general RNA composition overview, nonmiRNA mapped reads were mapped against RNAcentral<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> and then assigned to various RNA species of interest.</p>
                <p id="Par34">Raw and normalized data were uploaded to NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> and are accessible through GEO Series accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE147380">GSE147380</ext-link>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec15">
                <title>Assessment of hemolysis</title>
                <p id="Par35">As lysis of red blood cells (hemolysis) could confound the analysis of circulating microRNAs due to the release of miRNAs from red blood cells, an assessment of hemolysis was conducted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. In order to determine the degree of hemolysis two methods were applied: First, 2 µl of serum were loaded on a NanoDrop spectrophotometer to determine absorbance at 414 nm (free hemoglobin). Secondly, miR-23a-3p and miR-451a were analyzed by RT-qPCR and the hemolysis miRNA ratio according to Blondal et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> was calculated: ΔCq = CqmiR-23a-3p – CqmiR-451a.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec16">
                <title>Reverse transcription and qPCR (RT-qPCR)</title>
                <p id="Par36">The identical RNA samples that were used for NGS analysis, were used for results verification by RT-qPCR. Starting from total RNA samples, cDNA was synthesized using the miRCURY RT Kit (Qiagen, Germany). Reaction conditions were set according to recommendations by the manufacturer. In total, 2 µl of total RNA were used per 10 µl reverse transcription (RT) reaction. To monitor RT efficiency and presence of impurities with inhibitory activity, a synthetic RNA spike-in (cel-miR-39-3p) was added to the RT reaction. Validated LNA-enhanced forward and reverse miRCURY primer assays for all targets, including spike-in controls, were obtained from Qiagen. PCR amplification was performed in a 96-well plate format in a Roche LC480 II instrument (Roche, Germany) using miRCURY SYBR® Green mix (Qiagen, Germany) with the following settings: 95 °C for 10 min, 45 cycles of 95 °C for 10 s, and 60 °C for 60 s, followed by melting curve analysis. To calculate the cycle of quantification values (<italic>Cq</italic>-values), the second derivative method was used. <italic>Cq</italic>-values were normalized to the RNA spike-in control level, by subtracting the individual miRNA <italic>Cq</italic>-value from the RNA Spike-In Cq, thus obtaining delta-Cq (Δ<italic>Cq</italic>) values that were used for the analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec17">
                <title>Target network analysis</title>
                <p id="Par37">Target network analysis was conducted using miRNet (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirnet.ca">www.mirnet.ca</ext-link>), a public and web-based tool that allows to visualize the intersections between individual miRNA regulatory functions based on miRNA-target interaction data from 11 databases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. miRbase miRNA IDs for the differentially regulated miRNAs were uploaded. Since cell-free circulating miRNAs were analyzed no tissue background was selected (“exosomes” were not selected since most miRNAs in serum are in protein complexes). A “hypergeometric test” and “empirical sampling” were performed to identify gene pathways enriched among the identified targets.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec18">
                <title>Statistics</title>
                <p id="Par38">Statistical analysis of preprocessed NGS data was done with R v3.6 and the packages pheatmap v1.0.12, pcaMethods v1.78 and genefilter v1.68. Differential expression analysis with edgeR v3.28<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> used the quasi-likelihood negative binomial generalized log-linear model (GLM) functions provided by the package. FDR correction was performed to adjust for multiple testing, and a cut-off of FDR &lt; 5% was applied<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. No paired testing model in EdgeR was applied. Significance of differentially regulated miRNAs (according to EdgeR) was determined by using EdgeR GLM method together with Benjamini–Hochberg adjustment for multiple testing. An FDR of &lt;5% was considered statistically significant. Repeated measures ANOVA analysis combined with Tukey’s multiple comparison test was used to assess RT-qPCR data. Regarding baseline characteristics and laboratory parameters, analysis was conducted using SPSS 25 (IBM SPSS Statistics, USA). Non-normally distributed data are given as median + interquartile range (IQR). Categorical data are given in number (%). Correlation analysis were performed using Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient. A <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant for comparison of baseline characteristics and correlation analysis. All tests were two-sided.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec19">
                <title>Reporting summary</title>
                <p id="Par39">Further information on research design is available in the <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">Nature Research Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary information</title>
              <sec id="Sec20">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
                  <media xlink:href="41526_2020_121_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
                    <caption>
                      <p>Supplementary Information</p>
                    </caption>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
                  <media xlink:href="41526_2020_121_MOESM2_ESM.pdf">
                    <caption>
                      <p>Reporting Summary</p>
                    </caption>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec>
              <title>Supplementary information</title>
              <p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41526-020-00121-9.</p>
            </sec>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>We would like to thank the German Aerospace centre (DLR) as well as the German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Energy for provision by means of support and funding for the conduction of the outlined study. Furthermore, we would like to thank NoveSpace (France) and TAmiRNA GmbH (Austria) where the small RNA NGS analysis was conducted with special thanks to Matthias Hackl as well as all study participants and investigators involved in this project, for their ongoing effort and support.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>P.J.: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, software, validation, visualization, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing; M.L.: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, resources, software, writing—review and editing; B.W.: data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, resources, software, statistics, visualization, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing; M.F.: Conceptualization, resources, validation, visualization, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing; T.K.: Data curation, investigation, project administration, resources, software, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing; T.A.: Data curation, investigation, project administration, resources, software, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing; M.K.: Conceptualization, methodology, resources, writing—review and editing; N.-Y.B.-B.: Conceptualization, data curation, funding acquisition, investigation, methodology, project administration, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing; C.J.: Conceptualization, data curation, funding acquisition, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, validation, visualization, writing—original draft, writing—review and editing.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability</title>
              <p>The datasets of raw and normalized generated and analysed during the current study are were uploaded to NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> and are accessible through GEO Series accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE147380">GSE147380</ext-link>.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p id="Par40">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yaqub</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Space travel: medicine in extremes</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Respir. Med.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>21</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70192-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25466547?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466547</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hughes-Fulford</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>To infinity… and beyond! Human spaceflight and life science</article-title>
                  <source>Faseb J.</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>2858</fpage>
                  <lpage>2864</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.11-0902ufm</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21880668?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21880668</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Convertino</surname>
                      <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Status of cardiovascular issues related to space flight: Implications for future research directions</article-title>
                  <source>Respir. Physiol. Neurobiol.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>169</volume>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resp.2009.04.010</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hughson</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular regulation during long-duration spaceflights to the International Space Station</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <volume>112</volume>
                  <fpage>719</fpage>
                  <lpage>727</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.01196.2011</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lathers</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acute hemodynamic responses to weightlessness in humans</article-title>
                  <source>J. Clin. Pharm.</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>615</fpage>
                  <lpage>627</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1552-4604.1989.tb03390.x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Norsk</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asmar</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Damgaard</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Christensen</surname>
                      <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fluid shifts, vasodilatation and ambulatory blood pressure reduction during long duration spaceflight</article-title>
                  <source>J. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>593</volume>
                  <fpage>573</fpage>
                  <lpage>584</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2014.284869</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25774397?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25774397</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blaber</surname>
                      <given-names>AP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zuj</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goswami</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cerebrovascular autoregulation: lessons learned from spaceflight research</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>113</volume>
                  <fpage>1909</fpage>
                  <lpage>1917</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-012-2539-x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23132388?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23132388</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pietsch</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effects of weightlessness on the human organism and mammalian cells</article-title>
                  <source>Curr. Mol. Med.</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <lpage>364</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/156652411795976600</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21568935?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21568935</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crawford-Young</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of microgravity on cell cytoskeleton and embryogenesis</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Dev. Biol.</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <lpage>191</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1387/ijdb.052077sc</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16479487?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479487</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zuj</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impaired cerebrovascular autoregulation and reduced CO(2) reactivity after long duration spaceflight</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>302</volume>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00029.2012</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Upregulation of miR-223 in the rat liver inhibits proliferation of hepatocytes under simulated microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>Exp. Mol. Med.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emm.2017.80</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bimpong-Buta</surname>
                      <given-names>NY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Blood parameter analysis after short term exposure to weightlessness in parabolic flight</article-title>
                  <source>Clin. Hemorheol. Microcirc.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>CH-189314</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Beheshti, A., Ray, S., Fogle, H., Berrios, D. &amp; Costes, S. V. A microRNA signature and TGF-beta1 response were identified as the key master regulators for spaceflight response. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>13</bold>, e0199621 (2018).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hughes-Fulford</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chang</surname>
                      <given-names>TT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martinez</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>CF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spaceflight alters expression of microRNA during T-cell activation</article-title>
                  <source>Faseb J.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>4893</fpage>
                  <lpage>4900</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.15-277392</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26276131?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26276131</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transient gene and microRNA expression profile changes of confluent human fibroblast cells in spaceflight</article-title>
                  <source>Faseb J.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>2211</fpage>
                  <lpage>2224</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201500121</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26917741?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26917741</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Armand-Labit</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pradines</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Circulating cell-free microRNAs as clinical cancer biomarkers</article-title>
                  <source>Biomol. Concepts</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <lpage>81</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/bmc-2017-0002</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28448269?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28448269</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mirna, M. et al. MicroRNAs in inflammatory heart diseases and sepsis-induced cardiac dysfunction: a potential scope for the future? <italic>Cells</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1352 (2019).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeng</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Principles of micro-RNA production and maturation</article-title>
                  <source>Oncogene</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>6156</fpage>
                  <lpage>6162</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1209908</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17028594?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028594</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortez</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MicroRNAs in body fluids–the mix of hormones and biomarkers</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Rev. Clin. Oncol.</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
                  <lpage>477</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrclinonc.2011.76</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21647195?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21647195</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cui, M. et al. Circulating microRNAs in cancer: potential and challenge. <italic>Front. Genet.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 626 (2019).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bell</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taylor</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Functional roles for exosomal microRNAs in the tumour microenvironment</article-title>
                  <source>Comput. Struct. Biotechnol. J.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <lpage>13</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2016.10.005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27872688?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27872688</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reichholf</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Time-resolved small RNA sequencing unravels the molecular principles of MicroRNA homeostasis</article-title>
                  <source>Mol. Cell</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <fpage>756</fpage>
                  <lpage>768</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2019.06.018</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31350118?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31350118</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blondal</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessing sample and miRNA profile quality in serum and plasma or other biofluids</article-title>
                  <source>Methods</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>59</volume>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2012.09.015</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Limper</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interactions of the human cardiopulmonary, hormonal and body fluid systems in parabolic flight</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>114</volume>
                  <fpage>1281</fpage>
                  <lpage>1295</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-014-2856-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24623065?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24623065</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heegaard, N. H. et al. Diurnal variations of human circulating cell-free Micro-RNA. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>11</bold>, e0160577 (2016).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Absence of miR-223-3p ameliorates hypoxia-induced injury through repressing cardiomyocyte apoptosis and oxidative stress by targeting KLF15</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. J. Pharm.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>841</volume>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <lpage>74</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2018.10.014</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bai</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>miR-941 as a promising biomarker for acute coronary syndrome</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Cardiovasc. Disord.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>017</fpage>
                  <lpage>0653</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12872-017-0653-8</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recently evolved tumor suppressor transcript TP73-AS1 functions as sponge of human-specific miR-941</article-title>
                  <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>1063</fpage>
                  <lpage>1077</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy022</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29474580?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29474580</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hu, H. Y. et al. Evolution of the human-specific microRNA miR-941. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>3</bold>, 1–10 (2012).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yan</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>miR-24-3p promotes cell migration and proliferation in lung cancer by targeting SOX7</article-title>
                  <source>J. Cell Biochem.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <fpage>3989</fpage>
                  <lpage>3998</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.26553</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29231262?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29231262</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeng</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Le</surname>
                      <given-names>YG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xin</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>LncRNA CASC2 inhibited the viability and induced the apoptosis of hepatocellular carcinoma cells through regulating miR-24-3p</article-title>
                  <source>J. Cell Biochem.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <fpage>6391</fpage>
                  <lpage>6397</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.26479</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29091305?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091305</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dong</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MiR-24-3p enhances cell growth in hepatocellular carcinoma by targeting metallothionein 1M</article-title>
                  <source>Cell Biochem. Funct.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>491</fpage>
                  <lpage>496</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbf.3213</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27650047?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27650047</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MicroRNA-24-3p attenuates myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury by suppressing RIPK1 expression in mice</article-title>
                  <source>Cell Physiol. Biochem.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <lpage>62</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000495161</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30439713?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30439713</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MiR-486-5p negatively regulates oncogenic NEK2 in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>
                  <source>Oncotarget</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>52948</fpage>
                  <lpage>52959</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.17635</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28881785?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28881785</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geng</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>miR-486-5p inhibits cell proliferation and invasion through repressing GAB2 in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>
                  <source>Oncol. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>3525</fpage>
                  <lpage>3530</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30127957?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30127957</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinas</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transfer of microRNA-486-5p from human endothelial colony forming cell-derived exosomes reduces ischemic kidney injury</article-title>
                  <source>Kidney Int.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>90</volume>
                  <fpage>1238</fpage>
                  <lpage>1250</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.kint.2016.07.015</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27650731?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27650731</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kanehisa</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goto</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.27</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10592173?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Girardi</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Integration analysis of microRNA and mRNA expression profiles in human peripheral blood lymphocytes cultured in modeled microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>Biomed. Res. Int.</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>296747</volume>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Teodori, L., Costa, A., Campanella, L. &amp; Albertini, M. C. Skeletal muscle atrophy in simulated microgravity might be triggered by immune-related microRNAs. <italic>Front. Physiol.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 1926 (2019).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Engeland</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cell cycle arrest through indirect transcriptional repression by p53: I have a DREAM</article-title>
                  <source>Cell Death Differ.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <lpage>132</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cdd.2017.172</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29125603?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29125603</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barnum, K. J. &amp; O’Connell, M. J. Cell cycle regulation by checkpoints. <italic>Methods Mol. Biol.</italic> 0888-0882_0882 (2014).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masyuk</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prognostic relevance of serum lactate kinetics in critically ill patients</article-title>
                  <source>Intensive Care Med.</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <lpage>61</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-018-5475-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30478622?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30478622</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bimpong-Buta</surname>
                      <given-names>NY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis of human microcirculation in weightlessness: Study protocol and pre-study experiments</article-title>
                  <source>Clin. Hemorheol. Microcirc.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <lpage>127</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/CH-170366</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29710687?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29710687</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shelhamer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Parabolic flight as a spaceflight analog</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl Physiol.</source>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <volume>120</volume>
                  <fpage>1442</fpage>
                  <lpage>1448</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.01046.2015</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Andrews, S. FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link> (2010).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ewels</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magnusson</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lundin</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kaller</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>MultiQC: summarize analysis results for multiple tools and samples in a single report</article-title>
                  <source>Bioinformatics</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>3047</fpage>
                  <lpage>3048</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw354</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 5039924?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27312411</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Martin, M. Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads. <italic>EMBnet</italic>10.14806/ej.17.1.200 (2011).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Langmead</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trapnell</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salzberg</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title>
                  <source>Genome Biol.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>2009</fpage>
                  <lpage>2010</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR49">
                <label>49.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Friedlander</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mackowiak</surname>
                      <given-names>SD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rajewsky</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>miRDeep2 accurately identifies known and hundreds of novel microRNA genes in seven animal clades</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>52</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr688</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21911355?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21911355</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR50">
                <label>50.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zerbino</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ensembl 2018</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>D754</fpage>
                  <lpage>D761</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1098</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29155950?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29155950</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR51">
                <label>51.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griffiths‐Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The microRNA registry</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>D109</fpage>
                  <lpage>D111</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh023</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 14681370?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681370</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR52">
                <label>52.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>The RNAcentral Consortium.</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>RNAcentral: a hub of information for non-coding RNA sequences</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>D221</fpage>
                  <lpage>D229</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1034</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR53">
                <label>53.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barrett</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>NCBI GEO: archive for functional genomics data sets—update</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <fpage>D991</fpage>
                  <lpage>D995</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1193</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23193258?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193258</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR54">
                <label>54.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirschner</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Haemolysis during sample preparation alters microRNA content of plasma</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0024145</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR55">
                <label>55.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>miRNet—dissecting miRNA-target interactions and functional associations through network-based visual analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw861</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR56">
                <label>56.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Robinson</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McCarthy</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smyth</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>K. edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title>
                  <source>Bioinformatics</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <lpage>140</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19910308?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR57">
                <label>57.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benjamini</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hochberg</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>
                  <source>J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <lpage>300</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
