<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:54:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7750487" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7750487</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-23</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bbpr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochem Biophys Rep</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochem Biophys Rep</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Biochemistry and Biophysics Reports</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2405-5808</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7750487</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7750487</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7750487</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33364446</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-5808(20)30185-0</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrep.2020.100875</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100875</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Amyloid fibril formation is suppressed in microgravity</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Matsushita</surname>
                    <given-names>Hiroaki</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <email>hiroakim@niu.ac.jp</email>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Isoguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>Aito</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Okada</surname>
                    <given-names>Masamitsu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Masuda</surname>
                    <given-names>Teruaki</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Misumi</surname>
                    <given-names>Yohei</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ichiki</surname>
                    <given-names>Yuko</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ueda</surname>
                    <given-names>Mitsuharu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ando</surname>
                    <given-names>Yukio</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <email>andoy430@niu.ac.jp</email>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">∗∗</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Amyloidosis Research, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Nagasaki International University, 2825-7 Huis Ten Bosch Sasebo, Nagasaki, 859-3298, Japan</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Neurology, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Kumamoto University, 1-1-1 Honjo, Kumamoto, 860-0811, Japan</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>hiroakim@niu.ac.jp</email></corresp>
                <corresp id="cor2"><label>∗∗</label>Corresponding author. Department of Amyloidosis Research, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Nagasaki International University, 2825-7 Huis Ten Bosch Sasebo, Nagasaki, 859-3298, Japan. <email>andoy430@niu.ac.jp</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>25</volume>
              <elocation-id>100875</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>9</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0010">
                <p>In the future, humans may live in space because of global pollution and weather fluctuations. In microgravity, convection does not occur, which may change the amyloidogenicity of proteins. However, the effect of gravity on amyloid fibril formation is unclear and remains to be elucidated. Here, we analyzed the effect of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation of amyloidogenic proteins including insulin, amyloid β<sub>42</sub> (Aβ<sub>42</sub>), and transthyretin (TTR). We produced microgravity (10<sup>−3</sup> <italic>g</italic>) by using the gravity controller Gravite. Human insulin, Aβ<sub>42</sub>, and human wild-type TTR (TTRwt) were incubated at pH 3.0, 7.0, and 3.5 at 37 °C, respectively, in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground or in microgravity. We measured amyloidogenicity via the thioflavin T (ThT) method and cell-based 1-fluoro-2,5-bis[(<italic>E</italic>)-3-carboxy-4-hydroxystyryl]benzene (FSB) assay. ThT fluorescence intensity and cell-based FSB assay results for human insulin samples were decreased in microgravity compared with results in 1 <italic>g</italic>. Aβ<sub>42</sub> samples did not differ in ThT fluorescence intensity in microgravity and in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground. However, in the cell-based FSB assay, the staining intensity was reduced in microgravity compared with that on 1 <italic>g</italic>. Human TTRwt tended to form fewer amyloid fibrils in ThT fluorescence intensity and cell-based FSB assays in microgravity than in 1 <italic>g</italic>. Human insulin and Aβ<sub>42</sub> showed decreased amyloid fibril formation in microgravity compared with that in 1 <italic>g</italic>. Human TTRwt tended to form fewer amyloid fibrils in microgravity. Our experiments suggest that the earth's gravity may be an accelerating factor for amyloid fibril formation.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0015">
                <title>Highlights</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010">
                    <list-item id="u0010">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0010">Soon, humans may live in space where gravity is less than the ground.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="u0015">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0015">In microgravity, amyloidogenic proteins did not form much amyloid fibrils.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="u0020">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0020">Amyloidosis patients are beneficial to live in space.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Insulin</kwd>
                <kwd>Aβ<sub>42</sub></kwd>
                <kwd>TTR</kwd>
                <kwd>Microgravity</kwd>
                <kwd>Amyloidosis</kwd>
                <kwd>Amyloid fibrils</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <kwd-group id="kwrds0015">
                <title>Abbreviations</title>
                <kwd>Aβ, amyloid β</kwd>
                <kwd>DMSO, dimethyl sulfoxide</kwd>
                <kwd>FSB, 1-fluoro-2,5-bis[(<italic>E</italic>)-3-carboxy-4-hydroxystyryl]benzene</kwd>
                <kwd>PBS, phosphate-buffered saline</kwd>
                <kwd>ThT, thioflavin T</kwd>
                <kwd>TTR, transthyretin</kwd>
                <kwd>TTRwt, wild-type transthyretin</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0025">In amyloidosis, is protein metabolism disorder, soluble proteins are deposited as abnormal insoluble fibrils in tissues. Amyloid fibrils are formed by polymerization of the β-sheet conformation of amyloidogenic proteins. Amyloid fibrils are similar to nylon fibrils.</p>
              <p id="p0030">Amyloidosis is a group of hereditary or nonhereditary diseases that are distinguished by extracellular deposition of insoluble amyloid fibrils derived from different proteins in organs such as the eyes, nerves, heart, liver, kidneys [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>]. So far, 37 amyloidogenic proteins have been identified as disease-causing molecules in amyloid-related illnesses such as prion disease, Alzheimer's disease, AA amyloidosis, systemic immunoglobulin light-chain amyloidosis, hereditary transthyretin amyloidosis ATTRv (familial amyloid polyneuropathy), and wild-type transthyretin amyloidosis ATTRwt (senile systemic amyloidosis) [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>]. Aging, genetic mutations, inflammation, obesity, neoplastic disorders, and medical treatments reportedly affect amyloidosis development by means of misfolding, overproduction, and decreased clearance of disease-specific amyloid-related proteins and by proteolysis [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In addition, the protein-protein interaction of amyloidogenic proteins may be important in amyloid fibril formation.</p>
              <p id="p0035">Space medicine has made remarkable progress, and many reports on the effects of gravity on healthy astronauts have been published [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In space, microgravity influences human physiology and pathological conditions including blood pressure, osteogenesis, muscle wasting, obstructive stress, vestibular organs, and radiation effects. However, the relationship of gravity with various diseases has not been clarified. In the amyloid formation mechanism, protein-protein polymerization is indispensable for forming amyloid fibrils. No convection exists in zero gravity and under such conditions, the frequency of the protein-protein interaction may change; microgravity may thus affect amyloidogenicity.</p>
              <p id="p0040">Recently, abnormal weather has been occurring throughout the world; in the future, human beings may live in space. Because of that possibility, we should investigate whether various amyloidoses may be affected by the gravity changes in space.</p>
              <p id="p0045">In this study, we analyzed the effects of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation of amyloidogenic proteins including human insulin, amyloid β<sub>42</sub> (Aβ<sub>42</sub>), and human transthyretin (TTR) by means of the gravity controller Gravite, which produces microgravity in a laboratory on the ground.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="sec2.1">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Amyloid fibril formation of human insulin</title>
                <p id="p0050">Recombinant human insulin solution (Eli Lilly and Company, Indiana, USA) was mixed with an equal volume of 1 mol/L glycine-HCl buffer at pH 3.0 and the 10 μM of insulin was incubated at 37 °C with agitation for 96 h in microgravity controlled by Gravite [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.2">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Amyloid fibril formation of Aβ<sub>42</sub></title>
                <p id="p0055">Samples of 2 μM Aβ<sub>42</sub> (human, 1–42) (Peptide Institute, Inc., Osaka, Japan) were incubated in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) at 37 °C for 24 h in microgravity controlled by Gravite [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.3">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Amyloid fibril formation of human wild-type TTR (TTRwt)</title>
                <p id="p0060">To make acid-induced amorphous aggregates of human TTRwt, we incubated 20 μM recombinant full-length human TTRwt (FUJIFILM Wako Pure Chemical Corporation, Osaka, Japan) at pH 3.5 in 50 mM sodium acetate buffer containing 50 mM NaCl for 48 h at 37 °C, according to methods used in our previous study [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], with samples being incubated in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground and in microgravity.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.4">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Microgravity production</title>
                <p id="p0065">To produce microgravity in the laboratory at 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground, we used the gravity controller Gravite (Space Bio-Laboratories Co., Ltd., Hiroshima, Japan) [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This device produces microgravity similar to gravity in space. The principles of the instrument are summarized briefly as follows: microgravity (10<sup>−3</sup> <italic>g</italic>) was generated by rotating a sample around two axes and integrating the gravity vector and the temporal axis. In 8 min, these specific conditions create a environment of 10<sup>−3</sup> <italic>g</italic> that is measured by the gravity acceleration sensor; and this environment was defined as simulated microgravity [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.5">
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Thioflavin T (ThT) fluorescence assay</title>
                <p id="p0070">During <italic>in vitro</italic> incubations of human insulin, Aβ<sub>42</sub>, or human TTR under each gravity condition, we analyzed ThT fluorescence with a spectrofluorometer (F-2700; Hitachi High Technologies, Tokyo, Japan) and using a quartz cuvette with a 10-mm path length under excitation and emission wavelengths of 445 and 490 nm (insulin and Aβ<sub>42</sub>) and 442 and 489 nm (TTR), respectively. Since each amyloidogenic protein and peptide have different molecular structure, it is more appropriate that TTR experiment should be performed in different excitation and emission lengths. Samples (each 3 μL) were mixed with 600 μL of 5 μM ThT in 50 mM glycine/NaOH buffer, pH 9.5, and were used for measurements, obtained at room temperature [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. We obtained three scans per sample.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.6">
                <label>2.6</label>
                <title>Cell-based 1-fluoro-2,5-bis[(E)-3-carboxy-4-hydroxystyryl]benzene (FSB) assay</title>
                <p id="p0075">In the cell-based FSB assay, we seeded glomotel cells in half-area 96-well culture plates (Greiner Bio-One, Kremunster, Austria) [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. After 24 h, we added human insulin, Aβ<sub>42</sub>, or TTR to the cell culture medium (DMEM, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Massachusetts, USA) and incubated the samples at 37 °C for 24 h. We fixed the cultured cells with 10% formaldehyde neutral buffer solution (Nacalai Tesque, Kyoto, Japan) for 30 min. After we washed the fixed cells with PBS, we stained the cells with 0.0001% FSB in 50% EtOH for 30 min. We washed FSB-stained cells with 50% EtOH once, followed by washing with PBS three times. We analyzed the amount of amyloid in deposits by using the IN Cell Analyzer 2200 (GE Healthcare).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.7">
                <label>2.7</label>
                <title>Statistics</title>
                <p id="p0080">We used the Student <italic>t</italic>-test to identify significant differences between two conditions. <italic>P</italic> values less than 0.01 or 0.05 were considered to be significant. Data are shown as means + SEM.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec3.1">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Effect of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation of human insulin</title>
                <p id="p0085">To examine the effect of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation of human insulin, we incubated the protein at pH 3.0 and at 37 °C in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground or in microgravity (10<sup>−3</sup> <italic>g</italic>). The human insulin samples increased in ThT fluorescence intensity in a time-dependent manner when incubated in 1 <italic>g</italic>. In contrast, intensity values decreased in microgravity (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). In the cell-based FSB assay, the staining intensity was also reduced in microgravity compared with that in 1 <italic>g</italic> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Amyloid fibril formation of human insulin in microgravity and in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground. (A) ThT fluorescence intensity of human insulin. (B) Cell-based FSB assay of human insulin. White and black bars indicate 1 <italic>g</italic> and microgravity, respectively. Data represent means + SEM. **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, vs. the 1 <italic>g</italic> group.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3.2">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Effect of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation of Aβ<sub>42</sub></title>
                <p id="p0090">Samples of Aβ<sub>42</sub> were incubated at pH 7.0 at 37 °C in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground or in microgravity. The ThT fluorescence intensity of the peptide samples did not differ significantly at 24 h in microgravity compared with that in 1 <italic>g</italic> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). However, in the cell-based FSB assay, the staining intensity was significantly reduced at 24 h in microgravity compared with that in 1 <italic>g</italic> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B). After 24 h of incubation, the peptide could not be measured because it formed aggregates in the solution.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Amyloid fibril formation of Aβ<sub>42</sub> in microgravity and in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground. (A) ThT fluorescence intensity of Aβ<sub>42</sub>. (B) Cell-based FSB assay of Aβ<sub>42</sub>. White and black bars indicate 1 <italic>g</italic> and microgravity, respectively. Data represent means + SEM. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. the 1 <italic>g</italic> group.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3.3">
                <label>3.3</label>
                <title>Effect of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation of human TTRwt</title>
                <p id="p0095">Human TTRwt samples were incubated at pH 3.5 at 37 °C in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground or in microgravity. The protein tended to form fewer amyloid fibrils in the ThT fluorescence intensity and cell-based FSB assays in microgravity compared formation in 1 <italic>g</italic> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). At 24 and 96 h of incubation, no obvious differences were observed for results in 1 <italic>g</italic> and in microgravity (data not shown).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Amyloid fibril formation of human TTRwt in microgravity and in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground. (A) ThT fluorescence intensity of human TTR. (B) Cell-based FSB assay of human TTRwt. White and black bars indicate 1 <italic>g</italic> and microgravity, respectively. Data represent means + SEM.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="p0100">That microgravity can be produced either by space flight or by free fall has been well documented. However, such conditions cannot reproduced in test tube experiments in the laboratory. Fortunately, the development of the gravity controller Gravite has allowed production of microgravity conditions in a typical laboratory in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground. Therefore, we were able to investigate the effect of microgravity on amyloid fibril formation in amyloidogenic proteins including human insulin, Aβ<sub>42</sub>, and human TTRwt.</p>
              <p id="p0105">The present study provided the following important findings: (1) Human insulin and Aβ<sub>42</sub> showed significantly suppressed amyloid fibril formation in microgravity compared with that in 1 <italic>g</italic> on the ground. (2) Human TTRwt tended to form fewer amyloid fibrils in microgravity compared with formation in 1 <italic>g</italic>. To form amyloid fibrils, the following conditions are required: induction of structural changes via mutation of amyloidogenic proteins, and a protein-protein (peptide-peptide) interaction, which is indispensable. Our experiments confirmed that microgravity suppressed amyloid fibril formation by reducing the protein-protein interaction via decreased convection.</p>
              <p id="p0110">Why human TTRwt in microgravity alone did not show a significant difference in amyloid formation between 1 <italic>g</italic> and microgravity, compared with data for human insulin and Aβ<sub>42</sub>, is unknown. Because human TTR forms tetramers, the TTR tetramers must dissociate into monomers before amyloid formation of monomeric TTR. TTRwt may be protected against amyloid fibril formation as tetramers even in microgravity. In cell based assay, decrease in TTR aggregation in microgravity tended to be more obvious, suggesting effect of medium, such as albumin may influence the result.</p>
              <p id="p0115">Ueda et al. [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] recently demonstrated that the C-terminal fragment of TTR81-127 did form tetramers and amyloid fibrils at neutral pH. In addition, the variant TTR ATTR V30 M is less stable in tetrameric form than TTRwt [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Therefore, experiments with variant TTR or ATTR V30 M may provide improved results.</p>
              <p id="p0120">Human insulin was able to form amyloid fibrils in 1 <italic>g</italic> because it exists in monomeric form in water-soluble solutions. Our results clearly indicate that microgravity suppressed the amyloid fibril formation, ThT fluorescence intensity, and cell-based FSB assay results of insulin (Fig. 1AB).</p>
              <p id="p0125">Aβ<sub>42</sub> did not show significant differences for 1 <italic>g</italic> and microgravity in the ThT fluorescence intensity assay (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A) because Aβ<sub>42</sub> is hydrophobic and dissolves poorly in water-soluble solutions. Furthermore, Aβ<sub>42</sub> forms aggregates during prolonged incubations. Therefore, we could not extend experiments to more than 24 h of incubation. Recently, a cell-based assay was used to elucidate the effects of amyloid toxicity on cell viability [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Aβ<sub>42</sub> suppressed the staining intensity of the cell-based FSB assay in microgravity compared with 1 <italic>g</italic> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B). We thus suggest that microgravity reduced the toxicity of Aβ<sub>42</sub> through the process of amyloid formation.</p>
              <p id="p0130">In summary, gravity may changed amyloid fibril formation. In microgravity, amyloid fibril formation may be suppressed, and as the results showed, the cytotoxicity of amyloid fibrils may be reduced. We preliminary performed electron microscopic studies for the samples subjected to these experiments. Unfortunately, differences were not obvious, compared to biochemical studies. There is a possibility that biochemical changes may be more sensitive than those of morphology. Further studies are needed. Our experiments suggest that amyloidogenic proteins form fewer amyloid fibrils in microgravity and that patients with amyloidosis may be more suitable than healthy people to live in space.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec5">
              <title>Author statement</title>
              <p id="p0135">Hiroaki Matsushita, data collection and writing a paper. Aito Isoguchi, data collection. Masamitsu Okada, data collection. Teruaki Masuda, data analysis and interpretation. Yohei Misumi, data analysis and interpretation. Yuko Ichiki, data analysis and interpretation. Mitsuharu Ueda, research ideas and designs. Yukio Ando, research ideas and approval of final draft.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec6">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p id="p0140">This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs2">Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research</funding-source> (KAKENHI grant number 19H03565).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec7">
              <title>Ethical approval</title>
              <p id="p0145">Not required.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec8">
              <title>Guarantor</title>
              <p id="p0150">HM.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec9">
              <title>Contributorship</title>
              <p id="p0155">Conception and design of study: HM, AI, Acquisition of data: MO, TM, YM, YI, Drafting the manuscript: MU, and YA.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing interest</title>
              <p id="p0160">The authors have no conflicts of interest relevant to the content of this article.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebib0010">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benson</surname>
                      <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buxbaum</surname>
                      <given-names>J.N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eisenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Amyloid nomenclature 2018: recommendations by the International Society of Amyloidosis (ISA) nomenclature committee</article-title>
                  <source>Amyloid</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <lpage>219</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30614283</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiti</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dobson</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Protein misfolding, amyloid formation, and human disease: a summary of progress over the last decade</article-title>
                  <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
                  <volume>86</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <lpage>68</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28498720</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ueda</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Okada</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizuguchi</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A cell-based high-throughput screening method to directly examine transthyretin amyloid fibril formation at neutral pH</article-title>
                  <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
                  <volume>294</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>11259</fpage>
                  <lpage>11275</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31167790</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ueda</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Horibata</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shono</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinicopathological features of senile systemic amyloidosis: an ante- and post-mortem study</article-title>
                  <source>Mod. Pathol.</source>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>1533</fpage>
                  <lpage>1544</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21822203</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ueda</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ando</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recent advances in transthyretin amyloidosis therapy</article-title>
                  <source>Transl. Neurodegener.</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25228988</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sperry</surname>
                      <given-names>B.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reyes</surname>
                      <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ikram</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tenosynovial and cardiac amyloidosis in patients undergoing carpal tunnel release</article-title>
                  <source>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.</source>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>2040</fpage>
                  <lpage>2050</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30336828</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ando</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coelho</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berk</surname>
                      <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Guideline of transthyretin-related hereditary amyloidosis for clinicians</article-title>
                  <source>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23425518</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williams</surname>
                      <given-names>D.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The biomedical challenges of space flight</article-title>
                  <source>Annu. Rev. Med.</source>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <lpage>256</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471177</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nakamura</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Misumi</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nomura</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Extreme adhesion activity of amyloid fibrils induces subcutaneous insulin resistance</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes</source>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>609</fpage>
                  <lpage>616</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30552107</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shin</surname>
                      <given-names>W.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Di</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cao</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Amyloid β-protein oligomers promote the uptake of tau fibril seeds potentiating intracellular tau aggregation</article-title>
                  <source>Alzheimer's Res. Ther.</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31627745</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lai</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Colón</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelly</surname>
                      <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The acid-mediated denaturation pathway of transthyretin yields a conformational intermediate that can self-assemble into amyloid</article-title>
                  <source>Biochemistry</source>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <fpage>6470</fpage>
                  <lpage>6482</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8639594</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Misumi</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ando</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ueda</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Chain reaction of amyloid fibril formation with induction of basement membrane in familial amyloidotic polyneuropathy</article-title>
                  <source>J. Pathol.</source>
                  <volume>219</volume>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>481</fpage>
                  <lpage>490</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19790249</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Furukawa</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tanimoto</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fukazawa</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Simulated microgravity attenuates myogenic differentiation via epigenetic regulations</article-title>
                  <source>NPJ Microgravity</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29845109</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kawahara</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manabe</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>LIF-free embryonic stem cell culture in simulated microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>PloS One</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>e6343</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19626124</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mitsuhara</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Takeda</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Simulated microgravity facilitates cell migration and neuroprotection after bone marrow stromal cell transplantation in spinal cord injury</article-title>
                  <source>Stem Cell Res. Ther.</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23548163</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tojo</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sekijima</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelly</surname>
                      <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diflunisal stabilizes familial amyloid polyneuropathy-associated transthyretin variant tetramers in serum against dissociation required for amyloidogenesis</article-title>
                  <source>Neurosci. Res.</source>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <lpage>449</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028027</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <ack id="ack0010">
              <title>Acknowledgment</title>
              <p id="p0165">This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research</funding-source> (KAKENHI grant number 19H03565).</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
