<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:55:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7907254" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7907254</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>scirep</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7907254</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7907254</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7907254</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33633331</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">84197</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-84197-7</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Modelling physiology of haemodynamic adaptation in short-term microgravity exposure and orthostatic stress on Earth</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mohammadyari</surname>
                    <given-names>Parvin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gadda</surname>
                    <given-names>Giacomo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>gadda@fe.infn.it</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Taibi</surname>
                    <given-names>Angelo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8484.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 2064</institution-id><institution>Department of Physics and Earth Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Ferrara, </institution></institution-wrap>44122 Ferrara, Italy </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6045.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 5281</institution-id><institution>National Institute for Nuclear Physics (INFN), Section of Ferrara, </institution></institution-wrap>44122 Ferrara, Italy </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>11</volume>
              <elocation-id>4672</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>8</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="OpenAccess">
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <p id="Par1">Cardiovascular haemodynamics alters during posture changes and exposure to microgravity. Vascular auto-remodelling observed in subjects living in space environment causes them orthostatic intolerance when they return on Earth. In this study we modelled the human haemodynamics with focus on head and neck exposed to different hydrostatic pressures in supine, upright (head-up tilt), head-down tilt position, and microgravity environment by using a well-developed 1D-0D haemodynamic model. The model consists of two parts that simulates the arterial (1D) and brain-venous (0D) vascular tree. The cardiovascular system is built as a network of hydraulic resistances and capacitances to properly model physiological parameters like total peripheral resistance, and to calculate vascular pressure and the related flow rate at any branch of the tree. The model calculated 30.0 mmHg (30%), 7.1 mmHg (78%), 1.7 mmHg (38%) reduction in mean blood pressure, intracranial pressure and central venous pressure after posture change from supine to upright, respectively. The modelled brain drainage outflow percentage from internal jugular veins is 67% and 26% for supine and upright posture, while for head-down tilt and microgravity is 65% and 72%, respectively. The model confirmed the role of peripheral veins in regional blood redistribution during posture change from supine to upright and microgravity environment as hypothesized in literature. The model is able to reproduce the known haemodynamic effects of hydraulic pressure change and weightlessness. It also provides a virtual laboratory to examine the consequence of a wide range of orthostatic stresses on human haemodynamics.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
                <title>Subject terms</title>
                <kwd>Circulation</kwd>
                <kwd>Biophysics</kwd>
                <kwd>Physiology</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2021</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par71">Gravity fundamentally affects the blood circulation by altering the vessels pressure, blood flow rate and volume<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Physiological effects of microgravity (μg) on cardiovascular function have been known since the first data from Soviet and American spaceflights were studied<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. It is reported that about 50% of astronauts suffered from orthostatic pressure intolerance in the upright posture after space mission<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The physiological effects of hydrostatic pressure change on different parameters of cardiovascular system have largely been studied on humans and animals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Indeed, there is literature about the hydrostatic stress suffered by subjects living on Earth during posture change from head-down tilt (HDT) to head-up tilt (HUT) angles up to 90°, and by exposing the subjects to weightlessness condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. However, the mechanisms of cardiovascular adaptation to microgravity and posture changes are poorly understood<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par72">In response to the question “When there is no gravity pulling back the blood to heart, how the human body changes the venous drain strategy?”, there is one hypothesis that microgravity venous congestion causes a syndrome in which fluids shift away from legs towards upper limbs and head. This headward fluid shift leads to an augmentation in venous volume and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) which brings facial puffiness and bird legs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Other changes include increase in cardiac output<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, cerebral blood inflow (CBF)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, cerebral blood flow velocity (up to 30%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, cross-section area (CSA) of internal jugular vein (IJV)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, decrease in ICP and central venous pressure (CVP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> during parabolic flight (but no change in mean arterial blood pressure (BP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>) with respect to the supine position on Earth. Noteworthy, changes in CBF and IJV-CSA are introduced as the primary signs of microgravity exposure, and changes in ICP and CVP as the secondary signs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par73">Weightlessness environment eliminates the compressive forces that arose from tissues surrounding the vessel walls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. This fact contributes to increase vascular capacity and to reduce ICP and CVP to lower values than in supine position on Earth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. In the presence of a gravity field, the compliance properties of peripheral vessels allow them to hold a given volume of blood. This tendency remains active also in a microgravity environment, while vascular functionality and peripheral vascular resistance decrease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Therefore, during the landing day the lower total peripheral resistance (TPR) brings intracranial hypotension and syncope in astronauts due to rapid secondary shift of blood to the lower limbs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par74">Earth-based models such as HDT and water immersion are widely used to simulate the effects of microgravity on Earth and perform experiments on cardiovascular function and adaptation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Another possibility is to use parabolic flights in which 20–30 s of weightlessness allow to perform measurements in such a short time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. However, the results highly depends on the study conditions, accuracy of the measurements and the duration of microgravity exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Therefore, results from Earth-based simulations might not be used to infer conclusions about the microgravity environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Moreover, the number of clinical studies is limited due to the lack of standard data collection protocol on older missions, the limited number of space missions and studies on humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. These restrictions, in addition to limitations on Earth-based studies, lead to a poor understanding of the cardiovascular responses to microgravity. For all these reasons, the necessity to have a reliable computed simulation tool is highlighted in this framework<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p>
              <p id="Par75">Cardiovascular mathematical modelling is a useful method to study the human physiology and anatomy, and it is also used to plan and execute interventional procedures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. An important advantage of computational modelling is that it provides a virtual laboratory and allows the exploration of a wide range of orthostatic stresses and their complex physiological chain of events on the intra- and extracranial compartments at a low medical and computational cost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Many valuable models of the cerebral circulation (like the works of Gisolf et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and Buckey et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>) focused on intracranial segments and related control mechanisms, by providing a simplified description of the main arterial inflow and extracranial venous return. Whole body models such as the one developed by Zhang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> and Gallo et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> do not include brain compartments, and only the main outflow routes (IJV and VV) are included in the vascular network. Peripheral vessels play an important role in the brain and head drainage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, so that the choice to neglect them in order to simplify the model is not reasonable. Hence, the need of a comprehensive model that considers both extracranial and intracranial compartments with their interactions to adapt the whole hemodynamic system to changing environmental conditions is still not satisfied. Therefore, our overall goal is to make a hemodynamic model able to simulate the main and most reported physiological parameters such as ICP, CVP, IJV-CSA. Noteworthy, the lack of knowledge, discordant literature and measured data about hemodynamic adaptation over time during a spaceflight mission limit the computational approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. To deal with these restrictions, the current model is tuned with literature reporting data of hemodynamic physiology alteration in a short-time space mission or during a parabolic flight, whose experimental conditions and measurement data are compatible.</p>
              <p id="Par76">The presented model is an advanced version of previously published simulation tools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> that were calibrated by using experimental data limited to supine and upright positions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. In this work, new ideas were followed to fulfil the purposes listed below:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par77">to simulate a full range of posture changes from HDT to supine and HUT, other than microgravity;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par78">to compare the simulation results with upright measured data and literature;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par79">to investigate the role of collateral veins in carrying out blood in case of IJV collapse (HUT) or expansion (HDT and microgravity);</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par80">to calculate ICP and CVP changes for each simulated posture;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par81">to calculate flow rate changes after each posture or environmental condition change;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par82">to introduce new indexes useful for future investigations.</p></list-item></list></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p id="Par83">The mathematical model consists of three compartments, linked together, that simulate the arterial, brain and venous vasculature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. The arterial tree is simulated through a 1-D network, while the brain and venous compartments are simulated through 0-D networks. The scheme of the model is reported in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. We use pressure carried by anterior communicating artery in the model of the Willis circle as input to the 0-D intracranial model, and sum of pressures carried by external carotid arteries as input to the extracerebral duct. The venous compartment (blue boxes) includes veins from venous sinus to lumbo-azygos system and superior vena cava. The current version of our model is an open-loop system with a more sophisticated description of the collateral pathways, including not only the internal jugular and vertebral veins but also the external jugular veins, the vertebral plexus (including internal epidural venous plexus and deep cervical veins) and other anastomoses that carry blood to the downstream sections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Therefore, the current model allows simulation of blood flows and pressures in the main vessels and collateral routes taking into account the collapsibility of the veins. In the following, the model is described with focus on the new updates to simulate the altered gravity effects on hemodynamic system. More mathematical details of the model are reported in “<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary Material</xref>”.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mathematical model for the simulation of human circulation. Red boxes are the anatomy (left) and scheme (right) of the arterial tree. Green boxes are the anatomy (left), scheme (middle) of the Willis circle tree, and the scheme of the intracranial 0-D submodel (right). Blue boxes are the scheme (left) and anatomy (right) of the venous compartment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Venous compartment adaptation</title>
                <p id="Par84">In the 0-D compartment, pressure <italic>P</italic> in the model is defined at every node as a function of time <italic>t</italic>. Equation (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) is an example of pressure variation in the venous compartment (upper segment of right IJV):<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{dP}{{dt}} = \frac{1}{{C_{jr3} }}\left[ {\left( {P_{vs} - P_{jr3} } \right)G_{jr3} - \left( {P_{jr3} - P_{c3} } \right)G_{cjr3} - \left( {P_{jr3} - P_{jr2} } \right)G_{jr2} } \right]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vs</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par85">In this equation, <italic>P</italic>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>G</italic> are the pressure, capacitance and conductance of the vessel in the upper and middle segment of the right IJV (<italic>jr3</italic> and <italic>jr2</italic>, respectively), venous sinus (<italic>vs</italic>), upper collateral segment (<italic>c3</italic>), and upper right anastomotic connection (<italic>cjr3</italic>). To take into account the IJV collapsibility and the dynamics of pressure change due to posture variation, <italic>G</italic> should vary following the CSA change. The conductance function of the segment <italic>x</italic> (<italic>G</italic>-function) has a nonlinear switch-like behaviour as in the following equation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} &amp; G_{x} = k_{x} \left[ {1 + \left( {\frac{2}{\pi }} \right)arctan \left( {\frac{{P_{xint} - P_{xext} }}{A}} \right) } \right]^{2} \\ &amp; k_{x} = \frac{{V_{0}^{2} }}{{8\pi\upmu L^{3} }} \\ \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xint</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xext</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">μ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>L</italic> is the segment length, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>0</italic></sub> is the half-maximal blood volume of the segment, <italic>µ</italic> is the blood viscosity, and <italic>A</italic> is the slope of the pressure–volume relationship or elastance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. The sensitivity of Eq. (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>) to pressure variation due to posture changes (e.g. from supine to upright position) on a gravity field is implemented in the difference between internal <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>xint</italic></sub> and external <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>xext</italic></sub> pressure. This difference is defined as transmural pressure (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> = <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>xint</italic></sub> − <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>xext</italic></sub>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Therefore, following the <italic>G</italic>-function (Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>), if <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> has positive values the IJV is fully open, while if <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> reaches null or negative values the IJV is partially or fully collapsed. To properly define <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>xext</italic></sub>, we introduced the following equations:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P}_{xext}= {P}_{xhydro}+{P}_{TW}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xext</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xhydro</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TW</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P_{xhydro} = \rho \left( {\frac{g}{{g_{Earth} }}} \right)L\;sin\;\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xhydro</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Earth</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P}_{TW}=\left[1-\left(\frac{g}{{g}_{Earth}}\right)\right]\mathrm{R}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TW</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Earth</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>ρ</italic> is the blood density, <italic>θ</italic> is the body orientation with respect to the gravity acceleration vector of modulus <italic>g</italic>, <italic>g</italic><sub><italic>Earth</italic></sub> is the modulus of gravity acceleration vector on Earth, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>xhydro</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> are the hydraulic and surrounding tissue weight pressure on vessel <italic>x</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> is related to body size and it emphasizes inter-individual differences<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Buckey et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> introduced the interindividual-dependent variable <italic>R</italic> as the radius of the body section in which external pressure is measured. We borrowed that concept to tune such parameter in accordance to the characteristics of our model. The <italic>G</italic>-function for supine, upright or HDT, and microgravity are defined by Eqs. from (<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">6</xref>) to (<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="">8</xref>), respectively:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${G}_{jr3}={k}_{jr3}{\left[1+\left(\frac{2}{\pi }\right)arctan\left(\frac{{P}_{vs}}{A}\right) \right]}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vs</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${G}_{jr3}={k}_{jr3}{\left[1+\left(\frac{2}{\pi }\right)arctan \left(\frac{{P}_{vs}-{P}_{j3hydro}}{A}\right) \right]}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vs</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${G}_{jr3}={k}_{jr3}{\left[1+\left(\frac{2}{\pi }\right)arctan\left(\frac{{P}_{vs}-{P}_{j3hydro}-{P}_{TW} }{A}\right) \right]}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vs</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TW</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par88">In this work we assumed the same <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> for all the IJV segments (J1, J2, and J3), while values of <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>hydro</italic></sub> were calculated from Eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) by taking into account the average distance of each segment from the hydrostatic indifference point (HIP<sub>CSF</sub>). CSF pressure was also assumed constant. ICP gradient can be predicted according to the hydrostatic pressure gradients from the HIP<sub>CSF</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the cited IJV segments and HIP<sub>CSF</sub> in a HUT subject (left). Reference position and the other conditions analyzed in this work are also reported (right).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Left: Illustration of the three modelled IJV segments (J1–J3) and the corresponding vessel lengths (L1–L3) measured from the hydrostatic indifference point (HIP<sub>CSF</sub>) of a subject in head-up tilt position (HUT). Right: supine (reference position, top), head-down tilt (HDT, middle) and microgravity (bottom) condition. <italic>θ</italic> tilt angle, <italic>g</italic> normalized modulus of gravity acceleration vector with respect to g<sub>Earth</sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> IJV transmural pressure, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>hydro</italic></sub> hydraulic pressure, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> tissue weight pressure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par89">Indeed, in case of posture variation on Earth (g = 1), the hydraulic pressure gradient causes ICP change and orthostatic stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. When in microgravity (g ≈ 0), hydraulic pressure gradient has been considered null for the entire angle range<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Moreover, the compressive force that arose from tissues surrounding the vessel walls were eliminated in microgravity due to weightlessness. Obviously, it is not possible to properly simulate this condition on Earth.</p>
                <p id="Par90">Moreover, the model takes into account the breathing effect on the central venous pressure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Breathing effect on the hydraulic properties of the IJV and VV leads to an increase in flow, even if the intracranial autoregulation mechanisms prevent alterations of cerebral perfusion due to breathing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. To simulate effects of the thoracic pump, the respiratory pressure pulse wave (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>res</italic></sub>) has been considered. The average duration time of one breathing cycle is set to 4.8 s. <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>res</italic></sub> was used as input to calculate the CVP pulse (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>cv</italic></sub>), i.e., at the end of the modelled venous pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Taking into account the posture dependency of CVP, the <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>cv</italic></sub> equation were modified to include contributions of hydrostatic pressure change as well as weightlessness:<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} &amp; \mathop \smallint \limits_{{P_{cv0} }}^{{P_{cv} }} dP_{cv} = \int\limits_{{t_{0} }}^{t} { \frac{1}{{C_{svc} }}\left[ {\left( {P_{svc1} - P_{cv} } \right)G_{svc1} + \left( {P_{azy} - P_{cv} } \right)G_{azy} - \left( {P_{svc2} - P_{cv} } \right)G_{svc2} } \right] dt} \\ &amp; P_{CV0} = P_{a0} + P_{res} + P_{cv\_hydro} + P_{TW} \\ \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo largeop="false">∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:munderover><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">svc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">azy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">azy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">res</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>_</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TW</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a0</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>cv0</italic></sub> are the arterial and central venous pressure in supine position on Earth. Since the superior vena cava (SVC) is a long vein, in our model configuration it is divided into two segments (SVC1 and SVC2). <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${C}_{svc}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">svc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is equal for both segments compliances. <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${G}_{svc1} , {G}_{svc2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${G}_{azy}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">azy</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the SVC1, SVC2 and azygous conductance, respectively. Therefore, change in <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>hydro</italic></sub> simulates the posture change effects from HDT to supine and upright on Earth, while <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> is equal to zero. When simulating microgravity condition <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>hydro</italic></sub> is set to zero, while <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> acts to decompress the vascular network. In this work, P<sub>TW</sub> is considered to be the same for all the modelled segments of IJV.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Brain compartment adaptation</title>
                <p id="Par92">Equations for intracranial dynamics published by Ursino and Lodi<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> are used in the brain part of our model. These equations take into account the mass preservation at all jointing parts of the modelled vessels. At the intracranial level, the storage capacitance (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>ic</italic></sub>) is defined by means of the following differential equation:<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${C}_{ic}\frac{{dP}_{ic}}{dt} = \frac{{dV}_{pa}}{dt}+\frac{{dV}_{vi}}{dt} +{q}_{f}- {q}_{o}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ic</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ic</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dV</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pa</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dV</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vi</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ic</italic></sub> is the ICP, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>pa</italic></sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>vi</italic></sub> are blood volume at the pial arteries and intracranial veins, <italic>q</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> and <italic>q</italic><sub><italic>o</italic></sub> are the rate of formation and outflow of CSF. With the assumption of a monoexponential pressure–volume relationship for the craniospinal space, intracranial storage capacitance is inversely proportional to ICP:<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${C}_{ic}=\frac{1}{{k}_{E} {P}_{ic}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ic</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ic</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>E</italic></sub> is the intracranial elastance. Moreover, intracranial venous capacitance <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>vi</italic></sub> is defined as follow:<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${C}_{vi}=\frac{1}{{{k}_{ven} (P}_{v}- {P}_{ic}- {P}_{v1})}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">vi</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ven</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ic</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>ven</italic></sub> is a constant value, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>v</italic></sub> is the cerebral venous pressure and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>v1</italic></sub> is the transmural pressure. The hydraulic pial artery resistance (<italic>R</italic><sub><italic>pa</italic></sub>) has control on the cerebrovascular mechanisms, to keep balance between pial artery volume and resistance:<disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${R}_{pa}=\frac{{k}_{R} {C}_{pan}^{2}}{{V}_{pa}^{2}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pa</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pan</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pa</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> is a constant, and <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>pan</italic></sub> is a parameter to make hydraulic resistance independent from blood volume. By that, the resistance depends to the capacitance and the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> value. According to the literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, the effect of gravity on cerebral blood circulation is considered by multiplying the supine value (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>x0</italic></sub>) in the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>E</italic></sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>ven</italic></sub>, and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> parameters of Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ11" ref-type="">11</xref>) to (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="">13</xref>) to a factor as written below:<disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${k}_{x}= {k}_{x0}(1- \alpha sin\theta +\beta {P}_{TW})$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TW</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>α</italic> and <italic>β</italic> are parameters properly set to adjust the output, and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> is one of the aforementioned parameters (<italic>x</italic> = {<italic>E</italic>, <italic>ven</italic>, <italic>R</italic>}).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Arterial compartments adaptation</title>
                <p id="Par98">The nonlinear 1-D equations (see “<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary Material</xref>”) were solved by using the finite element methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Since enough information to adjust the 1-D compartments has not been reported in literature, we decided to adjust the arterial pressure <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> (Eq. <xref rid="Equ15" ref-type="">15</xref>) and external carotid arteries pressure <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ex</italic></sub> (Eq. <xref rid="Equ16" ref-type="">16</xref>) by using <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>hydro</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub>:<disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P}_{a} ={P}_{a0} + {P}_{xhydro}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xhydro</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ15.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>16</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P}_{ex}={P}_{ex0}+ {P}_{xhydro}+ {P}_{TW}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ex</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xhydro</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TW</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ16.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par99">To do this, we followed the format of equation for ICP reported in the work of Magnaes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> (Eq. <xref rid="Equ17" ref-type="">17</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ17"><label>17</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P}_{ic}={P}_{ic0}+ \rho \mathrm{g} L sin\theta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ic</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ17.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ic0</italic></sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a0</italic></sub>, and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ex0</italic></sub> are respectively the intracranial, arterial, and external carotid pressure in supine position on Earth.</p>
                <p id="Par101">Since there are no reports of changes in systolic and mean arterial pressure in short-term spaceflight and parabolic flights studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, P<sub>TW</sub> is not added to Eq. (<xref rid="Equ15" ref-type="">15</xref>). Moreover, plasma volume reduction (about 10%) is not considered in the study because no decrease in ICP and cerebral artery compliance was observed after short-duration spaceflight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. In accordance to the literature, the impedance of distal cerebral arteries would be reduced in response to mild decreases in plasma volume<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Hence, we decided to insert P<sub>TW</sub> in the P<sub>ex</sub> described in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ16" ref-type="">16</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Flow analysis</title>
                <p id="Par102">In order to analyze the flow in the head and neck network of the model, the following definitions of flow rate proposed by Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> were used and adjusted with respect to the latest anatomical updates of the model published by Mohammadyari et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In the following it is reported how the flow rate calculated by the arterial 1-D compartment is being used as input for the 0-D venous compartment. The head blood inflow (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBin</italic></sub>) indicates the amount of blood entering the head through the vertebral artery (VA) and the two branches of common carotid (CC), that is the internal common carotid (IC) and external common carotid (EC):<disp-formula id="Equ18"><label>18</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Q}_{HBin}=\frac{{Q}_{CC}+({Q}_{IC}+{Q}_{EC})}{2}+{Q}_{VA}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">IC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">EC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">VA</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ18.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par103">Cerebral blood flow (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>CBF</italic></sub>) indicates the incoming flow into the Willis circle of brain compartment which is supplied by IC and VA:<disp-formula id="Equ19"><label>19</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Q}_{CBF}={Q}_{IC}+{Q}_{VA}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CBF</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">IC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">VA</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ19.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par104">The ECAs enter the facial and extracranial compartment and then are mainly drained by the temporal and facial veins to join external jugular vein (EJV) and the rest of neck venous network. The previous version of the venous network model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> assumed that the ECA flow rate supplies the anastomosis network of the neck. Our latest published update<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> allows us to change the previous assumption, by stating that all the extracranial inflow (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ex</italic></sub>) is supplying the deep cervical vein (DCV) and EJV (see the venous compartment scheme in the left blue box of Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Cerebral venous outflow (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>CVO</italic></sub>) is the flow that originates from the intracranial compartment and is defined by the sum of IJVs-J3, vertebral veins (VVs) and the epidural veins (EDVs), including DCV and internal venous plexus vein (IVP)):<disp-formula id="Equ20"><label>20</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Q}_{CVO}={Q}_{J3}+{Q}_{VV}+{Q}_{EDV}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CVO</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">VV</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">EDV</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ20.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par105">It is important to add the IVP because of the well-known role of this vein and VV as a main outstream pathway of blood from brain to SVC in the upright position, when the IJV is collapsed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. The head blood outflow (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBout</italic></sub>) is equivalent to the sum of the flow of the IJV-J1, EJV, VV and EDV:<disp-formula id="Equ21"><label>21</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Q}_{HBout}={Q}_{J1}+{Q}_{VV}+{Q}_{EJV}+{Q}_{EDV}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">VV</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">EJV</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">EDV</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ21.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par106">In order to analyze the role of collateral vessels in head and neck drainage, the collateral-distal (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>C-D</italic></sub>) and collateral-proximal flows (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>C-P</italic></sub>) were defined as the outflows which directly go into the brain and neck collaterals, respectively:<disp-formula id="Equ22"><label>22</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Q}_{C-D}={Q}_{CBF}-{Q}_{CVO}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CBF</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CVO</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ22.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ23"><label>23</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${Q}_{C-P}={Q}_{HBin}-{Q}_{HBout}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ23.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par107">Collateral flow index (CFI) and delta cerebral venous outflow (DCVO) are the two factors that Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> defined to examine the percentage of blood entering the head and the normalized outflow difference:<disp-formula id="Equ24"><label>24</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$CFI=\frac{{Q}_{C-P}}{{Q}_{HBin}}\times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ24.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ25"><label>25</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$DCVO_{upright} = \left[ {\left. {\left( {\frac{{Q_{HBout} }}{{Q_{HBin} }}} \right)} \right|_{supine} - \left. {\left( {\frac{{Q_{HBout} }}{{Q_{HBin} }}} \right)} \right|_{upright} } \right] \times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">upright</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mfenced close="|"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">supine</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mfenced close="|"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">upright</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ25.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par108">We also defined the DCVO<sub>HDT</sub> and DCVO<sub>μg</sub> to investigate the outflow differences during HDT and μg with respect to supine position, and the peripheral veins outflow index (PVI), which is equal to the percentage difference of blood that passes from the peripheral veins (except the IJV):<disp-formula id="Equ26"><label>26</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$DCVO_{HDT} = \left[ {\left. {\left( {\frac{{Q_{HBout} }}{{Q_{HBin} }}} \right)} \right|_{supine} - \left. {\left( {\frac{{Q_{HBout} }}{{Q_{HBin} }}} \right)} \right|_{HDT} } \right] \times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HDT</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mfenced close="|"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">supine</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mfenced close="|"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HDT</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ26.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ27"><label>27</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$DCVO_{\mu g} = \left[ {\left( {\frac{{Q_{HBout} }}{{Q_{HBin} }}} \right)|_{supine} - \left( {\frac{{Q_{HBout} }}{{Q_{HBin} }}} \right)|_{\mu g} } \right] \times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">supine</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBin</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ27.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ28"><label>28</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$PVI=\frac{{Q}_{HBout}- {Q}_{J3}}{{Q}_{HBout}}\times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HBout</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Article_Equ28.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
                <p id="Par109">With these equations we can study the posture change effects on the haemodynamic model from − 10° HDT to 90° HUT (upright). The model parameters have been taken from previously published articles by Gadda et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Model calculations are performed by the software package MATLAB-Simulink 2019b<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec7">
              <title>Results and discussion</title>
              <p id="Par110">In this work we improved the mathematical haemodynamic model to simulate the hydrostatic pressure changes and weightlessness condition. The model is calibrated in accordance to the data taken from literature. The focus was on the head and neck part of the haemodynamic system. Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents the considered literature pressure values (mean ± standard deviation) and the simulated mean values of pressure at the level of aorta (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>), braincase (ICP), and SVC (CVP). Noteworthy, since our model is not a closed-loop time dependent model, only the steady state conditions are simulated and presented in the following.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Simulated mean pressure and literature pressure values (mean ± standard deviation) considered in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Supine</th><th align="left">θ = 30°</th><th align="left">θ = 60°</th><th align="left">Upright</th><th align="left">HDT</th><th align="left">μg</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Simulated values</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub></td><td align="left">100.8 ± 12.5</td><td align="left">85.8 ± 12.5</td><td align="left">74.8 ± 12.5</td><td align="left">70.8 ± 12.5</td><td align="left">106.0 ± 24.5</td><td align="left">100.8 ± 12.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">9.5 ± 0.4</td><td align="left">6.7 ± 0.8</td><td align="left">3.7 ± 0.4</td><td align="left">2.1 ± 0.4</td><td align="left">10.5 ± 0.1</td><td align="left">8.3 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVP</td><td align="left">4.2 ± 1.2</td><td align="left">3.3 ± 1.3</td><td align="left">2.7 ± 1.3</td><td align="left">2.5 ± 1.3</td><td align="left">4.4 ± 1.2</td><td align="left">3.9 ± 1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>j3</italic></sub></td><td align="left">4.8 ± 0.9</td><td align="left">4.4 ± 0.8</td><td align="left">4.5 ± 0.8</td><td align="left">4.6 ± 0.8</td><td align="left">5.0 ± 0.9</td><td align="left">4.7 ± 0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>j2</italic></sub></td><td align="left">4.6 ± 0.9</td><td align="left">4.0 ± 0.9</td><td align="left">3.9 ± 0.6</td><td align="left">3.8 ± 0.6</td><td align="left">4.9 ± 0.9</td><td align="left">4.5 ± 0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>j1</italic></sub></td><td align="left">4.4 ± 1.1</td><td align="left">3.5 ± 1.2</td><td align="left">2.8 ± 1.3</td><td align="left">2.6 ± 1.3</td><td align="left">4.6 ± 1.0</td><td align="left">4.2 ± 1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Lindén et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">10.5 ± 1.5</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">− 0.8 ± 3.8</td><td align="left">− 9°: 15.8 ± 1.2</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Lawley et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub></td><td align="left"> ~ 100</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">Δ = − 13.0 ± 7.1</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">Δ = − 1.9 ± 5.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">15 ± 2</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">4 ± 1</td><td align="left">− 6°: 15 ± 4 (Δ = 1.9 ± 0.5)</td><td align="left">13 ± 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVP</td><td align="left">7 ± 3</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">2 ± 3</td><td align="left">− 6°: unchanged (Δ = − 0.5 ± 0.5 )</td><td align="left">4 ± 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Eklund et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">10.5 ± 1.5</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">− 0.8 ± 3.8</td><td align="left">− 9°: 15.8 ± 1.3</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Petersen et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub></td><td align="left">103 ± 19</td><td align="left">10°: 88 ± 9</td><td align="left">20°: 87 ± 7</td><td align="left">87 ± 8</td><td align="left">− 10°: 86 ± 11</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">9.4 ± 3.8</td><td align="left">4.8 ± 3.6</td><td align="left">1.3 ± 3.6</td><td align="left">− 2.4 ± 4.2</td><td align="left">14.3 ± 4.7</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Qvarlander et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">11.0 ± 2.1</td><td align="left">27°: 2.3 ± 2.5</td><td align="left">57°: − 1.0 ± 3.0</td><td align="left">71°: − 1.8 ± 3.2</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Mekis and Kamenik</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub></td><td align="left">72.9 ± 11.6</td><td align="left">20°: 65.1 ± 13.1</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">− 20°: 85.4 ± 14.0</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVP</td><td align="left">8.1 ± 4.9</td><td align="left">20°: 4.5 ± 3.8</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">− 20°: 12.7 ± 4.7</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Buckey et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup><bold> (mathematical model)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ICP</td><td align="left">6.1</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVP</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">− 6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>All values are reported in mmHg. We refer to pressure gradient ∆ when absolute values are not reported by cited authors.</p><p><italic>θ</italic> tilt angle, <italic>HDT</italic> head-down tilt, <italic>μg</italic> microgravity, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> arterial pressure, <italic>ICP</italic> intracranial pressure, <italic>CVP</italic> central venous pressure.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par111">We see from Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> that subject posture affects the measured pressure values. In particular, transition from supine to upright causes a pressure decrease, while transition from supine to HDT causes a pressure increase. Arterial BP is hypothesised to be about 100 mmHg in supine, to decrease by increasing the HUT angle till the value of 70 mmHg in upright, and to increase to 105 mmHg at a HDT angle of 6°<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Also, it is reported that in microgravity it remains unaffected with respect to measurements performed in the supine position before the flight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> around the mean value of 100 mmHg<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Petersen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> reported a 17 mmHg drop in arterial BP when passing from supine to − 10° HDT (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Our model shows good agreement with aforementioned literature when simulations of arterial BP in HUT, − 10° HDT, and weightlessness condition are performed. As reported in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, the mean simulated arterial BP decreases of 30 mmHg in upright with respect to the supine position, while it increases of 5 mmHg in HDT, and it remains constant in microgravity condition.</p>
              <p id="Par112">ICP values are frequently reported in literature, and a significant reduction during HUT posture change from supine is always measured<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Moreover, the normal range of ICP for a supine adult is about 7–15 mmHg, and in general less than 20 mmHg<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. Literature in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> reported ICP change in sitting/upright in comparison with supine in the range of 12.8 mmHg (116%) to 11 mmHg (73%) (Qvarlander et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and Lawley et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>). Our simulated ICP decreases of about 7.4 mmHg (78%) in upright with respect to the supine position, which is within the aforementioned literature range, while it increases of 1 mmHg in HDT. Lawley et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> reported a slight increase (i.e. Δ = 1.8 ± 0.5 mmHg) for − 6° HDT which is comparable with our finding. However, Lindén et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and Eklund et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> measured the same increase in the mean value of ICP (5.3 mmHg) for − 9° HDT. Such high pressure difference cannot be calculated by the known hydrostatic pressure equation implemented in the model (Eq. <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>). The difference with data reported in literature might be due to the measurement dependency to experimental conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> also shows that ICP in microgravity environment has a slight reduction (Δ = − 1.9 ± 5.1) with respect to supine position on Earth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. During simulation of microgravity condition, our model calculates a ICP of 8.3 mmHg, and a ICP reduction of 1.2 mmHg with respect to supine position on Earth, in very good agreement with measurement data during 5–10 parabolic flights reported by Lawley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Besides, measurements of CVP reported by Lawley et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> indicated that such value does not change when passing from supine to − 6° HDT. Mekis and Kamenik<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> measured a 4.6 mmHg augmentation for − 20° HDT. Results from our model shows a 1.6 mmHg reduction of CVP in upright with respect to the supine position on Earth, while it is almost unchanged in − 10° HDT. Noteworthy, the equation used in the model to calculate CVP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> is only influenced by <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>hydro</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> on the initial value (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>cv0</italic></sub>), then CVP is affected mainly by IJV changes as explained in the “<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>” (Eqs. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>–<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="">8</xref>) and “<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary Material Section</xref>”.</p>
              <p id="Par113">Gallo et al. reported 5.1% reduction for simulated CVP, in accordance with observed early spaceflights data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Simulated CVP in microgravity condition shows a slight decrease (7.6%) with respect to the simulation in supine position on Earth. Moreover, their CVP value in microgravity is lower than in upright and supine position. Trend of our model results in different conditions is in very good agreement with this and other literature data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Moreover, simulated CVP in HDT is higher than in microgravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>; this result suggests that the upright fluid shift does not contribute to CVP reduction in microgravity, while the gravitational unloading of the <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>TW</italic></sub> plays a key role. The model also allows to compare the pressure variation in the three segments of left IJV for HUT, HDT and μg with respect to the supine condition, considering that J3 is the farthest segment from HIP<sub>CSF</sub>, and that pressure in each segment of IJV and in each condition is calculated accordingly (i.e. <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>J3hydro</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>J2hydro</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>J1hydro</italic></sub>). Moreover, due to the relatively larger CSA of segment J1, this section exhibits the lowest pressure value in supine, and consequently the higher pressure variation in upright and HDT (ΔP<sub>J1</sub> &gt; ΔP<sub>J2</sub> &gt; ΔP<sub>J3</sub>). The IJV pressure value decreases when passing from supine to upright and increase at − 6° HDT. In microgravity it is higher than in upright, and comparable to the value in supine position. Therefore, the IJV pressure change follows the pattern of simulated CVP variation in different conditions.</p>
              <p id="Par114">In Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> the simulated flow rates are reported and compared for different vessels, posture and gravity conditions. Because of the low flow rate at the collateral vessels, in this work we reported the vertebral vein flow rate as the summation of flow at right and left vertebral vein. The same strategy was used for epidural and external jugular veins. Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> stated that the blood flow at each segment of IJV is more than that of VVs or EDV. Moreover, in the publication of Gadda et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> it is reported that blood flow in J3 is lower than in the other segments (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>J1</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>J2</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>J3</italic></sub>) with the subject in standing position. Therefore, it means that the higher segment (with respect to the HIP<sub>CSF</sub> zero level) is more collapsed. The simulated flow rates reported in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> (summation of left and right, J1: 10.6, J2: 9.7 and J3: 7.8 ml/s) are then in good agreement with the experimental data reported by Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> and Gadda et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Furthermore, it is proven that an increase of the tilt angle contributes to the IJVs collapse and expansion of peripheral veins as a compensatory mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In this regard, the <italic>G</italic>-function for all the simulated neck veins has been integrated in the model (Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>), so as to allow the model to simulate the different degree of collapse at IJV segments, other than the slight dilatation in VV, IVP, and DCV. In other words, the model takes into account the increase of IJV resistance and the TPR decrease during upright simulations. Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A shows simulated flow rates for different posture condition on Earth. We can see that flow is properly driven to the peripherals when in upright, in good agreement with literature reports. The model simulates a reduction in <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBin</italic></sub>, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>CBF</italic></sub>, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ex</italic></sub>, and IJVs flow rates, and augmentation of VVs and EDV flow rates. The extracranial veins such as EJVs do not show significant changes. Regarding the total <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBin</italic></sub> and <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>CBF</italic></sub> values, reductions after 90° posture change from supine to upright are about 20% and 15% (from 14.0 and 10.8 ml/s in supine to 11.2 and 9.2 ml/s in upright), respectively. The modelled <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>CBF</italic></sub> reduction is comparable with the 12% reduction reported by Alperin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Similarly, Zhang and Levine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> measured 10–20% reduction in CBF velocity in the middle cerebral artery. Moreover, Sato et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and Serrador and Freeman<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> showed that the inflow increase is due to the functionality of central arteries, and not to the peripheral ones during upright tilt. This means that the change in flow rate can be directly related to flow velocity variation, and our 20% simulated reduction in Q<sub>HBin</sub> is then in very good agreement with literature. In Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B the environmental variables are HDT angle and weightlessness. Considering the fluid shift in the head-down position and microgravity, the augmented <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBin</italic></sub> leads to an outflow increase. Such increased outflow is mainly supported by the IJVs, with a consequent increase of IJV-CSA, since the flow rate can be calculated by multiplying CSA and mean velocity (see Eq. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">22</xref> in “<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary material</xref>”)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Moreover, the 30% reduction in blood flow velocity during parabolic flight reported by Bondar et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> can be interpreted as 30% reduction in total blood inflow which is the same as our model response reduction (4 ml/s). For what concerns effects of microgravity, literature highlighted the role of tissue weight on pressure changes and flow rates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. HDT is only able to model the headward fluid shift in inherently ground-based simulation condition. Besides, astronauts after a long-term space mission show puffy faces, and thus suggesting that the fluid volume in head and neck is augmented also by the microgravity environment rather than exclusively by HDT. Although we are modelling the short-term microgravity exposure, the unloading tissue weight effect implies difference between Earth-based HDT simulation and real microgravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The model simulates higher <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBin</italic></sub> (+ 4.1 ml/s), Q<sub>CBF</sub> (+ 3.9 ml/s), and IJV (+ 1.7 ml/s) flow rate in microgravity with respect to supine position on Earth. Therefore, model results are satisfactory and in good agreement with what highlighted by literature reports and predictions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Niggemann et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, Valdueza et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> and Ciuti et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> emphasized the important role of peripheral veins such as EDV in venous drainage in the upright position. However, due to the difficulty to properly assess flow rate in small and inaccessible veins, such value has not been quantitively reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Therefore, the calculated <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>EDV</italic></sub> can be assumed as a predicted mean value.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of simulated flow rates for different posture conditions on Earth (1 g, left), supine and HDT on Earth (1 g), and weightlessness (μg, right). <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>HBin</italic></sub> total blood flow to the head, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>CBF</italic></sub> cerebral blood inflow, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ex</italic></sub> extracerebral blood flow, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>jl1</italic></sub> flow in the lower segment of left IJV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>jr1</italic></sub> flow in the lower segment of right IJV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>jl2</italic></sub> flow in the middle segment of left IJV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>jr2</italic></sub> flow in the middle segment of right IJV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>jl3</italic></sub> flow in the upper segment of left IJV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>jr3</italic></sub> flow in the upper segment of right IJV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>vv</italic></sub> flow in the VV, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>edv</italic></sub> flow in epidural vein, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ejv</italic></sub> flow in external jugular vein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Simulated mean flows and literature flow values (mean ± standard deviation) considered in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Primary pathway (IJV)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Secondary pathway</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Simulated values</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine</td><td align="left">9.4 ± 1.8</td><td align="left">VV: 0.7 ± 0.3</td><td align="left">EDV: 1.1 ± 0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30°</td><td align="left">8.1 ± 1.2</td><td align="left">VV: 1.0 ± 0.2</td><td align="left">EDV:1.2 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">60°</td><td align="left">4.4 ± 0.4</td><td align="left">VV: 1.7 ± 0.2</td><td align="left">EDV:1.6 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Upright</td><td align="left">3.0 ± 0.3</td><td align="left">VV: 2.0 ± 0.2</td><td align="left">EDV:1.7 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HDT (− 10°)</td><td align="left">9.4 ± 1.9</td><td align="left">VV: 0.7 ± 0.3</td><td align="left">EDV: 1.1 ± 0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Microgravity</td><td align="left">12.9 ± 1.9</td><td align="left">VV: 0.8 ± 0.4</td><td align="left">EDV: 0.6 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Ciuti et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine</td><td align="left">5.6 ± 3.9</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 0.6 ± 2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Upright</td><td align="left">2.0 ± 2.1</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 0.4 ± 0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Zamboni et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine</td><td align="left">6.2 ± 4.5</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 0.6 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Upright</td><td align="left">5.0 ± 5.3</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 1.1 ± 0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Alperin et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine</td><td align="left">10.2 ± 2.4</td><td align="left" colspan="2">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Upright</td><td align="left">5.1 ± 4.4</td><td align="left" colspan="2">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Cirovic et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine</td><td align="left">15.5 ± 8.0</td><td align="left" colspan="2">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Upright</td><td align="left">6.2 ± 3.2</td><td align="left" colspan="2">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><bold>Valdueza et al.</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine</td><td align="left">11.7 ± 4.5</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 0.7 ± 0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15°</td><td align="left">2.5 ± 2.2</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 1.5 ± 1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30°</td><td align="left">2.3 ± 3.3</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 1.8 ± 1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45°</td><td align="left">1.8 ± 2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 2.2 ± 1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Upright</td><td align="left">1.2 ± 1.7</td><td align="left" colspan="2">VV: 3.5 ± 2.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>All values are reported in ml/s.</p><p><italic>IJV</italic> internal jugular vein, <italic>VV</italic> vertebral vein, <italic>EDV</italic> epidural vein (summation of VV and DCV), <italic>HDT</italic> head-down tilt.</p><p><sup>a</sup>The IJV flow is the average value of the three segments (J1, J2, and J3).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par115">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the mean flow rates computed by our model and measurements (mean ± standard deviation) from literature. Valdueza et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> reported a 90% reduction of IJV flow and a 425% increase of VV flow in upright posture compared to supine. Ciuti et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, Cirovic et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and Alperin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> measured 64%, 60% and 50% reduction in the IJV flow rate during the transition from supine to sitting posture, respectively. Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> measured flow in the three segments of IJV. They reported a flow reduction of 20%, 37%, and 34% in J1, J2, and J3 respectively, with an overall IJV average reduction of 37%. They also measured a 26% increase of VV flow after the posture change from supine to upright. The presented model simulates a IJV flow reduction of 68% (from 9.4 ml/s supine to 3.0 ml/s in upright). Conversely, the modelled secondary pathway (sum of VVs and DCVs flows) shows an increase of 108% (from 1.8 ml/s supine to 3.7 ml/s in upright) as compensatory system response of the model. Alperin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> reported the normalized IJV outflow with respect to the total cerebral blood flow in both positions of supine and upright as 75% ± 14% and 42% ± 34%, respectively. The same values calculated by our model are 67% and 26%. Such results are comparable, if we consider the large uncertainty in the experimental values. Model results did not show significant differences in the mean flow rate values when in supine and after HDT, however they show a significant increase of IJV flow rate in microgravity condition. On the other hand, the modelled secondary pathway flows did not change neither in HDT nor in microgravity conditions. Arbeille et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> reported an IJV volume increase during a long-term space mission. They measured a volume increase of 178% and 225% after 15 days and 4–5.5 months, respectively. Comparison with our results (increase of 37% in total IJV flow rate) shows that the presented model is able to simulate the short-term microgravity exposure condition. To our knowledge, there is no literature report about direct measurements of venous flow rates for what concern HDT and microgravity.</p>
              <p id="Par116">Finally, the simulated mean values of CFI, DCVO and PVI indexes are reported in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, and compared with results from Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> who proposed the first two indexes. The new index of PVI indicates that, in a simulation of supine position, 42% of the brain and head outflow is passing through peripheral veins. This index is highly sensitive to posture change so that in upright, HDT (− 10°), and microgravity it increases up to 78%, 57%, and 53%, respectively. Our model simulations also show that, in supine position, 3% of the blood entering into the head and neck circulation goes to the collateral (CFI). This percentage increases up to 13% in upright position, 8% in HDT, and 11% in microgravity condition. The DCVO index emphasises the importance of posture change and weightlessness on the blood circulation since it represents the normalized outflow difference with respect to the supine reference condition. Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> reported this index just for the upright posture. Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> shows that our simulated values are in good agreement with the experimental findings of Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Simulated and literature mean indexes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Supine</th><th align="left">Upright</th><th align="left">HDT</th><th align="left">μg</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"><bold>CFI</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simulated values</td><td align="left">3%</td><td align="left">13%</td><td align="left">8%</td><td align="left">11%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup></td><td align="left">1 ± 3%</td><td align="left">9 ± 19%</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"><bold>DCVO</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simulated values</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">10%</td><td align="left">5%</td><td align="left">7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zamboni et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup></td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">5 ± 10%</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"><bold>PVI</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simulated values</td><td align="left">42%</td><td align="left">78%</td><td align="left">57%</td><td align="left">53%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>HDT</italic> head-down tilt, <italic>μg</italic> microgravity, <italic>CFI</italic> collateral flow index, <italic>DCVO</italic> delta cerebral venous outflow, <italic>PVI</italic> peripheral veins outflow index.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par117">However, there are limitations in such simulations. Since the space environment is not easily accessible, there is not a united protocol to measure the physiological parameters in astronauts and then tune the simulation model accordingly. The other limitation mentioned by literature is that measurement results are highly dependent on the study conditions, such as the duration of the spaceflight and inter-individual differences (e.g. body size and weight)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Moreover, this current version of the model is not able to follow the haemodynamic changes and body adaptation concerning the long-term mission and transient condition (in-flight).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="Par118">In this study, we presented an updated version of a mathematical model based on physiological parameters to study human blood circulation, with focus to head and neck vasculature. Our model is the first full-body map that provides comprehensive insights into the effect of microgravity on human body physiology, including the effects of hydraulic pressure change and weightlessness. The microgravity physiology is a complex subject, hence, the aim of the present work was to show the capability of this model to be used as a helpful tool in the process of understanding the consequence of any hydrostatic change in cardiovascular physiology. Noteworthy, this is a multiscale model tuned by literature data and it is not able to assess any change in human haemodynamic system. The main capability and purpose of such modelling is the calculation of physiological changes if the pertinent equations and parameters are correctly introduced. Another advantage of the presented model is the possibility to modify the equations of the 0-D compartment in order to simulate additional orthostatic stress causes. Limitations aside, this model offers the possibility to investigate counteracting procedures to reduce the orthostatic stress in returning astronauts, and it will be the subject of future work.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Information</title>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <p>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
                    <media xlink:href="41598_2021_84197_MOESM1_ESM.docx">
                      <caption>
                        <p>Supplementary Information.</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>A</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par2">Slope of the pressure–volume relationship (elastance)</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>BP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par3">Blood pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>C</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par4">Capacitance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>C3</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par5">Upper collateral segment</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par6">Common carotid artery</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CFI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par7">Collateral flow index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>C<sub>IC</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par8">Intracranial capacitance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>C<sub>J3</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par9">Upper anastomotic connection</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CSA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par10">Cross-section area</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CSF</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par11">Cerebrospinal fluid</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>C<sub>vi</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par12">Intracranial venous capacitance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CVP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par13">Central venous pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>DCV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par14">Deep cervical vein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>DCVO</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par15">Delta cerebral venous outflow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>EC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par16">External carotid artery</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>EDV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par17">Epidural vein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>EJV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par18">External jugular vein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>g</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par19">Modulus of gravity acceleration vector</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>G</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par20">Conductance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>g<sub>Earth</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par21">Modulus of gravity acceleration vector on Earth</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HDT</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par22">Head-down tilt</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HIP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par23">Hydrostatic indifference point</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HUT</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par24">Head-up tilt</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>IC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par25">Internal carotid artery</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ICP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par26">Intracranial pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>IJV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par27">Internal jugular vein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>IVP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par28">Internal venous plexus</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>J1</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par29">Internal jugular vein, segment 1</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>J2</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par30">Internal jugular vein, segment 2</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>J3</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par31">Internal jugular vein, segment 3</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>k<sub>E</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par32">Intracranial elastance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>L</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par33">Vessel segment length</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>µ</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par34">Blood viscosity</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>µG</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par35">Microgravity</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par36">Pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>a</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par37">Arterial pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>a0</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par38">Arterial supine pressure on Earth</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>ex</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par39">External carotid artery pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>ex0</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par40">External carotid supine pressure on Earth</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>ext</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par41">External pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>hydro</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par42">Hydraulic pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>ic0</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par43">Intracranial supine pressure on Earth</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>int</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par44">Internal pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>T</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par45">Transmural pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>TW</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par46">Tissue weight pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>P<sub>v</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par47">Cerebral venous pressure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>PVI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par48">Peripheral veins outflow index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par49">Flow rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>CBF</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par50">Cerebral blood flow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>C-D</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par51">Collateral-distal flow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>C-P</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par52">Collateral-proximal flow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>CVO</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par53">Cerebral venous outflow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>ex</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par54">Extracranial inflow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>q<sub>f</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par55">CSF formation rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>HBin</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par56">Head blood inflow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q<sub>HBout</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par57">Head blood outflow</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>q<sub>o</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par58">CSF outflow rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>R</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par59">Radius of the body section</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ρ</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par60">Blood density</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>R<sub>pa</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par61">Pial artery resistance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SVC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par62">Superior vena cava</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>θ</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par63">Body orientation with respect to the gravity acceleration vector</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>TPR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par64">Total peripheral resistance</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>V<sub>0</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par65">Parameter related to blood volume</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>VA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par66">Vertebral artery</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>V<sub>vi</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par67">Blood volume at intracranial veins</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>V<sub>Pa</sub></term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par68">Blood volume at pial arteries</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>VS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par69">Venous sinus</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>VV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par70">Vertebral vein</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher's note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec>
              <title>Supplementary Information</title>
              <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-021-84197-7.</p>
            </sec>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>A.T. conceived the experiment, G.G. and P.M. designed the model, performed simulations, data analysis and wrote the initial draft of the manuscript. All authors contributed to editing and improving the manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p id="Par119">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bondar</surname>
                      <given-names>RL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cerebral blood flow velocities by transcranial Doppler during parabolic flight</article-title>
                  <source>J. Clin. Pharmacol.</source>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>915</fpage>
                  <lpage>919</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1552-4604.1991.tb03648.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1761720?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1761720</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lawley</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of gravity and microgravity on intracranial pressure</article-title>
                  <source>J. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>595</volume>
                  <fpage>2115</fpage>
                  <lpage>2127</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP273557</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28092926?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28092926</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marshall-Goebel</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Damani</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bershad</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Brain physiological response and adaptation during spaceflight</article-title>
                  <source>Neurosurgery.</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>85</volume>
                  <fpage>E815</fpage>
                  <lpage>E821</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/neuros/nyz203</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31215633?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31215633</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nicogossian</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Space Physiology and Medicine</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Norsk</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vasorelaxation in space</article-title>
                  <source>Hypertension</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <lpage>73</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.0000194332.98674.57</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16301338?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301338</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mader</surname>
                      <given-names>TH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Optic disc edema, globe flattening, choroidal folds, and hyperopic shifts observed in astronauts after long-duration space flight</article-title>
                  <source>Ophthalmology</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>118</volume>
                  <fpage>2058</fpage>
                  <lpage>2069</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2011.06.021</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21849212?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21849212</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hargens</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vico</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Long-duration bed rest as an analog to microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>120</volume>
                  <fpage>891</fpage>
                  <lpage>903</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00935.2015</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26893033?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26893033</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keil</surname>
                      <given-names>LC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKeever</surname>
                      <given-names>KH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Skidmore</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hines</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Severs</surname>
                      <given-names>WB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of head-down tilt and water immersion on intracranial pressure in nonhuman primates</article-title>
                  <source>Aviat. Space Environ. Med.</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>63</volume>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <lpage>185</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1567318?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1567318</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alperin</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>SH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sivaramakrishnan</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hushek</surname>
                      <given-names>SG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantifying the effect of posture on intracranial physiology in humans by MRI flow studies</article-title>
                  <source>J. Magn. Reson. Imaging.</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <fpage>591</fpage>
                  <lpage>596</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmri.20427</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16217773?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16217773</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ciuti</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Righi</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forzoni</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fabbri</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pignone</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Differences between internal jugular vein and vertebral vein flow examined in real time with the use of multigate ultrasound color Doppler</article-title>
                  <source>AJNR Am. J. Neuroradiol.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <fpage>2000</fpage>
                  <lpage>2004</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3174/ajnr.A3557</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23721896?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23721896</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Convertino</surname>
                      <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cooke</surname>
                      <given-names>WH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vascular functions in humans following cardiovascular adaptations to spaceflight</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Astronaut.</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <lpage>266</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actaastro.2006.08.007</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gisolf</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Human cerebral venous outflow pathway depends on posture and central venous pressure</article-title>
                  <source>J. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>560</volume>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
                  <lpage>327</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2004.070409</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15284348?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15284348</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>DS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Internal jugular pressure increases during parabolic flight</article-title>
                  <source>Physiol. Rep.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>e13068</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14814/phy2.13068</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28039409?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28039409</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Niggemann</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Position dependent changes of the cerebral venous drainage—Implications for the imaging of the cervical spine</article-title>
                  <source>Cent. Eur. Neurosurg.</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <lpage>37</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1253348</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20552542?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20552542</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qvarlander</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sundström</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malm</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eklund</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postural effects on intracranial pressure: Modeling and clinical evaluation</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <fpage>1474</fpage>
                  <lpage>1480</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00711.2013</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24052030?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24052030</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Buckey, J. C. <italic>et al.</italic> The importance of tissue weight and tissue compressive forces in human spaceflight. Paper presented at the international astronautical congress, Adelaide, Australia, 25–29 September 2017.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Levine</surname>
                      <given-names>BD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Autonomic ganglionic blockade does not prevent reduction in cerebral blood flow velocity during orthostasis in humans</article-title>
                  <source>Stroke</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>1238</fpage>
                  <lpage>1244</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.STR.0000260095.94175.d0</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17332450?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332450</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Norsk</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Adaptation of the cardiovascular system to weightlessness: Surprises, paradoxes and implications for deep space missions</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Physiol. (Oxf.)</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>228</volume>
                  <fpage>e13434</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apha.13434</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31872965</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sato</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Blood flow in internal carotid and vertebral arteries during orthostatic stress</article-title>
                  <source>Exp. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <fpage>1272</fpage>
                  <lpage>1280</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2012.064774</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22689443?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22689443</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Serrador</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freeman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Enhanced cholinergic activity improves cerebral blood flow during orthostatic stress</article-title>
                  <source>Front. Neurol.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2017.00103</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28373858?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28373858</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buckey</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Central venous pressure in space</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <lpage>25</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1996.81.1.19</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8828643?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8828643</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verheyden</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beckers</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aubert</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Adaptation of heart rate and blood pressure to short and long duration space missions</article-title>
                  <source>Respir. Physiol. Neurobiol.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>169</volume>
                  <fpage>S13</fpage>
                  <lpage>S16</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resp.2009.03.008</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19833299?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833299</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vascular adaptation to microgravity: What have we learned?</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <fpage>2415</fpage>
                  <lpage>2430</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.2001.91.6.2415</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11717201?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11717201</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lindén</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Normal-tension glaucoma has normal intracranial pressure: A prospective study of intracranial pressure and intraocular pressure in different body positions</article-title>
                  <source>Ophthalmology</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>125</volume>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <lpage>368</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2017.09.022</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29096996?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29096996</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Christensen</surname>
                      <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ivanova</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Norsk</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sympathetic nervous activity decreases during head-down bed rest but not during microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>99</volume>
                  <fpage>1552</fpage>
                  <lpage>1557</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00017.2005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15961614?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15961614</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gallo</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ridolfi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scarsoglio</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular deconditioning during long-term spaceflight through multiscale modeling</article-title>
                  <source>NPJ Microgravity</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41526-020-00117-5</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33083524?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33083524</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mader</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olufsen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahdi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling cerebral blood flow velocity during orthostatic stress</article-title>
                  <source>Ann. Biomed. Eng.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>43</volume>
                  <fpage>1748</fpage>
                  <lpage>1758</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10439-014-1220-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25549771?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25549771</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Slesnick</surname>
                      <given-names>TC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Role of computational modelling in planning and executing interventional procedures for congenital heart disease</article-title>
                  <source>Can. J. Cardiol.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>1159</fpage>
                  <lpage>1170</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjca.2017.05.024</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28843327?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28843327</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diaz-Artiles</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heldt</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>LR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of artificial gravity on the cardiovascular system: Computational approach</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Astronaut.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>126</volume>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <lpage>410</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actaastro.2016.05.005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sharp</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batzel</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Montani</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Space physiology IV: Mathematical modeling of the cardiovascular system in space exploration</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>113</volume>
                  <fpage>1919</fpage>
                  <lpage>1937</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-013-2623-x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23539439</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Noda</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Himeno</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gravitational effects on global hemodynamics in different postures: A closed-loop multiscale mathematical analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Mech. Sinica</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>595</fpage>
                  <lpage>618</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10409-016-0621-z</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zamboni</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An ultrasound model to calculate the brain blood outflow through collateral vessels: A pilot study</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Neurol.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2377-13-81</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23845008?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23845008</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohammadyari</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadda</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taibi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Munuera Del Cerro</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Paediatric haemodynamic modelling: Development and experimental validation using quantitative flow MRI</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. Radiol. Exp.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41747-020-0146-x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32173785?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173785</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadda</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new hemodynamic model for the study of cerebral venous outflow</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>308</volume>
                  <fpage>H217</fpage>
                  <lpage>H231</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00469.2014</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25398980?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25398980</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadda</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validation of a hemodynamic model for the study of the cerebral venous outflow system using MR imaging and echo-color Doppler data</article-title>
                  <source>AJNR Am. J. Neuroradiol.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>2100</fpage>
                  <lpage>2109</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3174/ajnr.A4860</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27444939?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27444939</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fung</surname>
                      <given-names>YC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Biomechanics. Circulation</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Braakman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sipkema</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Westerhof</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A dynamic nonlinear lumped parameter model for skeletal muscle circulation</article-title>
                  <source>Ann. Biomed. Eng.</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>593</fpage>
                  <lpage>616</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02367465</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 2589694?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2589694</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otsuka</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Long-term exposure to space's microgravity alters the time structure of heart rate variability of astronauts</article-title>
                  <source>Heliyon</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <fpage>e00211</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00211</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28050606?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28050606</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>LF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hargens</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spaceflight-induced intracranial hypertension and visual impairment: Pathophysiology and countermeasures</article-title>
                  <source>Physiol. Rev.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>98</volume>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <lpage>87</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00017.2016</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29167331?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29167331</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadda</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Majka</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zieliński</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gambaccini</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taibi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A multiscale model for the simulation of cerebral and extracerebral blood flows and pressures in humans</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>118</volume>
                  <fpage>2443</fpage>
                  <lpage>2454</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-018-3971-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30171350?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30171350</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ursino</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lodi</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A simple mathematical model of the interaction between intracranial pressure and cerebral hemodynamics</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>82</volume>
                  <fpage>1256</fpage>
                  <lpage>1269</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1997.82.4.1256</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9104864?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9104864</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ursino</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ter Minassian</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lodi</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beydon</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cerebral hemodynamics during arterial and CO(2) pressure changes: In vivo prediction by a mathematical model</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>279</volume>
                  <fpage>H2439</fpage>
                  <lpage>H2455</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.2000.279.5.H2439</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11045982?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11045982</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maas</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mean systemic filling pressure: Its measurement and meaning</article-title>
                  <source>Neth. J. Crit. Care</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-014-0727-2</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Majka</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadda</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taibi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gałązka</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zieliński</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Protective properties of the arterial system against peripherally generated waves</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Biosci.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>286</volume>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <lpage>21</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mbs.2017.01.007</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28131788?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28131788</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magnaes</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Body position and cerebrospinal fluid pressure. Part 2: Clinical studies on orthostatic pressure and the hydrostatic indifferent point</article-title>
                  <source>J. Neurosurg.</source>
                  <year>1976</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>698</fpage>
                  <lpage>705</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1976.44.6.0698</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1271090?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1271090</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kurazumi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ogawa</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morisaki</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iwasaki</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of mild decrement in plasma volume simulating short-duration spaceflight on intracranial pressure</article-title>
                  <source>NPJ Microgravity.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41526-018-0053-0</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30302393?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30302393</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nathoo</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caris</surname>
                      <given-names>EC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiener</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mendel</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>History of the vertebral venous plexus and the significant contributions of Breschet and Batson</article-title>
                  <source>Neurosurgery</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <fpage>1007</fpage>
                  <lpage>1014</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/NEU.0b013e3182274865</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21654535?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21654535</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">MathWorks Inc. (2019) Natick, MA. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mathworks.com/products/simulink.html">https://mathworks.com/products/simulink.html</ext-link>. Accessed 25 April 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR49">
                <label>49.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eklund</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The pressure difference between eye and brain changes with posture</article-title>
                  <source>Ann. Neurol.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>80</volume>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <lpage>276</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24713</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27352140?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27352140</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR50">
                <label>50.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petersen</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petersen</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andresen</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Secher</surname>
                      <given-names>NH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Juhler</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postural influence on intracranial and cerebral perfusion pressure in ambulatory neurosurgical patients</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Physiol. Regul. Integr. Comp. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>310</volume>
                  <fpage>R100</fpage>
                  <lpage>R104</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00302.2015</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26468260?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26468260</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR51">
                <label>51.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mekis</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamenik</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Influence of body position on hemodynamics in patients with ischemic heart disease undergoing cardiac surgery</article-title>
                  <source>Wien Klin. Wochenschr.</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>122</volume>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <lpage>62</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00508-010-1346-9</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20517674?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20517674</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR52">
                <label>52.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rangel-Castillo</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gopinath</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Robertson</surname>
                      <given-names>CS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Management of intracranial hypertension</article-title>
                  <source>Neurol. Clin.</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>521</fpage>
                  <lpage>541</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ncl.2008.02.003</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18514825?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18514825</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR53">
                <label>53.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lakin</surname>
                      <given-names>WD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stevens</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Penar</surname>
                      <given-names>PL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling intracranial pressures in microgravity: The influence of the blood-brain barrier</article-title>
                  <source>Aviat. Space Environ. Med.</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <fpage>932</fpage>
                  <lpage>936</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/asem.2060.2007</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17955940?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17955940</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR54">
                <label>54.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Foldager</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Central venous pressure in humans during microgravity</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>81</volume>
                  <fpage>408</fpage>
                  <lpage>412</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1996.81.1.408</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8828692?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8828692</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR55">
                <label>55.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grigoriev</surname>
                      <given-names>AI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kotovskaya</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fomina</surname>
                      <given-names>GA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The human cardiovascular system during space flight</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Astronaut.</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <fpage>1495</fpage>
                  <lpage>1500</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actaastro.2009.11.013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR56">
                <label>56.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Valdueza</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>von Münster</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoffman</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schreiber</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Einhäupl</surname>
                      <given-names>KM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Postural dependency of the cerebral venous outflow</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>355</volume>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <lpage>201</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(99)04804-7</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10675123?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675123</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR57">
                <label>57.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cirovic</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walsh</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fraser</surname>
                      <given-names>WD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gulino</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of posture and positive pressure breathing on the hemodynamics of the internal jugular vein</article-title>
                  <source>Aviat. Space Environ. Med.</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>74</volume>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <lpage>131</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12602443?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12602443</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR58">
                <label>58.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arbeille</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Provost</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zuj</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vincent</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Measurements of jugular, portal, femoral, and calf vein cross-sectional area for the assessment of venous blood redistribution with long duration spaceflight (Vessel Imaging Experiment)</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <fpage>2099</fpage>
                  <lpage>2106</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-015-3189-6</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25991027?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25991027</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
