<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:51:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8552058" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8552058</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-10</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jamasd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8552058</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8552058</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8552058</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34705011</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34705011</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.31465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi210902</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="online-only">
                  <subject>Online Only</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area">
                  <subject>Neurology</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Comparison of Dural Venous Sinus Volumes Before and After Flight in Astronauts With and Without Spaceflight-Associated Neuro-Ocular Syndrome</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Preflight vs Postflight Dural Venous Sinus Volumes in Astronauts With and Without SANS</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Preflight vs Postflight Dural Venous Sinus Volumes in Astronauts With and Without SANS</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rosenberg</surname>
                    <given-names>Mark J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Coker</surname>
                    <given-names>Michael A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>James A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BS</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yazdani</surname>
                    <given-names>Milad</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Matheus</surname>
                    <given-names>M. Gisele</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Blouin</surname>
                    <given-names>Christopher K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Al Kasab</surname>
                    <given-names>Sami</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Collins</surname>
                    <given-names>Heather R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Roberts</surname>
                    <given-names>Donna R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="zoi210902aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="zoi210902aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston</aff>
              <aff id="zoi210902aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Radiology and Radiological Science, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston</aff>
              <aff id="zoi210902aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <title>Article Information</title>
                <p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> August 25, 2021.</p>
                <p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> October 27, 2021. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.31465</uri></p>
                <p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2021 Rosenberg MJ et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p>
                <corresp id="zoi210902cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Donna R. Roberts, MD, Department of Radiology and Radiological Science, Medical University of South Carolina, 96 Jonathan Lucas St, Charleston, SC 29425 (<email xlink:href="robertdr@musc.edu">robertdr@musc.edu</email>).</corresp>
                <p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Drs Roberts and Collins had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
                <p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Al Kasab, Roberts.</p>
                <p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Rosenberg, Coker, Taylor, Yazdani, Matheus, Blouin, Collins, Roberts.</p>
                <p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Rosenberg, Coker, Taylor, Yazdani, Al Kasab, Collins, Roberts.</p>
                <p><italic>Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Taylor, Matheus, Blouin, Roberts.</p>
                <p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Taylor, Blouin, Collins.</p>
                <p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Roberts.</p>
                <p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Rosenberg, Roberts.</p>
                <p><italic>Supervision:</italic> Matheus, Al Kasab, Roberts.</p>
                <p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> None reported.</p>
                <p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This research was funded by grant number 20-EPSCoR2020-0069 from National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA).</p>
                <p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The NASA Lifetime Surveillance of Astronaut Health (LSAH) Program provided all astronaut data and evaluated the final manuscript to ensure astronaut anonymity. NASA had no role in the design and conduct of the study; analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or scientific approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
                <p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> The authors wish to acknowledge the contributions of Giuseppe Barisano, MD (University of Southern California), who provided consultation for this study. The demographic and image data for astronauts were provided by Wafa Taiym, MS, and Sara Mason, BS (LSAH Program, NASA Johnson Space Center). None of these individuals were compensated for their time.</p>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-10-27T10:00">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="epub"/>. -->
              <volume>4</volume>
              <issue>10</issue>
              <elocation-id>e2131465</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2021 Rosenberg MJ et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2131465.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2131465.pdf</self-uri>
              <self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.31465"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="key-points">
                <title>Key Points</title>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-1">
                  <title>Question</title>
                  <p>Given that thrombosis and abnormal internal jugular venous flow have been documented in astronauts, does a retrograde extension of clot occur intracranially, and is abnormal dural venous sinus flow associated with spaceflight associated neuro-ocular syndrome (SANS)?</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-2">
                  <title>Findings</title>
                  <p>In this cohort study of 12 astronauts, there was no evidence of intracranial dural venous sinus thrombosis. Astronauts with SANS had significantly greater preflight to postflight increases in intracranial dural venous volumes than astronauts without SANS.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-3">
                  <title>Meaning</title>
                  <p>The finding of an association between intracranial venous congestion and SANS suggests that aberrant venous flow may play a role in the development of SANS and astronauts with increased venous sinus compliance may be at increased risk.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
                <p>This cohort study clarifies the risk of internal jugular venous thrombosis among astronauts by evaluating the intracranial venous structures following spaceflight and assesses associations between intracranial venous congestion and spaceflight-associated neuro-ocular syndrome (SANS).</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-4">
                  <title>Importance</title>
                  <p>Spaceflight-associated neuro-ocular syndrome (SANS) occurs in 40% to 60% of National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) International Space Station (ISS) astronauts who present postflight with ophthalmological findings and elevated intracranial pressure. The etiology of SANS is unknown; it is hypothesized that venous outflow congestion from the head and neck occurs because of microgravity, which is supported by the finding of internal jugular vein stagnant flow and thrombosis in some astronauts, but the impact on intracranial dural venous sinus structures remains unknown.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-5">
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>To clarify the potential risk of retrograde extension of clot intracranially among astronauts with internal jugular venous thrombosis by evaluating intracranial venous structures following spaceflight and to assess for any association between intracranial venous congestion and SANS.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-6">
                  <title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
                  <p>This retrospective cohort study of all NASA astronauts who had undergone magnetic resonance (MR) venography at the time of the study included quantitative and qualitative assessments of the intracranial venous system on preflight and postflight MR venograms. Data were collected a mean (SD) of 525.8 (187.5) days before spaceflight and 2.0 (1.5) days after return to Earth. A semiautomated segmentation of the venogram images was used, which was then compared with a neuroradiologist’s assessment.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-7">
                  <title>Exposures</title>
                  <p>A mean (SD) 184.3 (66.0) days of ISS spaceflight missions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-8">
                  <title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
                  <p>Dural venous sinus volumes before and after spaceflight.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-9">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>A total of 12 astronauts (2 [16.67%] women; 10 [83.33%] men), with a mean (SD) age of 47.8 (5.8) years, were included. Overall, 4 astronauts (33.33%) met the diagnostic criteria for SANS. No dural venous sinus thrombosis was detected for any astronaut. Astronauts with SANS had significantly greater median (range) preflight to postflight increases in volume vs astronauts without SANS for all 3 venous sinus structures: superior sagittal sinus (13.40% [8.70% to 17.47%] vs −2.66% [−15.84% to 5.31%,]; <italic>P</italic> = .004), right transverse/sigmoid sinus (17.15% [7.63% to 30.08%] vs 0.77% [−14.98% to 15.12%]; <italic>P</italic> = .02), and left transverse/sigmoid sinus (9.40% [5.20% to 15.50%] vs −1.40% [−14.20% to 12.50%]; <italic>P</italic> = .03). There was a positive correlation between the neuroradiologist’s evaluation and the semiautomated method for the superior sagittal sinus (<italic>r</italic><sub>pb</sub> = 0.64; <italic>P</italic> = .02) and the right transverse/sigmoid sinus (<italic>r</italic><sub>pb</sub> = 0.58; <italic>P</italic> = .050).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi210902-10">
                  <title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
                  <p>These findings, in conjunction with the growing body of evidence of abnormal blood flow dynamics during spaceflight, suggest an association between intracranial venous congestion and SANS. Thus, there is an implication that individuals with increased venous sinus compliance may be at increased risk of developing SANS. These findings should be confirmed in a larger astronaut population and may contribute to understanding disorders of intracranial venous outflow on Earth.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="H1-1-ZOI210902">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Spaceflight-associated neuro-ocular syndrome (SANS) occurs in approximately 40% to 60% of National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) International Space Station (ISS) astronauts who present post flight with altered visual acuity, areas of injury to the retina, globe flattening, optic disk edema, and mildly elevated intracranial pressures (ICPs).<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> The etiology of SANS is unknown, but a leading hypothesis is congestion of venous outflow from the head and neck because of microgravity-induced cephalad fluid shifts. This was supported by detection of stagnant flow by Doppler ultrasound<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and, in 2 cases, thrombosis in the internal jugular veins of ISS astronauts.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Considering the unknown risk of thrombus embolism and retrograde extension to the intracranial veins, a decision was made to provide anticoagulation treatment to the 1 astronaut who was diagnosed with thrombosis while aboard the ISS.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Treatment was carried out until 4 days prior to return to Earth.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The association of internal jugular vein stagnant flow and thrombosis with intracranial venous pressure as well as intracranial and intraocular pressure remains unknown. In this study, we conducted retrospective quantitative and qualitative assessments of the intracranial venous system in a cohort of NASA astronauts who had undergone magnetic resonance images (MRI) before and after spaceflight missions to the ISS.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-2-ZOI210902">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="H2-1-ZOI210902">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>At the time of data acquisition for this study, all NASA astronauts who had undergone MR venograms before and after ISS missions were included as participants in this study. While MRIs have been performed before and after spaceflight on all astronauts routinely, per NASA medical requirements since 2009, only recently has intracranial MR venography been included as part of the NASA medical operations protocol. Based on published guidelines,<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> astronauts who met the diagnostic criteria for SANS postflight were included in the SANS group, while the remainder were included in the non-SANS group.</p>
                <p>The MRI scans along with demographic data for this study were obtained from the NASA Lifetime Surveillance of Astronaut Health Program. The study was approved by the institutional review boards at the NASA Johnson Space Center and the Medical University of South Carolina. All astronauts signed written informed consent for use of their data, and the manuscript was reviewed by the NASA Lifetime Surveillance of Astronaut Health Office to ensure astronaut anonymity. The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline was followed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-2-ZOI210902">
                <title>Imaging Protocols and Image Processing</title>
                <p>MRI was performed on a 3T Siemens Verio scanner and included an MR venogram and a volumetric T1-weighted magnetization-prepared rapid acquisition of gradient-echo sequence. MR venograms were performed using a flow sensitive technique without administration of intravenous contrast with the following parameters: 0.5 × 0.5 × 1.6 mm<sup>3</sup> voxels; repetition time, 21 milliseconds; echo time, 5.42 milliseconds; flip angle, 30°. The following parameters were used for the structural T1-weighted sequences: 0.9 × 0.5 × 0.45 mm<sup>3 </sup>voxels; repetition time, 1900 milliseconds; echo time, 2.32 milliseconds; flip angle, 9°.</p>
                <p>Venous structures (ie, superior sagittal sinus, left and right transverse/sigmoid sinuses) were segmented using a semiautomated pipeline, and preflight to postflight percentage changes in venous volumes were calculated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zoi210902f1">Figure 1</xref>). The venograms were processed to enhance contrast before segmentation. The images were corrected for intensity in homogeneity artifact using the N4BiasFieldCorrection program from the Advanced Normalization Tools toolbox (version 2.3.4).<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Then, each astronauts’ structural images were aligned to their corresponding MR venograms at each corresponding preflight and postflight time using spm_coreg and spm_reslice<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> from the Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM) version 12 software suite. Once aligned, the structural images were subtracted from the venograms to provide a greater contrast between the tissue background and the bright sinuses, a feature not present in the structural images. Voxels in the difference images were then thresholded at 14% of maximum brightness, leaving only the sinus features.</p>
                <fig id="zoi210902f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Image Analysis Workflow</title>
                    <p>MNI indicates Montreal Neurological Institute; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging.</p>
                    <p><sup>a</sup>Radiologist was masked to astronauts’ spaceflight-associated neuro-ocular syndrome status.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2131465-g001"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Binary masks of the sinus regions were then obtained from the processed venogram images using itk-SNAP<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> version 3.2 for semiautomatic segmentation.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> To ensure that the extent of the sinus masks was the same, sinus image volume anterior to Y = 45 mm or inferior to Z = −65 mm in Montreal Neurological Institute (MNI) 152 standard space was excluded. To do this, binary masks of these regions were made in MNI space. Then, they were moved to each venogram image set and used as a mask. This alignment was composed of a nonlinear transformation made by fnirt (FMRIB Software Library<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> version 6.0.3) from MNI space to each participant’s structural image and a rigid body registration made by spm_coreg in SPM.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p>
                <p>The sinus masks were divided in a similar manner into right transverse/sigmoid sinus, left transverse/sigmoid sinus, and superior sagittal sinus. Sinus volume superior of Z = −15.5 mm was considered superior sagittal; sinus volume inferior of Z = −15.5 mm and right of X = 0.5 mm was considered right transverse; sinus volume inferior of Z = −15.5 mm and left of X = 0.5 mm was considered left transverse.</p>
                <p>Quality control was then performed by a neuroradiologist (D.R.R.) with 15 years of experience to ensure the masks accurately delineated each sinus. The sinus volumes were then found from the masks using MATLAB version R2019b (Mathworks).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-3-ZOI210902">
                <title>Radiologist Interpretation of Images</title>
                <p>To evaluate whether the preflight to postflight changes in size of the venous structures were clinically visible, the paired preflight and postflight venogram images were presented in a randomized order to a board-certified neuroradiologist (M.Y.) with 6 years of experience (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zoi210902f1">Figure 1</xref>). For each image pair, the radiologist rated the superior sagittal sinus and left and right transverse/sigmoid sinuses as either increased, decreased, or no change in size between the 2 image sets. The radiologist was masked to each astronaut’s SANS status.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-4-ZOI210902">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>Differences in the preflight to postflight percentage change in venous sinus volumes were evaluated with Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> tests and summarized with medians and ranges. Point-biserial correlations (<italic>r</italic><sub>pb</sub>) were run to examine the association between the reader’s evaluation of venous sinus volume changes and the semiautomated method. Spearman rank order correlation (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub>) was used to assess the correlation between the number of days between return and postflight MRI and the dural venous volume changes. Statistical significance was considered at the α = .05 threshold, with 2-sided <italic>P</italic> values reported. Data analysis was conducted in SPSS statistical software version 25 (IBM Corp).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-3-ZOI210902">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>At the time of data acquisition for this study, 12 NASA astronauts (2 [16.67%] women; 10 [83.33%] men; mean [SD] age, 47.8 [5.8] years) had undergone intracranial MR venography before and after ISS missions (mean [SD] duration, 184.3 [66.0] days) and therefore were included as participants in this study (<xref rid="zoi210902t1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>). Imaging was performed a mean (SD) of 525.8 (187.5) days prior to spaceflight and mean (SD) 2.0 (1.5) days after return to Earth.</p>
              <table-wrap id="zoi210902t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Demographic Characteristics</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="46.8%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="26.6%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="26.6%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th>
                      <th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Astronauts</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">With SANS (n = 4)</th>
                      <th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without SANS (n = 8)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD), y</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3 (2.8)</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.0 (6.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women, No. (%)</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (25.0)</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men, No. (%)</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (75.0)</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.5)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mission duration, mean (SD), d</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241.5 (87.5)</td>
                      <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.6 (27.5)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <p>Abbreviation: SANS, spaceflight-associated neuro-ocular syndrome.</p>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Based on published guidelines,<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> 4 of the 12 astronauts (33.33%) met the diagnostic criteria for SANS postflight, including globe flattening in 3 (75.00%), choroidal folds in 4 (100%), and optic disc edema in 3 (75.00%), and were included in the SANS group. The other 8 astronauts were included in the non-SANS group.</p>
              <p>On MR venography, there was no evidence of dural venous sinus or cortical vein thrombosis for any of the astronauts before or after flight. Astronauts with SANS had significantly greater median (range) preflight to postflight increases in volume than astronauts without SANS for all 3 venous sinus structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zoi210902f2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="zoi210902f3">Figure 3</xref>): superior sagittal sinus (13.40% [8.70% to 17.47%] vs −2.66% [−15.84% to 5.31%]; <italic>P</italic> = .004), right transverse/sigmoid sinus (17.15% [7.63% to 30.08%] vs 0.77% [−14.98% to 15.12%]; <italic>P</italic> = .02), and left transverse/sigmoid sinus (9.40% [5.20% to 15.50%] vs −1.40% [−14.20% to 12.50%]; <italic>P</italic> = .03). There were no significant correlations between the number of days between return and postflight MRI and the volume change in the right transverse/sigmoid sinus (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub> = −0.02, <italic>P</italic> = .96), left transverse/sigmoid sinus (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub> = 0.20, <italic>P</italic> = .53), or superior sagittal sinus (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub> = 0.09, <italic>P</italic> = .78).</p>
              <fig id="zoi210902f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Preflight to Postflight Percentage Changes in Venous Sinus Volumes for the Superior Sagittal Sinus and Left and Right Transverse/Sigmoid Sinuses for Astronauts With and Without Spaceflight-Associated Neuro-Ocular Syndrome (SANS)</title>
                  <p>The boxes indicate the IQR, with the line in each box representing the median and the edges representing the limits of the IQR. The whiskers indicate 1.5 times the IQR, and the open circles indicate data points from 1.5 to 3.0 times the IQR.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2131465-g002"/>
              </fig>
              <fig id="zoi210902f3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 3. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Three-Dimensional Reconstructions of the Preflight and Postflight Venograms for an Astronaut with Spaceflight-Associated Neuro-Ocular Syndrome (SANS) and an Astronaut Without SANS</title>
                  <p>These images were created using RadiAnt DICOM Viewer, version 2020.2.2 (Medixant).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2131465-g003"/>
              </fig>
              <p>There was only 1 instance of a no change reading by the neuroradiologist, so that value was excluded from statistical analysis. There was a positive correlation between the reader’s evaluation and the automatic method for the superior sagittal sinus (<italic>rpb</italic> = 0.64, <italic>P</italic> = .02) and the right transverse/sigmoid sinus (<italic>rpb</italic> = 0.58, <italic>P</italic> = .050). There was a similar finding for the left transverse/sigmoid sinus; however, it did not reach statistical significance (<italic>rpb</italic> = 0.59, <italic>P</italic> = .06).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-4-ZOI210902">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this study, NASA astronauts who presented clinically with SANS had enlargement of the dural venous sinuses consistent with intracranial venous congestion. In addition, our study found a correlation between semiautomated and experienced neuroradiologist assessments in evaluating venous sinus congestion in this population.</p>
              <p>SANS is considered by NASA to be one of the highest priority risks for human spaceflight.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> A leading hypothesis for the development of SANS is that in microgravity, loss of gravitational hydrostatic pressure leads to an upward shift of fluids from the lower body, with resultant venous congestion in the head and neck.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> However, it is unclear whether the venous congestion acts locally at the level of the intraorbital optic nerve and globe leading directly to the optic disc edema and areas of injury to the retina seen in SANS<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> or, alternatively, head and neck venous congestion obstructs venous outflow from the cranium, leading to intracranial hypertension, which is then transmitted along the optic nerve sheath, ultimately resulting in optic disc edema.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Based on this second hypothesized mechanism for SANS, idiopathic intracranial hypertension (IIH) has been considered a terrestrial model for SANS.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> IIH is a disorder of cerebrospinal fluid homeostasis in which patients present clinically with signs and symptoms of increased ICP, including vision changes, headaches, and papilledema.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> While the exact pathophysiology of IIH is unknown, venous hypertension and outflow obstruction have been proposed as primary mechanisms.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Our findings of venous congestion in intracranial venous sinuses supports the theory that SANS represents a global ICP pathology rather than an isolated ocular pathology. We hypothesize that venous congestion leads to increased ICP, which manifests in optic disk edema.</p>
              <p>On Earth, venous outflow obstruction can result from blockage of the dominant transverse sinus by intraluminal structures, such as prominent arachnoid granulations, chronic thrombus, fenestrations, and congenital septations, which appear at MR venography as focal areas of dural venous sinus narrowing.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> At invasive manometry, pressure gradients of greater than 10 mm Hg can be present across these focal stenoses,<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and treatment with stent placement across the stenoses reduces the pressure gradient, normalizing ICP.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Another appearance in patients with IIH at MR venography is long-segment transverse sinus narrowing, thought to result from extrinsic compression of the transverse sinus in the setting of elevated ICP.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Therefore, on Earth, the level of venous outflow obstruction occurs within the cranium because of intrinsic and/or extrinsic factors. For NASA astronauts with SANS, instead of narrowing, we found enlargement of the dural venous sinuses, which suggests the level of obstruction is further downstream, outside the cranium. We hypothesize dural venous sinus congestion in SANS results from the lack of normal drainage, facilitated on Earth by gravity, through the internal jugular veins and vertebral venous plexuses, as was recently documented in some ISS astronauts.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Unlike most veins, the dural venous sinuses are rigid structures that resist deformation despite large physiological variations in surrounding ICP.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> They are triangular in shape, formed from the tough periosteal and meningeal layers of dura, and are protected anatomically by attachment to the inner table of the skull.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Abnormal dural venous sinus compliance is considered by some to be a key factor in the development of IIH, as laxity of the dural venous sinus walls would allow narrowing at times of high ICP, thereby contributing further to venous outflow obstruction.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Here, distention of the walls of the dural venous sinuses in astronauts with SANS may reflect venous sinus laxity. Laxity may be a risk factor for the development of SANS, as dural venous sinus rigidity in astronauts without SANS may serve to resist the development of intracranial venous congestion.</p>
              <p>An alternative explanation for our findings may be that enlargement of the dural sinuses in astronauts with SANS occurs after return to Earth, prior to the postflight MRI. Imaging was performed in all of the astronauts within 5 days after landing, and we found no association with time to postflight imaging. However, compression of the venous system has been documented in patients with IIH, which resolves after cerebrospinal fluid diversion,<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> and the possibility that a reduction in ICP from in-flight levels on return to Earth could have resulted in expansion of the intracranial venous system needs further study. As dural sinus pressure is always maintained below cerebrospinal fluid pressure, because of the waterfall effect occurring at the level of the bridging veins, enlargement of the dural sinuses may reflect an abrupt ICP normalization on return to a 1 gravity environment, with a rebound cerebrospinal fluid overdrainage.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi210902r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Supporting this explanation, abrupt changes in ICP have been documented when alternating between microgravity and hypergravity during parabolic flight.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Arguing against this possibility is the moderately elevated opening pressures of as much as 28.5 cm of water documented post flight, months after return to Earth, in astronauts with SANS.<sup><xref rid="zoi210902r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p>
              <sec id="H2-5-ZOI210902">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>This study has limitations, including the small number of astronauts and the lack of invasive ICP and intravenous pressure correlation. These data would be helpful in determining the physiological significance of the change in dural venous sinus volumes that we document here. An additional limitation is the lack of data concerning any potential SANS countermeasure usage among the astronaut cohort.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-5-ZOI210902">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Our study, in conjunction with the growing body of evidence of abnormal blood flow dynamics with venous outflow stagnation during spaceflight, suggests an association between intracranial venous congestion and SANS. The implication thus exists that individuals with increased venous sinus compliance may be at increased risk of developing SANS. These findings should be confirmed in a larger astronaut population. These results underscore the need for further studies to determine whether changes in the venous sinus volumes documented here are clinically relevant and whether venous congestion contributes to the development of SANS or headaches among astronauts. Additionally, these results may provide insight into terrestrial disorders of intracranial venous congestion and cerebrospinal fluid homeostasis.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="REF-ZOI210902">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zoi210902r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mader</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Spaceflight associated neuro-ocular syndrome (SANS) and the neuro-ophthalmologic effects of microgravity: a review and an update</article-title>. <source>NPJ Microgravity</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41526-020-0097-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32047839?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32047839</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Marshall-Goebel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alferova</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of jugular venous blood flow stasis and thrombosis during spaceflight</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<elocation-id>e1915011</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.15011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31722025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31722025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Auñón-Chancellor</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pattarini</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sargsyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Venous thrombosis during spaceflight</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1905875</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31893522?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31893522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tustison</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Avants</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>N4ITK: improved N3 bias correction</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Med Imaging</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1310</fpage>-<lpage>1320</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMI.2010.2046908</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20378467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20378467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>Collingnon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delaere</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandermeulen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suetens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <part-title>Automated multi-modality image registration based on information theory</part-title>. In: <person-group><string-name><surname>Bizais</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barillot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Paola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>, eds. <source>Information Processing in Medical Imaging</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>:<fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web">itk-SNAP. Accessed September 27, 2021. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.itksnap.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php">http://www.itksnap.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Yushkevich</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang Gao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerig</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>ITK-SNAP: an interactive tool for semi-automatic segmentation of multi-modality biomedical images</article-title>. <source>Annu Int Conf IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>3342</fpage>-<lpage>3345</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/EMBC.2016.7591443</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28269019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28269019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web">FSL. FMRIB software library 6.0. Accessed September 27, 2021. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fsl.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl/fslwiki/">https://fsl.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl/fslwiki/</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fischl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Accurate and robust brain image alignment using boundary-based registration</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.06.060</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19573611?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19573611</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Improved optimization for the robust and accurate linear registration and motion correction of brain images</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>825</fpage>-<lpage>841</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2002.1132</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12377157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12377157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A global optimisation method for robust affine registration of brain images</article-title>. <source>Med Image Anal</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1361-8415(01)00036-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11516708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11516708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web">NASA. <person-group><collab>Human research roadmap</collab></person-group>. Accessed April 19, 2021. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://humanresearchroadmap.nasa.gov/">http://humanresearchroadmap.nasa.gov/</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group><string-name><surname>Stenger</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarver</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brunstetter</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. Evidence report: risk of spaceflight associated neuro-ocular syndrome (SANS). November 30, <year>2017</year>. Accessed September 24, 2021. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://humanresearchroadmap.nasa.gov/evidence/reports/SANS.pdf">https://humanresearchroadmap.nasa.gov/evidence/reports/SANS.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pool</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fluid shifts in weightlessness</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Environ Med</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>9 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>A86</fpage>-<lpage>A90</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 3675511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3675511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SMC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macias</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optic disc edema and choroidal engorgement in astronauts during spaceflight and individuals exposed to bed rest</article-title>. <source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>172</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 31876939?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31876939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mader</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pass</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optic disc edema, globe flattening, choroidal folds, and hyperopic shifts observed in astronauts after long-duration space flight</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2058</fpage>-<lpage>2069</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2011.06.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21849212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21849212</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gurney</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the current management idiopathic intracranial hypertension, and understanding the role of dural venous sinus stenting</article-title>. <source>Eye Brain</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/EB.S193027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32021528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32021528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Karahalios</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rekate</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khayata</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Apostolides</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Elevated intracranial venous pressure as a universal mechanism in pseudotumor cerebri of varying etiologies</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.46.1.198</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8559374?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8559374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Dinkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Men are from Mars, idiopathic intracranial hypertension is from venous: the role of venous sinus stenosis and stenting in idiopathic intracranial hypertension</article-title>. <source>Semin Neurol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>692</fpage>-<lpage>703</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0039-3399506</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31847040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31847040</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>King</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tress</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cerebral venography and manometry in idiopathic intracranial hypertension</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2224</fpage>-<lpage>2228</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.45.12.2224</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8848197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8848197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Asif</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Craven</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Idiopathic intracranial hypertension: 120-day clinical, radiological, and manometric outcomes after stent insertion into the dural venous sinus</article-title>. <source>J Neurosurg</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>723</fpage>-<lpage>731</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2017.4.JNS162871</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28984521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28984521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>LBE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plato</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dashti</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Endovascular treatment for venous sinus stenosis in idiopathic intracranial hypertension: an observational study of clinical indications, surgical technique, and long-term outcomes</article-title>. <source>World Neurosurg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>e165</fpage>-<lpage>e171</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2018.09.070</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30248468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30248468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Lateral sinus stenoses in idiopathic intracranial hypertension resolving after CSF diversion</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1907</fpage>-<lpage>1908</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.WNL.0000125285.44539.D7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15159514?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15159514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>De Simone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sansone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dural sinus collapsibility, idiopathic intracranial hypertension, and the pathogenesis of chronic migraine</article-title>. <source>Neurol Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-019-03775-w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30838545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30838545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Venous anatomy and imaging of the first centimeter</article-title>. <source>Semin Ultrasound CT MR</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>513</fpage>-<lpage>524</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.sult.2009.08.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20099637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20099637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The hemodynamic response of the cerebral bridging veins to changes in ICP</article-title>. <source>Neurocrit Care</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12028-009-9299-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19898968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19898968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>DE Simone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonavita</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Starling resistors, autoregulation of cerebral perfusion and the pathogenesis of idiopathic intracranial hypertension</article-title>. <source>Panminerva Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23736/S0031-0808.16.03248-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27598891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27598891</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi210902r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lawley</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howden</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of gravity and microgravity on intracranial pressure</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>595</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2115</fpage>-<lpage>2127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP273557</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28092926?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28092926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
