<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:49:53Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8685578" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8685578</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>frontmicrobio</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8685578</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8685578</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8685578</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34938279</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.765943</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Microbiology</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Original Research</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Comparative Genomics of Novel <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 Strains Isolated From the International Space Station and Description of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> sp. nov.</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Singh</surname>
                    <given-names>Nitin K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
                    <sup>†</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/397478/overview"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lavire</surname>
                    <given-names>Céline</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
                    <sup>†</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/691082/overview"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nesme</surname>
                    <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
                    <sup>†</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/213366/overview"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vial</surname>
                    <given-names>Ludovic</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/355461/overview"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nesme</surname>
                    <given-names>Xavier</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mason</surname>
                    <given-names>Christopher E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/232379/overview"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lassalle</surname>
                    <given-names>Florent</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/583017/overview"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Venkateswaran</surname>
                    <given-names>Kasthuri</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/23226/overview"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Biotechnology and Planetary Protection Group, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Pasadena, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>CNRS, INRAE, VetAgro Sup, UMR Ecologie Microbienne, Université de Lyon, Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1</institution>, <addr-line>Villeurbanne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Section of Microbiology, Department of Biology, University of Copenhagen</institution>, <addr-line>Copenhagen</addr-line>, <country>Denmark</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Physiology and Biophysics, Weill Cornell Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>New York, NY</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Parasites and Microbes Programme, Wellcome Sanger Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Hinxton</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                  <p>Edited by: Eric Daniel Becraft, University of North Alabama, United States</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                  <p>Reviewed by: Tatiana Matveeva, Saint Petersburg State University, Russia; Víctor González, National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico; Beatriz Jorrin, University of Oxford, United Kingdom</p>
                </fn>
                <corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Florent Lassalle, <email>fl4@sanger.ac.uk</email></corresp>
                <corresp id="c002">Kasthuri Venkateswaran, <email>kjvenkat@jpl.nasa.gov</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002">
                  <p><sup>†</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="other" id="fn004">
                  <p>This article was submitted to Evolutionary and Genomic Microbiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>06</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>12</volume>
              <elocation-id>765943</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>12</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2021 Singh, Lavire, Nesme, Vial, Nesme, Mason, Lassalle and Venkateswaran.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Singh, Lavire, Nesme, Vial, Nesme, Mason, Lassalle and Venkateswaran</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>Strains of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 (i.e., genomovar G3 of the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> species complex) have been previously isolated from diverse environments, including in association with plant roots, with algae, as part of a lignocellulose degrading community, from a hospital environment, as a human opportunistic pathogen, or as reported in this study, from a surface within the International Space Station. Polyphasic taxonomic methods revealed the relationship of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains to other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> spp., which supports the description of a novel species. The G3 strains tested (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9) were phenotypically distinguishable among the strains from other genomospecies of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium.</italic> Phylogenetic analyses of the 16S rRNA gene, <italic toggle="yes">gyr</italic>B gene, multi-locus sequence analysis, and 1,089-gene core-genome gene concatenate concur that tested G3 strains belong to the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genus and they form a clade distinct from other validly described <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species. The distinctiveness of this clade was confirmed by average nucleotide identity (ANI) and <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> digital DNA–DNA hybridization (dDDH) comparisons between the G3 tested strains and all known <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species type strains, since obtained values were considerably below the 95% (ANI) and 70% (dDDH) thresholds used for the species delineation. According to the core-genome phylogeny and ANI comparisons, the closest relatives of G3 strains were <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. strains UGM030330-04 and K599, members of a novel genomospecies we propose to call genomovar G21. Using this polyphasic approach, we characterized the phenotypic and genotypic synapomorphies of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3, showing it is a <italic toggle="yes">bona fide</italic> bacterial species, well separated from previously named <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species or other recognized genomic species. We thus propose the name <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> for this species previously referred to as <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3. The type strain of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> is IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup> (= LMG 32164 = NRRL B-65602). Comparative genomic analysis show <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains have species-specific genes associated with secretion of secondary metabolites, including an exopolysaccharide and putative adhesins and resistance to copper. <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> specific gene functions notably relate to surface adhesion and could be involved to colonize nutrient-poor and harsh habitats. The <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains from the ISS showed presence of a 40-kbp plasmid and several other potential mobile genetic elements detected that could also be part of conjugative elements or integrated prophages.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>
                  <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>genomovar G3</kwd>
                <kwd>ISS</kwd>
                <kwd>metagenomics</kwd>
                <kwd>phylogenomics</kwd>
                <kwd>MLSA</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source id="cn001">
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000104</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="3"/>
                <table-count count="3"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="69"/>
                <page-count count="15"/>
                <word-count count="11982"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="S1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species are firstly known for their pathogenic potential on plant, causing either crown gall or hairy root disease, depending on the presence of a tumor-inducing (Ti) or root-inducing (Ri) megaplasmid in their genome; however, most strains lack such plasmids and are not pathogenic. <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species are common members of soil communities, and are efficient colonizers of the rhizospheres of a wide variety of plant hosts (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Macrae et al., 1988</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Matthysse and McMahan, 1998</xref>), with which they have a commensal relationship (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Sanguin et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Dessaux and Faure, 2018</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> is a polyphyletic group, which taxonomy, originally aimed at reflecting the pathogenicity status of strains (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Townsend, 1907</xref>), was revised multiple times, in the light of growing phenotypic and genotypic evidence, notably showing that the pathogenicity status was not correlated to the diversity of agrobacteria. Based on biochemical testing and DNA-DNA hybridization (DDH), <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species were initially classified into three biovars (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Keane et al., 1970</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Kersters et al., 1973</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ophel and Kerr, 1987</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species belonging to biovar 1, as well as closely related species such as <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rubi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium larrymoorei</italic> can be recognized by the presence of a linear chromid as the second major molecule of the genome, a synapomorphic trait enabled by the landmark acquisition of the <italic toggle="yes">telA</italic> gene (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Ramírez-Bahena et al., 2014</xref>). The strains that belong to biovar 2 and biovar 3 are only distantly related to <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1, which later led to their reclassification into the genera <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Allorhizobium</italic>, respectively (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Young et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Mousavi et al., 2015</xref>). Further refinement of the taxonomy of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1, also known as the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> species complex, was conducted based on whole-genome information using DDH, leading to the classification of strains into species-level units called genomic species or genomovars (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Popoff et al., 1984</xref>). This classification framework was later validated and enriched by studies using amplified fragment-length polymorphism (AFLP), marker gene phylogeny, multi-locus sequence analysis (MLSA), comparative genome hybridization (CGH) and core-genome phylogeny (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Portier et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Costechareyre et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Lassalle et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Mousavi et al., 2015</xref>), as recently reviewed by <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Flores-Felix et al. (2020)</xref>. At the time of writing this communication, the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genus contained 15 named species, of which 11 had validly published names. Moreover, nine out of 15 described genomic species within the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 are not yet formally named: G3 (this study), G5, G6, G7 (“<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium deltaense</italic>”), G8 (“<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium fabrum</italic>”), G13, G15 (“<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium viscosum”</italic>), G19 and G20 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Mafakheri et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
              <p>Several hundred microbial strains were isolated and identified in an ongoing investigation to map microbial diversity of the International Space Station (ISS; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Checinska Sielaff et al., 2019</xref>). The ISS is a hermetically sealed closed system and their modules are at least 20-year-old, depending on their time of addition. The source of microorganisms is mainly through the human traffic, cargo transport and also associated with other experimental components. The air of the ISS is recirculated via an advanced environmental control system, and surfaces are maintained by implementing periodic cleaning. Previous attempts to isolate microorganisms from ISS environmental surfaces revealed that they generally consist of predominantly benign and commensal microorganisms (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Mhatre et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bijlani et al., 2021</xref>), but potentially pathogenic microorganisms were also sporadically isolated (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Knox et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018a</xref>). In 2015, several bacterial strains were collected from the observation deck (Cupola) of the ISS, and whole-genome sequences (WGS) were generated for these isolates (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bharadwaj et al., 2020a</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bijlani et al., 2020a</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Daudu et al., 2020a</xref>,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Solomon et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Simpson et al., 2021</xref>). Based on preliminary genomic analyses, three ISS strains were identified as belonging to the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 (also known as <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic> genomovar G3 or <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3).</p>
              <p>The first objective of this study is to describe the phylogenomic novelty and characterize the taxonomic affiliation of the three strains isolated from the ISS environment. We, therefore, assembled a dataset of complete genomes of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3, including previously released sequences from five strains isolated from various geographical regions and environments: an eosin flask from a hospital environment in France (CFBP 6623, sequenced twice), a cave in Lechuguilla, United States (LC34), algae in the United Kingdom (SUL3), <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> roots in Germany (Root651), and bioprospecting for lignocellulolytic microbes and enzymes from natural, highly evolved plant biomass-degrading systems in the United States (UGM030330-04). We added two novel sequences from <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains from our own collection, including an opportunistic pathogen isolated from cerebrospinal fluid (CFBP 6624) and one isolated from a tobacco plant rhizosphere (RTP8). In addition to traditional phenotype testing, molecular taxonomy utilizing 16S rRNA gene, <italic toggle="yes">gyr</italic>B, MLSA (<italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> genes), and core-gene-based phylogenic analyses were carried out to describe <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains.</p>
              <p>Second objective of this study is to perform a comparative genomic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains together with representatives of other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 41 genomes) to elucidate genomic complexity. Subsequently, experimental characterization of the plasmid content was carried out on the set of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strains available to us in culture, i.e., G3 strains IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, IIF1SW-B3, IIF1SW-B4, CFBP 6623, CFBP 6624, and RTP8 and reference strains “<italic toggle="yes">A. fabrum</italic> C58,” <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium radiobacter</italic> B6<sup>T</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium pusense</italic> CFBP 5494. Thirdly, a pangenome analysis was implemented to identify core homologous gene clusters specific to ISS isolates and other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains. Finally, the metagenome reads of ISS environmental surfaces (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018b</xref>) were mined for the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 species to understand the prevalence of these novel species in ISS.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results|discussion" id="S2">
              <title>Results and Discussion</title>
              <p>The three strains collected from ISS belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 along with six other G3 strains were subjected to a polyphasic characterization to determine the variable, conserved or distinctive traits of this genomic species.</p>
              <sec id="S2.SS1">
                <title>Genome Characteristics of Novel Genome Sequences</title>
                <p><xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes assembly statistics of all five novel ISS strains sequenced in this study. As an example, for strain IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, the Illumina NovaSeq platform yielded 1.8 × 10<sup>7</sup> paired-end (PE) reads were reduced to 1.79 × 10<sup>7</sup> PE reads after performing trimming and quality filtering. The assembled draft genome of ISS strains consisted of 76–81 contigs with a genome size of 6.25–6.29 × 10<sup>6</sup> bp; the assembled genomes of CFBP 6624 and RTP8 had 35 and 38 contigs, for a size of 5.48 × 10<sup>6</sup> bp and 5.44 × 10<sup>6</sup> bp, respectively. The contig N50 size was 3.21–3.78 × 10<sup>5</sup>-bp, with a mean coverage of 100x for ISS strains, and 18x and 19x for strains CFBP 6624 and RTP8, respectively. G + C% of the five genomes was 59.12–59.21.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>TABLE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Summary of the draft whole-genome sequences of several <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> strains.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Genome characteristics</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup></bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>IIF1SW-B3</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>IIF1SW-B4</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>CFBP 6624</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>RTP8</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCBI WGS accession</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYF000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYF000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYG000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYG000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYG000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYG000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JAFIRL000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JAFIRL000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JAFIRM000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JAFIRM000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># contigs (&gt; = 0 bp)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># contigs (&gt; = 1000 bp)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length (&gt; = 1000 bp)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,234,019</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,273,081</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,273,787</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,480,209</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,440,309</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Largest contig</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644,466</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644,466</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">726,576</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,342,491</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">928,660</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,240,486</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,282,603</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,282,746</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,483,735</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,445,056</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC (%)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.18</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.17</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.17</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.12</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.21</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350,004</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350,004</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354,854</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378,069</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320,860</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of genes</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,917</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,962</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,964</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,223</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,147</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># CDS</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,863</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,908</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,910</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,175</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,098</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S2.SS2">
                <title>Phylogenetic Relationship of G3 Strains With Other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> Species</title>
                <p>A Maximum Likelihood (ML) tree of 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) gene sequences shows that this marker is not able to resolve and distinguish all <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). All strains from genomospecies G3 and G4; G7 and G13; as well as G2 and G9 were found to have identical 16S rRNA gene sequences. In addition, the support for the topology of the 16S tree is generally low, with only branches leading to species <italic toggle="yes">A. rubi</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium bohemicum</italic> and the clade formed by <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies G6 and G8 being well supported. In addition, the type strains of non-biovar 1 species <italic toggle="yes">A. larrymoorei</italic> and “<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium albertimagni</italic>” are positioned within the clade containing otherwise only <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 strains, indicating that these 16S alleles are likely the result of horizontal gene transfer events. Similar results showing high similarities or identical 16S rDNA sequences for <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rosae</italic> NCPPB-1650<sup>T</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium skierniewicense</italic> Di1472 (99.7%), and <italic toggle="yes">A. rubi</italic> NBRC 13261<sup>T</sup> (99.5%) were reported (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kuzmanović et al., 2018</xref>). This altogether suggests that the 16S rRNA gene is not a good marker to identify <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species or to study their relationships, as observed in other taxa (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">La Duc et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>FIGURE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Phylogeny of 40 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> spp. strains based on 16S rRNA gene, <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, and MLSA. Conserved marker gene phylogenies of 40 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> distinct strains (41 when including the two published genome versions for strain CFBP 6623. <bold>(A)</bold> 16S rRNA gene phylogeny, based on 1,602 aligned positions), rooted with sequence from <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic> USDA 2370<sup>T</sup>; <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene phylogeny, based on 2,477 aligned positions; <bold>(C)</bold> multi-locus sequence analysis phylogeny, based on the concatenated alignments of genes <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic>, resulting into 9,968 aligned positions. All gene sequences were extracted from the 41 studied and then aligned with Clustal Omega (for coding genes, alignment was performed at the protein level and then reverse-translated into codons). Maximum-likelihood trees were inferred with RAxML-NG 1.0.0 under the model GTR + FO + G4m, taking the best of 20 independent inferences, started with 10 random trees and 10 parsimony-optimized tree. Branch supports were estimated with 200 Felsenstein bootstrap trees. Only branch support over 70% are displayed; full information on the trees are available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792148" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792148</ext-link>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792169" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792169</ext-link>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792100" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792100</ext-link>.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-12-765943-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The gene <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> provides a much better phylogenetic resolution of relationship among <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species, with all except genomospecies G7 forming highly supported clades (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). All nine strains belonging to G3 were grouped into one clade. The shallow grouping of species into clades is highly supported except G4, G7, and G9 strains, but deeper relationships within the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 are not. This indicate that <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> is a bona fide marker gene to identify and study the diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species, even though its use as a marker for amplicon-based surveys has been shown to be impractical due to the presence of the paralogous gene <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic> in the genome rendering selective amplification difficult (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Puławska and Kałużna, 2012</xref>).</p>
                <p>The MLSA tree provides further resolution for <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species, where strains belonging to various genomospecies were placed in a tight clade with high bootstrap values (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). The relationships between species according to this MLSA tree are mostly in agreement with previous reports based on the concatenation of multiple loci or core-genome genes (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Mousavi et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Lassalle et al., 2017</xref>), indicating that this four-loci MLSA scheme (including <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> genes) provides an efficient way to affiliate phylogenetic relationships among <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species. All nine strains of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 formed a clade with a bootstrap value &gt;88%.</p>
                <p>Finally, a tree based on the concatenation of 1,089 core-genome genes is fully resolved, with almost all branches having the highest support (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, bootstrap supports indicated if not 100%), and thus constitutes the gold standard for depicting the phylogenetic relationships of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>FIGURE 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Phylogeny of 40 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> spp. strains based on the concatenation of 1,089 core-genome genes. Maximum-likelihood phylogenetic tree of 40 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> distinct strains (41 when including the two published genome versions for strain CFBP 6623) obtained using the bioinformatic pipeline Pantagruel (data available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792178" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792178</ext-link>). The tree was computed with RAxML 8.1.2 based on the concatenation of 1,089 core-genome gene alignments under the GTRCATX model, with 200 rapid bootstraps and rooted with RAxML tree-balance algorithm. All branch supports are 100%, unless displayed.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-12-765943-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>According to the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> and MLSA trees, the closest species to <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains is the group formed of “<italic toggle="yes">A. fabrum</italic>” (G8) and <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G6 strains, and these results were in accordance with previous reports (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Lassalle et al., 2017</xref>). However, the core-genome tree revealed that the closest relatives were strains <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. (<italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic> sp.) UGM030330-04 and <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. (<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rhizogenes</italic>) K599 whereas strains belonging to genomovars G8 and G6 formed a different and distant clade (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). We note that strains UGM030330-04 and K599 are misnamed given these phylogenies clearly show that they are members of the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genus and thus not part of <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic>, nor of <italic toggle="yes">A. rhizogenes</italic>, which is a synonym of <italic toggle="yes">R. rhizogenes</italic>; they are thus more correctly referred to as <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S2.SS3">
                <title>Overall Genome Relatedness Indexes</title>
                <p>All average nucleotide index (ANI) values among <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains were over 97.5% whereas when comparing G3 strains to non-G3 strains, the ANI values were below 90.68% (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="DS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). The ANI values of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains and most closely related (as per core-genome) <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. strains UGM030330-04 and K599 were ∼90.5% similarity. Similarly, the ANI values of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains with other closely related – according to <italic toggle="yes">gyr</italic>B and MLSA trees – <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G6 (NCPPB 925) and G8 strains (J-07 and C58), exhibited ∼87.6% relatedness. Furthermore, average amino-acid identity (AAI) values among <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains were over 97.6% while values between G3 and other agrobacteria were below 94%. Likewise, the digital DNA:DNA hybridization (dDDH) values among <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains were over 83.6% while values between <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 and other agrobacteria were 41.7% or below. More specifically the dDDH values were ∼41.7% for comparisons with strains UGM030330-04 and K599, 34.5% with G6 strains, and &lt;33.9% with G8 strains. The ANI and dDDH values obtained for all the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 strains – including the ISS isolates – with other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species were below the threshold of 95% ANI (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Yoon et al., 2017</xref>) and 70% dDDH values (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Auch et al., 2010</xref>), which were established as standard for prokaryotic species delineation. We thus propose the name <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> for the genomospecies 3 (= genomovar G3) of the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 (i.e., <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic> species complex).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>TABLE 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>List of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomes used in this study and Average Nucleotide Identity (ANI), Average Amino acid Identity (AAI), and digital DNA-DNA Hybridization (dDDH) values of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup> compared with all other tested <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strains.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Organism</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>GenBank #</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                          <bold>OGRI values in comparison to <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup></bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Genomospecies</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>ANI</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>AAI</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>dDDH</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYF000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYF000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> IIF1SW-B3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYG000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYG000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> IIF1SW-B4</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYH000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYH000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 CFBP 6623</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900013535.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900013535.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.08</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.62</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. (<italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic> sp.) Root651</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_001427625.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_001427625.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.74</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.25</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.60</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 LC34</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_001005815.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_001005815.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.82</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.77</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.50</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 SUL3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_001263295.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_001263295.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.64</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.73</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 CFBP 6624</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JAFIRL000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JAFIRL000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.09</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.20</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 RTP8</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="JAFIRM000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JAFIRM000000000</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.08</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.15</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.40</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3 CFBP 6623</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCA_005221385.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCA_005221385.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.12</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.61</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.80</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. (<italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic> sp.) UGM030330-04</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_003208455.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_003208455.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.58</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.91</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.70</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. (<italic toggle="yes">A. rhizogenes</italic>) K599</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_002005205.3" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_002005205.3</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.51</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.39</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.50</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 7 Zutra 3/1</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900013515.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900013515.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.63</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.71</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.70</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 13 CFBP 6927</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900012615.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank"/>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.59</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.49</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.20</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium deltaense</italic> CNPSo 3391</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_003931535.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_003931535.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.66</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.25</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 7 RV3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900013505.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900013505.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.56</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.77</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 5 CFBP 6626</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900012595.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900012595.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.11</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.62</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.40</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium radiobacter</italic> B6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900045375.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900045375.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.97</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.95</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.40</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium radiobacter</italic> Kerr 14</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900011755.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900011755.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.79</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.06</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 6 NCPPB 925</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900012625.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900012625.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.54</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.09</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.50</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium fabrum</italic> J-07</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900013525.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900013525.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.39</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.88</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium fabrum</italic> C58</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_000092025.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_000092025.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.41</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.68</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.70</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 9 Hayward 0363</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900012565.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900012565.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.76</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.98</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.20</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium salinitolerans</italic> YIC 5082</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_002008225.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_002008225.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.55</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.18</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium arsenijevicii</italic> KFB 330</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_000949895.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_000949895.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.04</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.42</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.70</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="t2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">
                            <sup>*</sup>
                          </xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium nepotum</italic> 39 7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_000949865.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_000949865.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.21</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.99</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.60</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> CFBP 5771</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900039255.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900039255.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.72</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.34</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium fabacearum</italic> CNPSo 675</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_009649785.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_009649785.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.66</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.97</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.20</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 1 TT111</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900012575.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900012575.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.60</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.84</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 2 CFBP 5494</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900013495.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900013495.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.37</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.58</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 1 S56</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900014385.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900014385.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.51</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.89</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.10</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium pusense</italic> LMG 25623</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_900102105.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_900102105.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.51</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.59</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.80</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium larrymoorei</italic> AF3 10 ATCC 51759</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_000518585.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_000518585.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.42</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.11</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.80</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rubi</italic> W2 73</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_001692345.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_001692345.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.93</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.37</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rosae</italic> B20 3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_002915175.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_002915175.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.96</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rubi</italic> TR3 NBRC 13261</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_000739935.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_000739935.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.96</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.98</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium skierniewicense</italic> Di1472</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_013320815.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_013320815.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.42</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.84</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rosae</italic> NCPPB 1650</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_002915195.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_002915195.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.81</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.35</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium bohemicum</italic> R89-1</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_001562555.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_001562555.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.67</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.62</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium bohemicum</italic> R90</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_002896715.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_002896715.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.51</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.47</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium albertimagni</italic> AOL15</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <ext-link xlink:href="GCF_000300855.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">GCF_000300855.1</ext-link>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.04</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.57</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.60</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t2fn1">
                      <p>
                        <italic toggle="yes">*<italic toggle="yes">A. arsenijevicii</italic> is part of the <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic> species complex but has not received a genomospecies number.</italic>
                      </p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> sp. strains UGM030330-04 and K599 consistently form a distinct group in the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, MLSA and core-genome tree; these two strains share an ANI of 98.11% and have &lt;90.68% ANI with any other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strain. We therefore propose to group them into a new genomospecies of the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1, to be named genomovar G21, following the recently described genomovars G19 and G20 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Mafakheri et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S2.SS4">
                <title>Phenotypic Characterization</title>
                <p>Differential phenotypic characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains with six other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species are given in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="DS2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>. The biochemical tests were highly variable among <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species tested, in accordance with previous reports (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kuzmanović et al., 2018</xref>). However, we found a distinctive trait in that all <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 strains except those belonging to the <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> assimilated D-galacturonic acid. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains tested assimilated the following carbon sources (<xref rid="DS2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). D-maltose, D-trehalose, D-cellobiose, gentiobiose, sucrose, D-turanose, stachyose, D-raffinose, α-D-lactose, D-melibiose, β-methyl-D-glucoside, D-salicin, N-acetyl-D-glucosamine, N-acetyl-D-galactosamine, α-<sc>D</sc>-glucose, D-mannose, D-fructose, D-galactose, D-fucose, L-fucose, L-rhamnose, D-sorbitol, D-mannitol, D-arabitol, myo-inositol, glycerol, <sc>D</sc>-glucose- 6-PO4, D-fructose- 6-PO4, L-alanine, L-arginine, L-aspartic acid, L-glutamic acid, L-histidine, L-pyroglutamic acid, L-serine, pectin, D-gluconic acid, D-Glucuronic acid, quinic acid, methyl pyruvate, L-malic acid, γ-amino-butyric acid, propionic acid, acetic acid. Moreover, L-lactic acid, D-malic acid, bromosuccinic acid, β-hydroxy-D, L-butyric acid and acetoacetic acid support at least a weak metabolic activity. However, no metabolic activity was observed for <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains on N-acetyl-β-D-mannosamine, N-acetyl neuraminic acid, 3-Methyl Glucose, fusidic acid, D-serine, D-aspartic acid, D-galacturonic acid, L-galactonic acid lactone, mucic acid, D-saccharic acid, p-hydroxyphenylacetic acid, and sodium butyrate.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                  <label>TABLE 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Differential biochemical characteristics between <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> and closely related species.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Biochemical tests</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">A. nepotum<xref rid="t3fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">“A. fabrum”</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">A. pusense</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">A. radiobacter</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic toggle="yes">A. larrymoorei<xref rid="t3fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></italic>
                          </bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup></bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>CFBP 5771</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>39/7<sup>T</sup></bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>C58</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>CFBP 5494</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>B6</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>AF3.10<sup>T</sup></bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Raffinose</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">α-D-Lactose</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Arginine</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl Pyruvate</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-Acetyl-D-Galactosamine</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Galacturonic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Saccharic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Glucuronic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Lactic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Malic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bromosuccinic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetoacetic Acid</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pectin</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="t3fn1">
                      <p>
                        <italic toggle="yes">*Data from <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Puławska et al. (2012)</xref>; **Data from <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bouzar and Jones (2001)</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Panday et al. (2011)</xref>. +, positive; −, negative; w, weak reactions; nd, not determined.</italic>
                      </p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Among various compounds tested, ISS <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains did not metabolize citric acid and Niaproof 4 (an anionic surfactant) whereas other <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains utilized them. Most of the compounds tested were metabolized unvaryingly by all ISS strains whereas strain IIF1SW-B3 was able to utilize lithium chloride as sole carbon source as that of other <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains tested. Similarly, strain IIF1SW-B3 was metabolizing Tween 40 (polysorbate, surfactant) but other <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains did not assimilate it. However, all six tested <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains are tolerant to troleandomycin, rifamycin SV, lincomycin, guanidine HCl, vancomycin, potassium tellurite, aztreonam, 1% sodium lactate, tetrazolium violet, and tetrazolium blue, but not to minocycline. Moreover, they all grew at pH 6 but not or only weakly at pH 5. All six tested <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains did not grow at 4% NaCl and beyond. The strains IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, IIF1SW-B4, and RTP8 tested on tomato produced no tumor (results not shown) and are therefore considered not pathogenic on tomato plant.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S2.SS5">
                <title>Comparative Genomic Analysis and <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic>-Specific Gene Content</title>
                <p>Forty-nine genes were specifically found in <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> genomes. These genes were mostly interspersed in the genome and coded a range of functions (<xref rid="DS3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>), but a fraction clustered into three genomic islands, two on the linear chromosome and one on the largest of the two megaplasmids present in strain CFBP 6623 (pCFBP6623a). The first cluster of seven <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> specific genes clearly encodes the biosynthesis of a surface polysaccharide; the second encodes mostly proteins of unknown function, with one potentially related to type 6 secretion systems; the last <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> specific gene cluster on the plasmid encodes resistance to copper. Other <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> specific genes are scattered in the genome, but have related functions. There are notably two genes encoding ankyrin-repeat domain-containing proteins, as well as a protein containing an extracellular HAF repeat domain (InterPro domain IPR014262) and an autotransporter domain, all three exported to the cell surface and likely mediating attachment to an extracellular substrate. Together with the biosynthesis of a likely extracellular polysaccharide, these species-specific genes present a convergent function related to surface attachment and potentially resistance to stress from the external medium. This enrichment in the specific core-genome of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> suggests natural selection was at work and that surface attachment may have a strong role in <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> ecology. Indeed, the first reported <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains CFBP 6623 and CFBP 6624 were isolated from within an eosin flask and from a human clinical sample (likely as an opportunist taking advantage of another pathogen infection), respectively (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Popoff et al., 1984</xref>), showing already unusual colonization abilities for agrobacteria. Moreover, the strains recovered from the ISS were isolated from the surface of the observation dome (Cupola), which panel is made of aluminum with a polyurethane topcoat (e.g., Aeroglaze A276 or BMS10-60), an ultra-clean and smooth surface that carries very little microbial life. The independent isolation of G3 strains in such locations suggest that attachment to inhospitable surfaces may be a way for <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> to colonize new habitats where it can evade competition with other microbes.</p>
                <p>Similarly, the gene clustering analysis between the genomes of 40 different <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strains allowed the identification of ISS strains-specific gene clusters (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="DS4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). We found 556 genes specifically present in the three ISS strains; we identified these genes based on their presence in all ISS strains and none of the 17 genomes in the background clade comprising the other <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains, all strains of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium arsenijevicii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium nepotum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies G1, G5, G13, and G2 (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data</xref> online)<sup><xref rid="footnote1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></sup>. Using a more relaxed criterion allowing presence of the genes in a maximum of 2 out the 17 genomes in the background clade, to allow the detection of genes specifically gained by the ancestor of the ISS strains but that may have independently introduced in close relatives via horizontal gene transfer, we found 838 genes (<xref rid="DS4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>), most of them located in large contiguous regions.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F3">
                  <label>FIGURE 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Visualization of the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> pangenome. Genomes are ordered as layers using a tree based on average nucleotide identity (ANI) values matrix (Euclidean distance, Ward clustering). Color hue of ANI values are ranging from 70% ANI (white) to 100% ANI (red) and displayed as a heatmap on the right-side panel. Gene clusters are represented as vertical black bars indicating their presence in each genome layer. The central tree is ordering gene clusters based on their presence/absence in genomes using Euclidean distance and Ward clustering. The “Core GC” highlight indicates the gene clusters identified in all genomes. Gene clusters that are found in a single genome are collapsed as “Singletons GC.” The “<italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> ISS strains GC” highlight indicates gene clusters found exclusively on the three strains isolated from the International Space Station. The figure was created in Anvi’o v6.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-12-765943-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Among this wider set of ISS clone-specific genes, some were found to cover 10 entire contigs of the genome assembly of strain IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup> (<xref rid="DS5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref>), totaling to 347 genes over 613 kb of ISS clone-specific contigs, which possibly represent (parts of) extrachromosomal elements. Indeed, four of these ISS clone-specific contigs carried genes with functions associated to type 4 secretion systems (T4SS), with two seemingly complete clusters, indicating they may constitute conjugative elements such as plasmids or integrative and conjugative elements (ICE). Most of the other ISS clone-specific contigs carried transposase or genetic mobility-associated genes, suggesting they also constitute mobile genetic elements (MGEs). In addition, large contiguous portions of other contigs that were specific to the ISS strains carried transposase genes – often located at the extremity of the ISS clone-specific region – suggesting they may represent inserted MGEs such as transposons or genomic islands (<xref rid="DS4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 4</xref>, <xref rid="DS5" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>). In particular, the ISS clone-specific region of contigs #27 of strain IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup> genome assembly clearly corresponds to a prophage.</p>
                <p>Beyond genetic mobility, the ISS clone-specific genes displayed a range of other functions, which were enriched for a range of functions, some forming coherent cellular processes (<xref rid="DS6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). Among the top enriched functions, we found a multi-copper oxidase, accompanied by a chaperone for its maturation and transporters that might allow the assimilation of copper ions from the environment; these functions may form a pathway for biosynthesis of a redox enzyme that could be involved in a respiratory chain. Another set of coherent functions were found to be involved in scavenging and uptake of a ferric ion-siderophore complex, as well as a non-ribosomal peptide synthases-polyketide synthases (NRPS/PKS) biosynthetic cluster, which might be involved in the biosynthesis of the siderophore.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S2.SS6">
                <title>Plasmid Profiling</title>
                <p>Based on migration of genomic DNA on Eckhardt gels (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Vaudequin-Dransart et al., 1995</xref>), all <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains were evidenced to carry plasmids, although differences in size and number were observed between strains (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Indeed, strain CFBP 6624 presented a single plasmid of approximately 500 kb, whereas CFBP 6623, RTP8 and the three ISS strains showed one to three plasmids, with a common largest band around 260 kb. RTP8 and the three ISS strains have in common a 130-kb plasmid, and a 40-kb plasmid is present exclusively in the three ISS strains. The ISS strains do not harbor a pTi plasmid, as no classical <italic toggle="yes">vir</italic> genes were detected in their genomes (data not shown). Accordingly, no symptoms of crown-gall diseases were observed on injured tomato plants inoculated with any of the ISS strains (data not shown).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S2.SS7">
                <title><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> Reads in International Space Station Metagenomes</title>
                <p>In order to evaluate the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> onboard the ISS, we performed metagenomic read recruitment obtained from ISS environmental DNA shotgun datasets (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018b</xref>) with strain IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup> genome as a reference. Visual inspection of the mapped read profiles showed that most recruited reads were located on conserved bacterial genes encoding products such as ribosomal RNA operons, ribosomal proteins, DNA-directed RNA polymerase <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> or elongation factor Tu. Considering the high degree of conservation of these genes across distant bacterial lineages and the non-uniform read coverage of G3 contigs we conclude that despite being isolated from the same environment, <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> is not present in any detectable abundance in the ISS metagenomes.</p>
                <p>In summary, <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> genomes are diverse, and notably carry a variety of plasmids, even though none of the G3 strain in our dataset carried a tumorigenic plasmid. As previously shown for other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomic species (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Lassalle et al., 2017</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strain genomes share a number of species-specific genes. <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> specific gene functions notably relate to surface adhesion and could be involved in the ecological specificity of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> suggested by their varied source of isolation (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Popoff et al., 1984</xref>). Indeed, while most species of the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 are usually isolated from soils, plant rhizospheres or as plant pathogens inducing tumors (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Barton et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dodueva et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Weisberg et al., 2020</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains never have been isolated as a plant pathogen, nor a tumor-inducing plasmid was observed in their genome, which we confirmed by negative infection tests on tomato plants. Even though the isolation of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains RTP8 from a tobacco plant rhizosphere and Root651 from <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> roots prove that <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains are able to survive in plant rhizospheres, <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains were otherwise all isolated from a variety of unhospitable environments, including from an antiseptic flask, as an opportunistic pathogen of the human central nervous system, from a cave wall, and lastly from the inert surface of the ISS cupola. The ability to colonize these substrates, unusual for most agrobacteria, resonate with the finding that <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> genomes specifically carry genes involved in mediating attachment to surfaces, including production of putative adhesins and biofilm. This suggests a particular ability of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> to colonize a different kind of habitats, that are even poorer in nutrients and harsher than soil, thus possibly escaping competition with other agrobacteria that are better at growing in richer environments such as plant rhizospheres.</p>
                <p>The genomes of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains isolated from the ISS, appear to be highly similar, suggesting they are clonally related. As such, they carry further specific genomic traits, including the presence of a 40-kbp plasmid observed via electrophoresis, as well as several other potential MGEs detected in their specific genomic content, with several ISS clone-specific contigs carrying conjugation genes (cumulated length 346 kbp) and more contigs that could also be part of conjugative elements or other types of MGEs such as integrated prophages. These ISS clone-specific genes also include many potentially adaptive genes, including putative pathways for respiratory chain biosynthesis and iron scavenging, but it is unclear what would be the selective advantage those genes could bring to the ISS strains in the context they were isolated from.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S3">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p>Using a polyphasic approach, we characterized the phenotypic and genotypic synapomorphies of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> G3 (<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomospecies 3), showing it is a <italic toggle="yes">bona fide</italic> bacterial species, well separated from previously named <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species or other recognized genomic species. Based on this evidence, we propose to name this species <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> (formal description below). In addition, we performed an in-depth investigation of the pangenome, notably identifying species-specific genes, allowing us to relate the description of this new species to hypotheses on its ecology. Within this novel species, we further characterized the clonal group of strain isolated from the ISS, showing it possesses its own set of specific genes and MGEs that could carry adaptive traits linked to its survival in the ISS environment.</p>
              <sec id="S3.SS1">
                <title>Description of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> sp. nov.</title>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> (tom. ko’ni.s. N.L gen. n. <italic toggle="yes">tomkonis</italic> referring to David Tomko, a well-known NASA Space Biology scientist who advanced space research in the United States). Cells are Gram-stain-negative, non-spore-forming, aerobic rods, 0.5–0.6 μm in width and 0.8–1.6 μm in length. Colonies are translucent and cream to white, with a diameter of 2–3 mm on R2A medium after incubation for 3 days at 25°C. Growth occurs at 20°C through 35°C, with an optimum temperature of 25°C. <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains grew at pH 6 but not or only weakly at pH 5 with a pH optimum at 7.5. All tested <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains failed to grow at 4% NaCl and beyond.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains metabolize D-maltose, D-trehalose, D-cellobiose, gentiobiose, sucrose, D-turanose, stachyose, D-raffinose, α-D-lactose, D-melibiose, β-methyl-D-glucoside, D-salicin, N-acetyl-D-glucosamine, N-acetyl-D-galactosamine, α-<sc>D</sc>-glucose, D-mannose, D-fructose, D-galactose, D-fucose, L-fucose, L-rhamnose, D-sorbitol, D-mannitol, D-arabitol, myo-inositol, glycerol, <sc>D</sc>-glucose- 6-PO4, D-fructose- 6-PO4, L-alanine, L-arginine, L-aspartic acid, L-glutamic acid, L-histidine, L-pyroglutamic acid, L-serine, pectin, D-gluconic acid, D-Glucuronic acid, quinic acid, methyl pyruvate, L-malic acid, γ-amino-butyric acid, propionic acid, acetic acid. However, did not utilize N-acetyl-β-D-mannosamine, N-acetyl neuraminic acid, 3-Methyl Glucose, fusidic acid, D-serine, D-aspartic acid, D-galacturonic acid, L-galactonic acid lactone, mucic acid, D-saccharic acid, p-hydroxyphenylacetic acid, and sodium butyrate.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains tested are tolerant to troleandomycin, rifamycin SV, lincomycin, guanidine HCl, vancomycin, potassium tellurite, aztreonam, 1% sodium lactate, tetrazolium violet, and tetrazolium blue, but not to minocycline.</p>
                <p>The delineation of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> from other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species was based on overall genome relatedness indexes (all <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> share ANI &gt; 98% and dDDH &gt; 84%), as well as based on well-supported clades in <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene, MLSA (with <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> genes) or core-genome phylogenies. The type strain, IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup> (= LMG 32164 = NRRL B-65602), was isolated from the ISS Port panel of the Cupola, which is the observation deck for the crew. The type strain DNA G + C content is 59.18 mol% and its genome sequence is available from GenBank under WGS accession <ext-link xlink:href="JABXYF000000000" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">JABXYF000000000</ext-link>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S4">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <sec id="S4.SS1">
                <title>Sample Collection and Isolation of Bacteria</title>
                <p>The sampling of ISS surfaces performed for this study took place within the United States on-orbit segments. Samples collected during this study were: Node 3 (Locations #1, #2, and #3), Node 1 (Locations #4 and #5), Permanent Multipurpose Module (Location #6), U.S. Laboratory (Location #7), and Node 2 (Locations #8 and control). A detailed description of the various locations sampled was published elsewhere (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018b</xref>). Sample collection from ISS environmental surfaces, processing, and cultivation of bacteria have been previously reported (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Checinska Sielaff et al., 2019</xref>). Three strains isolated during the second flight from Location #1 (Cupola) surfaces, were later identified as belonging to the genus <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> via 16S rRNA gene sequencing of the cultivated strains; these were designated: IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, IIF1SW-B3, and IIF1SW-B4.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS2">
                <title>Phenotypic Characterization</title>
                <p>Strains IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, IIF1SW-B3, IIF1SW-B4, CFBP 6623, CFBP 6624, and RTP8 strains were subjected for the phenotypic characterization. All strains are grown on yeast extract-peptone-glucose (YPG) medium and collected from the surface of the agar plates (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Scortichini, 2012</xref>) before inoculation and screened for various organic substrate utilization using Biolog GEN III system (Biolog, Inc., Hayward, CA, United States) following manufacturer’s recommendations. Concurrently, two replicates of Biolog tests were carried out, and Biolog plates were incubated at 28°C for 48 h. After incubation, the OmniLog<sup>TM</sup> system was used to measure carbon substrate utilization.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS3">
                <title>Molecular Characterization of International Space Station Strains</title>
                <p>A loopful of purified microbial culture (only ISS strains) was subjected to DNA extraction with the UltraClean DNA kit (MO BIO, Carlsbad, CA, United States) or Maxwell Automated System (Promega, Madison, WI, United States) as per manufacturer instructions. The extracted DNA was eluted in 50-μL of molecular grade water and stored at −20°C until further analysis. The 16S rRNA gene was amplified using the forward primer, 27F (5′-AGA GTT TGA TCC TGG CTC AG-3′) and the reverse primer, 1492R (5′-GGT TAC CTT GTT ACG ACT T-3′) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Checinska Sielaff et al., 2019</xref>) and PCR was performed with the following conditions: denaturation at 95°C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles consisting of denaturation at 95°C for 50 s, annealing at 55°C for 50 s, and extension at 72°C for 1.5 min, and finalized by extension at 72°C for 10 min. The amplified products were treated with Antarctic phosphatase and exonuclease (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, United States) to remove 5′- and 3′- phosphates from unused dNTPs before sequencing. Sequencing was performed by Macrogen (Rockville, MD, United States) using 27F and 1492R primers for <italic toggle="yes">Bacteria</italic>. The resulting sequences were assembled using SeqMan Pro from the DNASTAR Lasergene package (DNASTAR Inc., Madison, WI, United States). Bacterial sequences were searched against the EzTaxon-e database (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2012</xref>) and identified based on the closest percentage similarity (&gt;98.6%) to previously identified microbial-type strains.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS4">
                <title>Analysis of Plasmid Content</title>
                <p>Plasmid profiles were determined by a modified Eckhardt agarose gel electrophoresis technique as previously described (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Vial et al., 2006</xref>). Isolates were grown overnight in YPG medium at 28°C until the optical density at 600 nm reached 0.4. Electrophoresis was carried out at 5 V for 30 min and 90 V for 5 h at 4°C on a 0.75% agarose gel containing 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate. Plasmids sizes were estimated by comparison with those of “<italic toggle="yes">A. fabrum</italic>” C58 and <italic toggle="yes">Allorhizobium vitis</italic> S4 (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Wood et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Slater et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS5">
                <title>Analysis of International Space Station Strains Pathogenicity on Tomato Plant</title>
                <p>To test if the ISS G3 strains were plant-pathogen strains, 3-week-old tomato plants, cultivated with a photoperiod of 16 h/8 h light/dark in a greenhouse were stem-injured and inoculated with 10 μL of bacterial overnight culture (10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml). The plants were then incubated for 21 days, and the presence or absence of crown gall symptoms was established by visual inspection. “<italic toggle="yes">A. fabrum</italic>” C58 strain was used as the positive control.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS6">
                <title>Whole Genome Sequencing of New <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> Strains</title>
                <p>The WGS sequencing of the three ISS G3 strains was carried out as per established procedures (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018a</xref>). Shotgun libraries were prepared using the Illumina Nextera Flex protocol (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018b</xref>) and sequenced using NovaSeq 6000 S4 flow cell 2 × 150 PE sequencing kit. Verification of the quality of the raw sequencing data was carried out using FastQC v0.11.7 using default parameters<sup><xref rid="footnote2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></sup>. Quality control for adapter trimming and quality filtering were performed using fastp v0.20.0 (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>), and then SPAdes v3.11.1 (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Bankevich et al., 2012</xref>) was used to assemble all the cleaned sequences. Fastp quality control was based on the following three parameters: (i) correction of mismatches in overlapped regions of paired-end reads, (ii) trimming of autodetected adapter sequences, and (iii) quality trimming at the 59 and 39 ends. To determine the quality of the assembled sequences, the number of contigs, the N50 value, and the total length were calculated using QUAST v5.0.2 (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Gurevich et al., 2013</xref>). Default parameters were used for all software. The WGS sequencing of strains RTP8 and CFBP 6624 was carried out by Beckman Coulter Genomics (Takeley, Essex, United Kingdom). SPAdes v3.8.1 (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Bankevich et al., 2012</xref>) was used to assemble all the cleaned sequences. All five new genomes were annotated using Prokka v1.14.5 (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Seemann, 2014</xref>) with the following options: “–force –addgenes –compliant –usegenus.” Protein function was annotated by performing a blastp similarity search against a reference proteome database made of 405 high-quality genome assemblies obtained from the NCBI RefSeq, selecting all genomes belonging to the <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobiaceae</italic> family available as on 14th August 2018 that had a contig N50 greater than 98 kbp (<xref rid="DS7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 7</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS7">
                <title>Overall Genome Relatedness Index Calculations</title>
                <p>The ANI (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Yoon et al., 2017</xref>) between each pair of the 40 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomes (41 genomes including the two published versions of strain CFBP 6623 genome) was calculated using pyANI (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Pritchard et al., 2016</xref>). The dDDH analysis was performed using the Genome-to-Genome Distance Calculator 2.0 (GGDC 2.0) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Auch et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS8">
                <title>Pangenome Analysis</title>
                <p>We applied two separate pangenome analysis pipelines to obtain robust estimates of the sets of genes present and absent in each genome and to compute core and clade-specific gene sets for the various taxonomic groups represented in our dataset, including <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1, <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains including ISS isolates.</p>
                <p>(1) On one hand, a pangenomic Snakemake workflow (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Köster and Rahmann, 2012</xref>) was run in anvi’o v6.2 (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Eren et al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, gene clusters (GC) were defined by clustering all-versus-all open-reading frames BLAST similarity scores using the Markov Clustering (MCL) algorithm (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Enright et al., 2002</xref>) with an inflation score of 8. Open reading frames were identified with Prodigal 2.6.3 in single mode (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Hyatt et al., 2010</xref>). Open reading frames were annotated using COG and KOfam databases (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Eren et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Delmont and Eren, 2018</xref>). Results were displayed using <italic toggle="yes">anvi-display-pan</italic> function (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Delmont and Eren, 2018</xref>). Functional enrichment in the ISS and G3 strain sets was obtained using <italic toggle="yes">anvi-compute-functional-enrichment</italic> function, as described in <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Shaiber et al. (2020)</xref>, based on the COG annotation of open reading frames. Only enrichment for which FDR adjusted <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 are reported in <xref rid="DS5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref>.</p>
                <p>(2) On the other hand, a phylogenomic database was built with the Pantagruel pipeline (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Lassalle et al., 2019</xref>), using the ‘‘usingGeneRax’’ branch of the code<sup><xref rid="footnote3" ref-type="fn">3</xref></sup> version “df79fee577b72389926a0138353fa657c11f3368.” The following pipeline tasks were performed: init, 00-03 and 05, leading to the clustering of homologous protein families with MMseqs2 (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Steinegger and Söding, 2017</xref>), the alignment of their reverse-translated coding sequences with Clustal Omega (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et al., 2011</xref>) and Python scripts using Biopython (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Weisberg et al., 2020</xref>), and the computation of a maximum-likelihood (ML) phylogenetic tree with RAxML 8.1.2 (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Stamatakis et al., 2005</xref>) based on the concatenation of 1,089 core-genome gene alignments, as previously described (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Lassalle et al., 2021</xref>) (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data</xref> File doi: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792178" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792178</ext-link>). In addition, clade-specific sets of homologous gene clusters were determined using the “get_clade_specific_genes.r” script from Pantagruel package using the homologous gene family presence/absence matrix as input.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS9">
                <title>Metagenome Sequence Reads Recruitment to Strain IIF1SW-B1</title>
                <p>Metagenomic datasets (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 42) previously obtained from environmental swabbing of the ISS (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2018b</xref>) were downloaded from NCBI-SRA BioProject <ext-link xlink:href="PRJNA438545" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">PRJNA438545</ext-link>, quality filtered and mapped using BWA-MEM (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Li and Durbin, 2009</xref>) against the genome assembly of strain IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>. These steps were performed using anvi’o v6.2 (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Eren et al., 2015</xref>) using anvi’o metagenomic workflow in reference mode and default parameters. Visual inspection of read mapping alignment was carried out using Artemis BamView (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Carver et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="S4.SS10">
                <title>Phylogenetic Analysis of Marker Genes</title>
                <p>For the 16S rRNA gene phylogenetic analysis, we extracted the 16S rRNA sequences from the genomes and added the reference 16S gene sequence from <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic> type strain USDA 2370<sup>T</sup> (GenBank accession <ext-link xlink:href="U29386.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">U29386.1</ext-link>) and then aligned all sequences with Clustal Omega (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et al., 2011</xref>) (<xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data</xref> File doi: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792148" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792148</ext-link>). For the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> single-gene phylogenetic analyses, as well as multi-locus sequence analysis (MLSA), we used the coding sequence (CDS) alignments for the marker genes <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> from the Pantagruel database described above (see <xref rid="FS1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data</xref> Files available at doi: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792169" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792169</ext-link> and doi: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792100" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792100</ext-link>). For the MLSA, we concatenated the CDS alignments of <italic toggle="yes">parE</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rpoB</italic> into a multi-locus alignment, totaling 9,968 positions. ML Phylogenies were then inferred based on these alignments with RAxML-NG 1.0.0 (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Stamatakis et al., 2005</xref>) with the options “–model GTR + G4 –all,” implying the use of the model GTR + FO + G4m, and that 20 independent inferences were run, starting with 10 random trees and 10 parsimony-optimized tree, and retaining the best ML tree from these 20 inferences. Branch supports were estimated with 200 Felsenstein bootstrap trees. The 16S tree was rooted using <italic toggle="yes">R. leguminosarum</italic> USDA 2370<sup>T</sup> sequence, whereas the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> and MLSA trees were rooted using the sequence from “<italic toggle="yes">A. albertimagni</italic>” AOL15 – a distant relative incorrectly classified in the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genus for which a classification in the newly proposed genus “<italic toggle="yes">Peteryoungia</italic>” was proposed (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Kuzmanović et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S5">
              <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
              <p>The draft genome sequences of three ISS strains including type strainIIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, as well as strains RTP8 and CFBP 6624, were deposited in NCBI. The genome sequences of isolates <italic toggle="yes">A. tomknonis</italic> IIF1SW-B1<sup>T</sup>, RTP8, and CFBP 6624 have been deposited to GenBank under the BioSample accessions <ext-link xlink:href="SAMN15333190" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">SAMN15333190</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="SAMN17917486" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">SAMN17917486</ext-link>, and <ext-link xlink:href="SAMN17918142" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">SAMN17918142</ext-link>, respectively; the WGS project accession numbers are also given in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The genome versions described in this paper are the first versions. Analysis intermediary data and result tables are available under the FigShare project available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://figshare.com/account/home#/projects/115866" ext-link-type="uri">https://figshare.com/account/home#/projects/115866</ext-link> with individual items available at the following DOIs: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792100" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792100</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792148" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792148</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792169" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792169</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14792178" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14792178</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14883546" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14883546</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14883516" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14883516</ext-link>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.14798289" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.14798289</ext-link>, and <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.16782964" ext-link-type="uri">10.6084/m9.figshare.16782964</ext-link>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="S6">
              <title>Author Contributions</title>
              <p>CL, LV, XN, KV, and NS conceived and designed the microbiological experiments. NS, CL, and LV performed the microbiological experiments. CL and LV carried out the phenotypic assays Biolog based biochemical characterization. CL performed the plant pathogenicity experiments. LV performed plasmid content analyses. XN managed the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strain collection and the non-ISS strain genome sequencing project. NS and KV managed the ISS strain collection and the ISS strain genome sequencing project. FL, JN, and NS analyzed the data. NS analyzed the <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> assemblies, including contig alignment, and annotation checks. FL performed phylogenetic and phylogenomic analyses. JN performed metagenomic analysis. FL and JN performed pangenome analyses. FL and KV wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1">
              <title>Conflict of Interest</title>
              <p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="pudiscl1">
              <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
              <p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <sec sec-type="funding-information" id="S7">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Part of the research described in this publication was carried out at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, under a contract with National Aeronautics and Space Administration. This research was funded by a 2012 Space Biology NNH12ZTT001N grant no. 19-12829-26 under Task Order NNN13D111T award to KV, which also funded the post-doctoral fellowships for NS. This research was funded in part to FL by the Wellcome Trust Grant (206194). For the purpose of Open Access, the author has applied a CC-BY public copyright license to any author accepted manuscript version arising from this submission.</p>
            </sec>
            <ack>
              <p>We would like to thank Aleksandra Checinska-Sielaff for isolating the strain and Achintya Bharathwaj for initial phylogenetic analyses, astronauts Captain Terry Virts for collecting samples aboard the ISS and the Implementation Team at NASA Ames Research Center (Fathi Karouia) for coordinating this effort, and Ryan Kemp (Zymo Research Corp.) for extracting DNA and Dan Butler (Weill Cornell Medicine) for performing shotgun sequencing using the NovaSeq platform. We acknowledged the Jet Propulsion Laboratory supercomputing facility staff, notably Narendra J. Patel (Jimmy) and Edward Villanueva, for their continuous support in providing the best possible infrastructure for BIGDATA analysis. © 2021 California Institute of Technology, Government sponsorship acknowledged. We would also like to thank Elise Lacroix for the plant cultures at the “Serre et Chambres Climatiques” platform of the FR BioEEnViS (UCBL) and L. Loiseau of PARMIC/CRB-EML platform of Ecologie Microbienne UMR CNRS 5557, UMR INRAE 1418.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="footnote1">
                <label>1</label>
                <p>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.16782964" ext-link-type="uri">https://10.6084/m9.figshare.16782964</ext-link>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="footnote2">
                <label>2</label>
                <p>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="footnote3">
                <label>3</label>
                <p>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/flass/pantagruel/tree/usingGeneRax" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/flass/pantagruel/tree/usingGeneRax</ext-link>
                </p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S9">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2021.765943/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2021.765943/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p>
              <supplementary-material id="FS1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Plasmid profiles of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains. Strains IIF1SW-B1, IIF1SW-B3 and IIF1SW-B4 showed the same plasmidic profil. Plasmids sizes were estimated by comparison with those of <italic toggle="yes">A. fabrum</italic> C58 and <italic toggle="yes">A. vitis</italic> S4 (data not shown). LC indicates the linear chromosome.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Image_1.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>ANI matrix of all tested <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strains.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS2" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Differential biochemical characteristics among <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.docx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS3" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>COG function enriched in 9 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> (G3) strains, compared to the 31 other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomes in the dataset.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_3.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS4" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>List of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> clade-specific homologous gene families. Clade-specific genes are listed per clade; with each list starting by a hashtag and the clade id: “# cladeXX”. <italic toggle="yes">A. tumefaciens</italic> species complex/<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 is clade1; <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> is clade20; the clonal group of ISS strains is clade27. Genomes are listed using short codes, with the correspondence to strain names provided at the top.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_4.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS5" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>List of contigs specific to the clonal group of <italic toggle="yes">A. tomkonis</italic> strains isolated from the ISS and their characteristics. The count of genes with genetic mobility-related functions is based on the Prokka annotation of proteins.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_5.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS6" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 6</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>COG function enriched in 3 <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tomkonis</italic> ISS strains, compared to the 37 other <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomes in the dataset.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_6.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="DS7" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Table 7</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>List of genome assemblies used as reference to annotate the new <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> genomes with Prokka.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_7.docx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auch</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Jan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klenk</surname><given-names>H.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Göker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Digital DNA-DNA hybridization for microbial species delineation by means of genome-to-genome sequence comparison.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Stand. Genomic Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4056/sigs.531120</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21304684?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21304684</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dvorkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulikov</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Comput. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.2012.0021</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22506599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuqua</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Ecological and evolutionary dynamics of a model facultative pathogen: <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> and crown gall disease of plants.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.13976</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29105274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29105274</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharadwaj</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daudu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O’hara</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020a</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriales</italic> Strains Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e817</fpage>–<lpage>e820</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharadwaj</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O’hara</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karouia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020b</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic> Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e942</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bijlani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eedara</surname><given-names>V. V. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Podile</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Methylobacterium ajmalii</italic> sp. nov., Isolated From the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>639396</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.639396</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33790880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33790880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bijlani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswaran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020a</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas</italic> Species Associated with the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e00578</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32554796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bijlani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswaran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020b</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Tremellomycetes</italic> Strains Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e00504</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32586865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouzar</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium larrymoorei</italic> sp. nov., a pathogen isolated from aerial tumours of <italic toggle="yes">Ficus benjamina. Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>1023</fpage>–<lpage>1026</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-51-3-1023</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11411669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11411669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcquillan</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>BamView: visualizing and interpretation of next-generation sequencing read alignments.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Brief. Bioinform.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbr073</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22253280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Checinska Sielaff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbaniak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>G. B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanov</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Characterization of the total and viable bacterial and fungal communities associated with the International Space Station surfaces.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiome</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-019-0666-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30955503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30955503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>fastp: an ultra-fast all-in-one FASTQ preprocessor.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>i884</fpage>–<lpage>i890</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty560</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30423086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30423086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costechareyre</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhouma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavire</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Portier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapulliot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertolla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Rapid and efficient identification of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> species by recA allele analysis: <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> recA diversity.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microb. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>862</fpage>–<lpage>872</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-010-9685-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20521039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20521039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daudu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O’hara</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020a</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Rhodotorula mucilaginosa</italic> Strains Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e00570</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32732232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daudu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O’hara</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020b</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of Bacillaceae Strains Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e00701</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MRA.00701-20</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33122406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33122406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delmont</surname><given-names>T. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eren</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Linking pangenomes and metagenomes: the <italic toggle="yes">Prochlorococcus</italic> metapangenome.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PeerJ</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e4320</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.4320</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29423345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29423345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dessaux</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). “<article-title>Niche Construction and Exploitation by <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>: How to Survive and Face Competition in Soil and Plant Habitats</article-title>,” in <source><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium Biology: From Basic Science to Biotechnology</italic></source>, <role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gelvin</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>), <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/82_2018_83</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33311142?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodueva</surname><given-names>I. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebedeva</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gancheva</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paponova</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutova</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Plant tumors: a hundred years of study.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Planta</italic></source>
<volume>251</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-020-03375-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 32189080?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32189080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouzounis</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>An efficient algorithm for large-scale detection of protein families.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1575</fpage>–<lpage>1584</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.7.1575</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11917018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eren</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esen</surname><given-names>O. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vineis</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sogin</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Anvi’o: an advanced analysis and visualization platform for ’omics data.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">PeerJ</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e1319</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1319</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26500826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26500826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores-Felix</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menendez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peix</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Fraile</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Velazquez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>History and current taxonomic status of genus <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>126046</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2019.126046</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 31818496?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31818496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saveliev</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyahhi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>QUAST: quality assessment tool for genome assemblies.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1075</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23422339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Locascio</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larimer</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Prodigal: prokaryotic gene recognition and translation initiation site identification.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-11-119</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20211023?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Crown Gall of Stone Fruit II. Identification and Nomenclature of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> Isolates.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Aust. J. Biol. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kersters</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sneath</surname><given-names>P. H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sackin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Numerical Taxonomic Analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiology</italic></source>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-78-2-227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Introducing EzTaxon-e: a prokaryotic 16S rRNA gene sequence database with phylotypes that represent uncultured species.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>716</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.038075-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22140171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22140171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blachowicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romsdahl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttenlocher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> Isolates from Air and Surfaces of the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">mSphere</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>e00227</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27830189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Köster</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Snakemake—a scalable bioinformatics workflow engine.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>2520</fpage>–<lpage>2522</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts480</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22908215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22908215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmanović</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagorzi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicenzo</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Taxonomy of <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobiaceae</italic> revisited: proposal of a new framework for genus delimitation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">bioRxiv</italic></source> [Preprint]. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.08.02.454807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmanović</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puławska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smalla</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesme</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium rosae</italic> sp. nov., isolated from galls on different agricultural crops.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2018.01.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29426637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29426637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Duc</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satomi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswaran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>gyrB as a phylogenetic discriminator for members of the <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus anthracis-cereus-thuringiensis</italic> group.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Microbiol. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2003.11.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14967230?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14967230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campillo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baude</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costechareyre</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapulliot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Genomic species are ecological species as revealed by comparative genomics in <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol. Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>781</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evr070</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21795751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21795751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dastgheib</surname><given-names>S. M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbarg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frühling</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Phylogenomics reveals the basis of adaptation of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudorhizobium</italic> species to extreme environments and supports a taxonomic revision of the genus.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>126165</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2020.126165</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33360413?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33360413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Planel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapulliot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbe</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubost</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Ancestral Genome Estimation Reveals the History of Ecological Diversification in <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol. Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>3413</fpage>–<lpage>3431</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evx255</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29220487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29220487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veber</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauneikaite</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Automated reconstruction of all gene histories in large bacterial pangenome datasets and search for co-evolved gene modules with Pantagruel.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">bioRxiv</italic></source> [Preprint]. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/586495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows–Wheeler transform.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1754</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19451168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macrae</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staden</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Colonization of Tomato Plants by Two Agrocin-Producing Strains of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>3133</fpage>–<lpage>3137</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.54.12.3133-3137.1988</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16347802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16347802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mafakheri</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taghavi</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puławska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lajudie</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osdaghi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Two Novel Genomospecies in the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> Species Complex Associated with Rose Crown Gall.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Phytopathology</italic></source>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>1859</fpage>–<lpage>1868</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-05-19-0178-R</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 31298994?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31298994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthysse</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Root Colonization by <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> Is Reduced in <italic toggle="yes">cel, attB, attD, and attR</italic> Mutants.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>2341</fpage>–<lpage>2345</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.64.7.2341-2345.1998</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9647796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9647796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhatre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pukall</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbarg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Description of Chloramphenicol Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Kineococcus rubinsiae</italic> sp. nov. Isolated from a Spacecraft Assembly Facility.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1957</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01957</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 32973710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32973710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Österman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahlberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesme</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavire</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Phylogeny of the <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium–Allorhizobium</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> clade supports the delineation of Neorhizobium gen. nov.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2013.12.007</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24581678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24581678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesme</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lajudie</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindström</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Revised phylogeny of <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobiaceae</italic>: proposal of the delineation of <italic toggle="yes">Pararhizobium</italic> gen. nov., and 13 new species combinations.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2014.12.003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25595870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25595870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B43">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ophel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). “<article-title>Ecology of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>: Plasmids and Biovars</article-title>,” in <source><italic toggle="yes">Molecular genetics of plant-microbe interactions: Proceedings of the Third International Symposium on the Molecular Genetics of Plant-Microbe Associations, Montréal, Québec, Canada, July 27–31, 1986</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>D. P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brisson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-009-4482-4_1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B44">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panday</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source><italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium pusense</italic> sp. nov., isolated from the rhizosphere of chickpea (<italic toggle="yes">Cicer arietinum</italic> L.). <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>2632</fpage>–<lpage>2639</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.028407-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21148676?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21148676</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B45">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popoff</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersters</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiredjian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miras</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coynault</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>[Taxonomic position of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strains of hospital origin].</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Ann. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>135A</volume>
<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B46">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Portier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer-Le Saux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mougel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerondelle</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapulliot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thioulouse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Identification of genomic species in <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> biovar 1 by AFLP genomic markers.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>7123</fpage>–<lpage>7131</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00018-06</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16936063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16936063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B47">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphris</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elphinstone</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Genomics and taxonomy in diagnostics for food security: soft-rotting <italic toggle="yes">enterobacter</italic>ial plant pathogens.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Anal. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c5ay02550h</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B48">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puławska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kałużna</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic relationship and genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> spp. isolated in Poland based on gyrB gene sequence analysis and RAPD.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</italic></source>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10658-011-9911-2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B49">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puławska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Süle</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source><italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium nepotum</italic> sp. nov. isolated from tumors on different plant species. <italic toggle="yes">Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2012.03.001</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22463808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22463808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B50">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramírez-Bahena</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapulliot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daubin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Single acquisition of protelomerase gave rise to speciation of a large and diverse clade within the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium/Rhizobium</italic> supercluster characterized by the presence of a linear chromid.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2014.01.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24440816?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24440816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B51">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanguin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Remenant</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechesne</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thioulouse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesme</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Potential of a 16S rRNA-Based Taxonomic Microarray for Analyzing the Rhizosphere Effects of Maize on <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> spp. and Bacterial Communities.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>4302</fpage>–<lpage>4312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02686-05</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16751545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16751545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B52">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scortichini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Detection and identification methods and new tests as developed and used in the framework of cost 873 for bacteria pathogenic to stone fruits and nuts <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas avellanae</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Plant Pathol.</italic></source>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B53">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Prokka: rapid prokaryotic genome annotation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>2068</fpage>–<lpage>2069</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu153</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24642063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24642063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B54">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaiber</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delmont</surname><given-names>T. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Functional and genetic markers of niche partitioning among enigmatic members of the human oral microbiome.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-020-02195-w</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33323122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33323122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B55">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dineen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Syst. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2011.75</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21988835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21988835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B56">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbaniak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O’hara</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of Various Bacterial Phyla Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>e00214</fpage>–<lpage>e00221</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MRA.00214-21</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 33927037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33927037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B57">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezdan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Checinska Sielaff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswaran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018a</year>). <article-title>Multi-drug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter bugandensis</italic> species isolated from the International Space Station and comparative genomic analyses with human pathogenic strains.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-018-1325-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30466389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30466389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B58">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karouia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswaran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018b</year>). <article-title>Succession and persistence of microbial communities and antimicrobial resistance genes associated with International Space Station environmental surfaces.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiome</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30514368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B59">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Setubal</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrand</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nester</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Genome sequences of three agrobacterium biovars help elucidate the evolution of multichromosome genomes in bacteria.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Bacteriol.</italic></source>
<volume>191</volume>
<fpage>2501</fpage>–<lpage>2511</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01779-08</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19251847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B60">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>C. O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1907</year>). <article-title>A Plant-Tumor of Bacterial Origin.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.25.643.671</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17746161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17746161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B61">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bharadwaj</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O’hara</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Draft Genome Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> Species Isolated from the International Space Station.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol. Resour. Announc.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e00923</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33060271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B62">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>RAxML-III: a fast program for maximum likelihood-based inference of large phylogenetic trees.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti191</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15608047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B63">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinegger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Söding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>MMseqs2 enables sensitive protein sequence searching for the analysis of massive data sets.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>1026</fpage>–<lpage>1028</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3988</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29035372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29035372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B64">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaudequin-Dransart</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poncet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponsonnet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesme</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Novel Ti plasmids in <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> strains isolated from fig tree and chrysanthemum tumors and their opinelike molecules.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol. Plant Microbe Interact.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/mpmi-8-0311</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 7756696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7756696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B65">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuny</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gluchoff-Fiasson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Comte</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oger</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>N-acyl-homoserine lactone-mediated quorum-sensing in <italic toggle="yes">Azospirillum</italic>: an exception rather than a rule.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2006.00153.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17064258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17064258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B66">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weisberg</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabima</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Unexpected conservation and global transmission of agrobacterial virulence plasmids.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>
<volume>368</volume>:<fpage>eaba5256</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aba5256</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 32499412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32499412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B67">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Setubal</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monks</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okura</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The genome of the natural genetic engineer <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> C58.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>
<volume>294</volume>
<fpage>2317</fpage>–<lpage>2323</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1066804</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11743193?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743193</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B68">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A large-scale evaluation of algorithms to calculate average nucleotide identity.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>1281</fpage>–<lpage>1286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28204908</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B69">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuykendall</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martínez-Romero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A revision of <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic> Frank 1889, with an emended description of the genus, and the inclusion of all species of <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic> Conn 1942 and <italic toggle="yes">Allorhizobium undicola</italic> de Lajudie et al. 1998 as new combinations: <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium radiobacter, R. rhizogenes, R. rubi, R. undicola</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. vitis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-51-1-89</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11211278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11211278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
