<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:43:50Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9583651" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9583651</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-10-24</datestamp>
        <setSpec>oxfordopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sleep Adv</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sleep Adv</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sleepadvances</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Sleep Advances</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2632-5012</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9583651</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9583651</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9583651</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36299616</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleepadvances/zpac033</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zpac033</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Festschrift in Honor of David F. Dinges</subject>
                  <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
                    <subject>Review Article</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00370</subject>
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00310</subject>
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00385</subject>
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01870</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Sleep, time, and space—fatigue and performance deficits in pilots, commercial truck drivers, and astronauts</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Maki</surname>
                    <given-names>Katherine A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Translational Biobehavioral and Health Disparities Branch, Clinical Center, National Institutes of Health</institution>, <addr-line>Bethesda, MD, 20814</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9894-6352</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fink</surname>
                    <given-names>Anne M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Biobehavioral Nursing Science, College of Nursing, University of Illinois Chicago</institution>, <addr-line>Chicago, IL, 60612</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
                  <xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <!--afink2@uic.edu-->
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Weaver</surname>
                    <given-names>Terri E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Biobehavioral Nursing Science, College of Nursing, University of Illinois Chicago</institution>, <addr-line>Chicago, IL, 60612</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Biobehavioral Health Sciences, School of Nursing, University of Pennsylvania</institution>, <addr-line>Philadelphia, PA, 19104</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Corresponding author. Anne M. Fink, Department of Biobehavioral Nursing Science, University of Illinois Chicago, 845 South Damen Ave, Room 750, Chicago, IL 60612, USA. Email: <email>afink2@uic.edu</email>.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-09-15">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>3</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <elocation-id>zpac033</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="corrected-typeset">
                  <day>20</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Sleep Research Society.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="zpac033.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <p>Sleep is essential for preventing fatigue in occupations that require sustained vigilance. We conducted a scoping review to synthesize knowledge about sleep, fatigue, and performance in pilots, commercial truck drivers, and astronauts. We found 28 studies where researchers objectively or subjectively measured sleep, fatigue, and performance. The research included laboratory-based (simulator) and field-based studies (i.e. real-world missions and a variety of shift-work schedules). Most researchers used actigraphy to measure sleep, and they found that ~6 hrs of sleep was common. The research also demonstrated how sleep duration and quality were negatively affected by schedule irregularity, early-morning start times, and high-risk missions (e.g. extravehicular activities in space). Collectively, the data demonstrated how shorter sleep durations, short off-duty time, and early-morning start times were associated with slower reaction times, more lapses in attention, and premature responses on psychomotor vigilance tests. Considering that few studies included polysomnography and circadian rhythm biomarkers, there remains limited knowledge about the effects of sleep microstructure and circadian rhythm alterations on performance abilities in these occupations. Future neurobiological and mechanistic discoveries will be important for enhancing vigilance, health, and safety for people working in the skies, on the roads, and in space.</p>
                <p>This paper is part of the David F. Dinges Festschrift Collection. This collection is sponsored by Pulsar Informatics and the Department of Psychiatry in the Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>accidents</kwd>
                <kwd>aviation</kwd>
                <kwd>driving</kwd>
                <kwd>psychomotor vigilance tests</kwd>
                <kwd>occupational health</kwd>
                <kwd>safety</kwd>
                <kwd>shift-work</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>NIH Clinical Center</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000098</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="21"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <boxed-text id="B1" position="float">
              <caption>
                <title>Statement of Significance</title>
              </caption>
              <p>Fatigue can have devastating consequences for people in sleepiness-sensitive occupations, such as pilots, truck drivers, and astronauts. Our scoping review highlights important findings about the variables that affect sleep, fatigue, and vigilance in these occupations in addition to illustrating the importance of developing interventions that could mitigate fatigue. Future research will be important for determining how alterations in circadian rhythms and sleep architecture affect job performance.</p>
            </boxed-text>
            <sec id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Sleep is critical for maintaining physical and psychological health. Adults require ~7 hrs of sleep each day, according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and the Sleep Research Society [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. From an occupational health perspective, fatigue (a biological demand for recuperative rest) threatens safety and job performance [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Many highly publicized accidents have been attributed to fatigue, which underscores the importance of understanding how to promote healthy sleep and workplace/public safety [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Occupational responsibilities may restrict the times people have available to sleep. In the transportation industries, for example, people often work across multiple times zones, which can cause their circadian rhythms to become misaligned with their schedules [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In occupations that require nighttime work, people rely on their abilities to obtain enough daytime sleep, although this is opposed by humans’ natural sleep–wake cycle patterns that favor wakefulness during the daytime and sleep during the night [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4–7</xref>]. Work-related stress and environmental conditions (e.g. uncomfortable sleeping locations, sustained light exposure, and noise) also disrupt sleep and increase the risk for poor performance during work due to fatigue [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
              <p>Airline pilots, commercial truck drivers, and astronauts are examples of occupations that require high-quality sleep for sustained vigilance during work. To perform their jobs effectively, they must endure stressful conditions and combine astute cognitive abilities with technical knowledge to make decisions safely under rapidly changing conditions [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10–19</xref>]. Research has demonstrated how insufficient sleep impairs work-time functioning [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], which ultimately led to regulations that enforced duty restrictions and recommended fatigue-management strategies. Examples include Title 14 of the Code of Federal Regulations, which outlined duty limitations for safer aviation in 2014 [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]; the U.S. Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration’s 2014 revisions to duty time for truck drivers [<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]; and the International Civil Aviation Organization’s 2015 fatigue-management guidelines [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p>
              <p>Safety-focused regulations were driven by the scientific discoveries of Dinges et al. [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], which established a battery of neurobehavioral performance metrics. Dinges and colleagues developed, tested, and validated methods for measuring vigilance and alertness, such as the 10-min Psychomotor Vigilance Test (PVT) [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] 3-min Brief PVT (PVT-B) [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and Cognition Test Battery [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The PVT and PVT-B have been valuable for objectively quantifying responses to randomly timed visual stimuli to improve the rigor of occupational health research (compared with relying on methods that could be confounded by learning effects or subjectivity) [<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Research participants’ subjective descriptions of fatigue, for example, may not be consistently correlated with the objective measurements provided by the PVT.</p>
              <p>In occupations where sleep times are restricted and there is a high-risk for catastrophic accidents, people are highly trained/experienced, but they are not impervious to the adverse effects of attention lapses caused by inadequate sleep. Therefore, it is important for researchers to determine how sleep-related variables affect people’s abilities for safe and effective job performance. Ultimately, the goal will be the development of optimal workplace practices that promote healthy sleep and mitigate the risks for errors and accidents. Previous reviews on this topic have focused on sleep deprivation rather than the occupationally relevant phenomena of short sleep and circadian misalignment [<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref>]. In addition, earlier reviews did not provide information about multiple occupations to allow for comparisons to understand the complex relationships among work schedules, sleep, fatigue, and performance in different settings. Therefore, the purpose of the present paper was to conduct a scoping review to synthesize research findings about objective and subjective measures of sleep, fatigue, and performance from three occupations—pilots, truck drivers, and astronauts.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials" id="s2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>A <italic toggle="yes">scoping review</italic> is a knowledge-synthesizing literature review that is guided by an exploratory question to determine key concepts, types of evidence, and research gaps [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. We conducted our review according to Arksey and O’Malley’s scoping review methodology [<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The following question guided the review: <italic toggle="yes">What is known about sleep, fatigue, and performance in the safety-sensitive occupations involving aviation, truck driving, and space missions?</italic> We chose to examine multiple occupations to determine similarities and differences; this aspect of the scoping review was important for understanding whether findings were occupation-specific or common across professions.</p>
              <p>To identify relevant research studies, we searched MEDLINE/PubMed in August 2022 (excluding papers published before 2014 because several organizations implemented duty restrictions to increase sleep around this time) [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The keywords for the search were “sleep, circadian, fatigue, and performance” in combination with “airline pilots” (retrieved 12 citations), “truck drivers” (retrieved 4 citations), or “astronauts” (retrieved 5 citations). We screened the abstracts to exclude review papers and focus only on original research reports; ultimately, we selected 11 data-based papers about airline pilots (excluded 1 review), 3 about truck drivers (excluded 1 review), and 5 about astronauts. Additional articles were found by handsearching and examining article reference lists (leading to the addition of 6 additional papers about airline pilots and 3 papers about astronauts). A total of 28 research papers were used for the scoping review (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Study characteristics, measures, and key findings</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study citations and aims for the 28 reviewed articles</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size (% women) <break/>
Age (years, mean ± SD)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation, location (field or simulator), and work schedule</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures of sleep, fatigue, and/or performance (objective and subjective)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Circadian rhythm-related findings</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep, fatigue, and performance findings</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Alzehairi <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To screen <break/>
pilots for sleep disorders, fatigue, and depression and determine risk factors</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344 <break/>
(% women not reported) <break/>
40 ± 8</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (Saudi Arabia) <break/>
Duty schedules were defined as day, night, or both <break/>
53% of the pilots were First Officers; 47% were Captains</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> PSQI, Athens Insomnia Scale <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Epworth Sleepiness Scale, Fatigue Severity Scale, VAS <break/>
Depressive symptoms were screened with the Patient Health Questionnaire. The Berlin Questionnaire was use for sleep apnea screening <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep or performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Many pilots had poor-quality sleep (i.e. a third of the sample had PSQI global scores &gt;5). Poor sleep quality, sleepiness, and insomnia were more common in pilots who flew during both days and nights; they had significantly higher PSQI global scores, higher Epworth Sleepiness Scale scores, and more positive answers on the Athens <break/>
Insomnia Index <break/>
Age and experience (years) were negatively associated with PSQI scores (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.83, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001 <break/>
and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.61, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001, respectively) and with positive answers on the Athens Insomnia Severity Index Scale (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.82, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;.001, respectively)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Arsintescu <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine relationships among work load, performance, subjective fatigue, sleep duration, and flight duration</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 <break/>
(8% women) <break/>
33 ± 8</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Specific work schedules were not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold><break/>
Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT (at TOD) <break/>
The NASA Task Load Index was used to measure workload (subjective)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration was 7.7 ± 1.7 hrs <break/>
Sleep duration was positively associated with the NASA Task Load Index scores (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.04, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05) and the mental (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.04, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05) and frustration (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.04, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05) sub-components. Samn-Perelli fatigue scores were positively associated with the effort and performance components of the NASA Task Load Index (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.10, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.10, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01, respectively) <break/>
Mean raw NASA Task Load Index scores were associated with PVT lapses (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.10, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01) and PVT response speed (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.10, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01). Effort and performance (NASA Task Load Index) were positively associated with PVT lapses (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> =.06, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01) and negatively associated with PVT response speed (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01; <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.06, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Arsintescu <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To develop a protocol for 6-sulfatoxy-melatonin analysis (urine) and examine methods for measuring sleep, fatigue, and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 <break/>
(9% women) <break/>
31 ± 7</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/>
Data were compared with a Baseline Block (5 days of mid- morning flights); the subsequent schedule involved four early flights (0500), four high-workload mid-day flights (1030), and four late flights (1600) that landed after midnight. Pilots were studied for 34 days</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Circadian (objective):</bold><break/>
Urinary 6-sulfatoxymelatonin levels <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold><break/>
Samn-Perelli Scale; Epworth Sleepiness Scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The circadian phase (determined by urinary 6-sulfatoxy-melatonin levels) was affected by pilots’ start times</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration decreased before early-morning take-offs compared with mid-day flights (7.4 ± 0.9 hrs versus 8.2 ± 0.9 hrs <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01). The mean PSQI scores did not differ according to start times <break/>
Samn-Perelli scale scores for early (4.0 ± 0.9, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), mid-day (3.9 ± 0.9, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) and late starts (3.9 ± 0.9, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) revealed how each of these times were associated with more fatigue than mid-morning start times (3.5 ± 0.8) <break/>
The PVT mean RT was significantly slower, and mean number of lapses was significantly higher for early, mid-day, and late start times (compared with the baseline period of mid-morning start times)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Barger <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To characterize sleep and hypnotic use during short and long missions and determine how chronic sleep-restriction affected performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 <break/>
(16%women) <break/>
46 ± 4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Astronauts</italic></bold><break/><bold>Laboratory</bold> (Earth/United States within the 3 months before launch and for 1 week after the space mission) and <break/><bold>Field</bold> (Space [for 1 to 30 weeks])</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep and Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Diaries, VAS for sleep quality and alertness <break/>
Subjects also completed medication logs <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration 5.9 ± 0.6 hrs on the Space Transportation System. Astronauts assigned to the ISS demonstrated a reduction in sleep time 3 months and 11 days pre-flight; sleep was shortest while in space (5.9 ± 0.9 hrs, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001compared with post-mission sleep) <break/>
Sleep duration declined significantly after the first week of the mission. In space, 78% of crew members used hypnotics to sleep (versus 27% in the 3 months before launch, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001) <break/>
Astronauts slept &lt;6 hrs on 51% of nights before EVAs. Average total sleep time was shortest before EVAs (5.9 ± 1.0 hrs) and sleep quality was rated poorly (62 ± 18 on a VAS scale of 0 to 100) <break/>
The VAS ratings for sleep quality were higher after landing compared with ratings obtained during shuttle missions (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001), along with3 months (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .024), and 11 days (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .003) before spaceflight. The VAS ratings for alertness were higher in the first 7 days after landing compared with the VAS values during shuttle missions (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001) and 11 days before spaceflight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .033). Subjective sleep quality was significantly higher in the first 7 days after landing compared with the in-flight periods (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001) and during preparations before spaceflight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .003)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Flynn-Evans <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine how PVT and fatigue ratings changed during a simulated mission and to evaluate bio-mathematical predictive models</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 <break/>
(6% women) <break/>
39 ± 8</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy volunteers recruited to simulate<bold><italic toggle="yes">astronauts’</italic></bold> activities <break/><bold>Laboratory</bold><break/>
(United States) Observational study with a stimulated 45-day space mission <break/>
Rest schedules allowed for 5 hrs of sleep during weekdays (0200–0700) and 8 hrs of sleep on weekends (1100–0700; 2 nights)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold><break/>
Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Samn-Perelli scale scores did not change significantly during the study, but the fatigue scores were significantly greater after 5 hrs of sleep versus 8 hrs of sleep (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). <break/>
Subjects’ performance on the PVT worsened from the beginning to the end of workdays (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .048) when the data were averaged across all study days. <break/>
Compared with weekends (after an 8-h sleep opportunity) the following PVT measures were slower on weekdays (5-h sleep opportunity): RT, fastest 10% RT, slowest 10% RT, and response speed. In addition, the average number of lapses was higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01 for all comparisons) <break/>
Bio-mathematical models were used to predict PVT performance based on Samn-Perelli fatigue ratings. Four models were able to predict relative changes in performance according to the day of the mission and by session of the day but were less accurate at capturing differences in PVT performance in the days following the 5 hrs of sleep condition</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Flynn-Evans <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine how work start time affected 6-sulfatoxymelatonin levels, sleep duration and timing, fatigue, and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 <break/>
(9% women) <break/>
31 ± 7</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/>
Baseline duty time was mid-morning (start time 1030); compared with early (0530 start), high-workload mid-day (1400) and late (1630)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diaries <break/><bold>Circadian (objective):</bold> Urinary 6-sulfatoxymelatonin levels <break/><bold>Circadian (subjective):</bold> Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The mean circadian phase of the 6-sulfatoxymelatonin levels was shifted earlier when pilots had early take-offs (compared with the mid-morning take-offs during the baseline period; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .004). No phase shift was associated with mid-day and late flights compared with baseline (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .67and .30, respectively)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilots slept 5.7 ± 0.7 hrs on the night before an early-take-off (compared with 6.8 ± 0.9 hrs before later flights, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01). The WASO was longer before earlier flights than mid-morning flights (54 ± 37 versus 45 ± 30 min, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05) <break/>
When pilots slept during different times of day, they did not rate the quality of their sleep differently. Sleep diary data revealed that pilots overestimated their total sleep duration (as compared with actigraphy-derived sleep measures) <break/>
Mean PVT RT was significantly slower for the early, mid-day and late start times compared with baseline (i.e. mid-morning start time). Comparisons of mean PVT lapses, RT, and response speed were not significantly different between mid-morning take-offs and pilots’ off-duty days</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Flynn-Evans <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To define circadian misalignment in space and determine how sleep was associated with mission-critical events</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 <break/>
(29% women) <break/>
47 ± 4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Astronauts</italic></bold><break/><bold>Field</bold> (Space) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Work and sleep times were not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective)</bold>: Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diaries (e.g. number of awakenings were documented), VAS rating of sleep quality (ranging from 0 to 100) <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> VAS ratings of alertness (ranging from 0 to 100) <break/><bold>Circadian (objective):</bold> Temperature (Circadian Performance Simulation Software) <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The circadian temperature rhythm did not align with 13% of astronauts’ sleep episodes pre-flight. In-flight, 19% of the sleep episodes were not optimally aligned with the circadian temperature rhythm <break/>
Pre-flight, astronauts slept significantly longer when their circadian temperature rhythm was aligned with their sleep timing (6.0 ± 1.2 hrs), compared with when it was misaligned (5.5 ± 1.8 hrs; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .002). In-flight, sleep was also significantly longer when aligned with the temperature circadian rhythm (6.4 ± 1.2 hrs) compared with circadian misaligned sleep (5.4 ± 1.4 hrs; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001) <break/>
Sleep quality ratings were higher (66.8 ± 17.7) when the circadian temperature rhythms were aligned with astronauts’ sleep timing (misaligned = 60.2 ± 21.1; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .01). Alertness ratings, however, were not different depending on whether sleep timing was aligned with the circadian rhythm (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .130)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep durations were 5.9 ± 0.9 hrs pre-flight and 6.1 ± 0.7 hrs in-flight (according to actigraphy) <break/>
According to sleep diaries, sleep durations did not differ between the pre-flight (6.3 ± 0.8 hrs) and in-flight periods (6.5 ± 0.7 hrs). Sleep quality measures were also similar (pre-flight, 62.3 ± 15.6; in-flight, 66.5 ± 13.4). Astronauts‘ alertness rating did not differ pre-flight versus in-flight (56.0 ± 19.5 pre-flight and 57.7 ± 18.7 during space flight</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Gander <break/>
et al. [<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To examine the effect of multiple trans-meridian flights and in-flight sleep duration on performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 <break/>
(0% women) <break/>
55</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States [East Coast or Hawaii] to Japan) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Flight from the East Coast departed at 1400 hrs or 0230 hrs, and they arrived in Hawaii at 0345 or 1500 hrs. Flight departed Hawaii at 1700 hrs and arrived in Japan at 1700 hrs. Flights departed Japan at 1700 or 0800 hrs and arrived in the United States at 0330 hrs or 1530 hrs</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective)</bold>: Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diaries <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In-flight sleep duration was ~3 hrs on flights travelling from the East coast to Japan; the relief crew for landing obtained 2.3 hrs of in-flight sleep <break/>
After a long-haul flight leg, pilots obtained significantly more sleep on post-trip day one compared to baseline (estimated mean sleep extension = 49 min, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .008). From post-trip day two onwards, total sleep time per 24 hrs was not significantly different from baseline <break/>
Total sleep time (in the prior 24 hrs) predicted KSS scores at TOD. In flights from Japan to the East Coast (United States of America), total sleep time in the prior 24 hrs was associated with mean RT and slowest 10% RT (at TOD). In the Japan to East Coast flight pattern, there was a main effect of total time awake on the slowest 10% RT</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. Gander et al. [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To combine sleep/wake history data from four studies of long-range and ultra-long-range flights to test association with fatigue and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 <break/>
(% women not reported) <break/>
43 (median, range 27–63)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (around the world) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Departure time was categorized in 4-hr bins: 0200–0559, 1000–1359, 1400–1759, 1800–2159, and 2200–0159</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective)</bold>: Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective)</bold>: Diaries <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective)</bold>: KSS, Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance</bold>: PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The median sleep duration prior to duty was 7.0 hrs (range 2.2–13.8 hrs). Median total sleep time in-flight was 3.7 hrs (range 0.2–6.3 hrs). Median total sleep time in the 24 hrs prior to TOD was 4.8 hrs (range 0.2–11.5 hrs) <break/>
For every 1-hr increase in sleep duration, the pre-flight KSS ratings and Samn-Perelli fatigue ratings decreased significantly. The duration of time awake at duty start was not associated with KSS or Samn-Perelli scores. Total sleep time in the 24 hrs before duty was associated with an increase in PVT response speed. The duration of time awake (at duty start) was not associated with PVT response speed <break/>
At TOD, time awake was associated with an increase in KSS and Samn-Perelli scores. Total sleep time (in the 24 hrs prior) was not associated with TOD KSS or Samn-Perelli scores. Total in-flight sleep was associated with a decrease in KSS and Samn-Perelli scores (TOD). Total sleep time in the prior 24 hrs was not associated with the slowest 10% RT on the PVT (TOD). The median KSS rating (pre-flight) was 3 (range 1–8) and at TOD was 3 (range 1–9). Median Samn Perelli rating (pre-flight) was 2 (range 1–6) and at TOD was 3 (range 1–7)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><break/>
Pilots’ KSS scores (pre-flight) were lower when flights departed between 1400 and 1759 hrs (compared with departures occurring between 2200 and 0159 hrs, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .003, or between 0200 and 0559 hrs, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001). The Samn-Perelli fatigue scores (pre-flight) were lower for departures between 1400 and 1759 (compared with departures occurring between 2200 and 0159 hrs, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0003, or 0200 and 0559 hrs <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0004). The KSS and Samn-Perelli scores were higher (at TOD) when flights arrived between 0600 and 0959 hrs compared with later landing times <break/>
Pre-flight PVT response speeds and flight departure time post hoc analyses were not significant after correcting for multiple comparisons <break/>
The mean PVT response speed and the slowest 10% of PVT responses were significantly faster at TOD for flights arriving between 1400–1759 hrs versus flights arriving earlier in the day <break/>
Median PVT response speed pre-flight was 4.27 (range 1.81–5.49) and at TOD was 4.00 (range 2.11–5.41). Median slowest 10% of PVT response speed pre-flight was 2.82 (range 0.37–4.45) and at TOD was 2.55 (range 0.38–4.48)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10. Gander et al. [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine the effects of departure and arrival times on fatigue and performance using combined analyses of data about long-range and ultra-long-range flights</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 <break/>
(% women not reported) <break/>
43 (median; range 27–63)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (Around the world) <break/>
Flight departure times and arrival times were categorized in 4-hr bins according to the following clock hours: 0200–0559, 0600–0959, 1000–1359, 1400–1759, 1800–2159, 2200–0159</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective)</bold>: Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective)</bold>: Diaries <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance</bold>: PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Pilots obtained more in-flight sleep on flights departing 1800–2159 and 2200–0159 versus 0200–0559 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0036; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0169), 1000–1359 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0001; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0010), or 1400–1759 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0001; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0001) <break/>
Pilots were less fatigued before flights departing 1400–1759 and 1800–2159 versus 2200–0159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0021; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0315), or 0200–0559 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0013; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0270). At TOD, pilots had higher KSS and Samn-Perelli ratings on flights arriving 0600–0959 versus 1000–1359 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0005; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> =.0347) <break/>
Flight departure time impacted KSS and Samn-Perelli ratings (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0002 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001). Pilots were less sleepy before flights departing 1400–1759 versus 2200–0159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0204) or 0200–0559 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .0032). Flight departure time did not impact pre-flight PVT metrics. At TOD, mean RT was slower on flights arriving 0200-0959 versus arriving 1400–1759 (0200–0559, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .003; 0600–0959, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .004). Mean RT was also significantly slower at TOD on flights arriving 0600–0959 than on flights arriving 1400–1759 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .004)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11. Ganesan et al. [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To examine the impact of one versus two consecutive nights of work on fatigue and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 <break/>
(28% women) <break/>
33.4 ± 10.1</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Truck drivers</italic></bold><break/><bold>Field</bold> (Australia) <break/>
Working 12-hr night-shifts in a coal mine in Australia (data were collected over 2 consecutive night-shifts) <break/>
All participants worked day shifts followed by a minimum of 2 days off work</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective)</bold>: Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective)</bold>: Diaries; PSQI <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Epworth Sleepiness Scale <break/><bold>Performance:</bold> PVT; driving</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration differed before the first and second work nights (9.1 ± 1.5 versus 5.4 ± 1.2, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01). There were increased KSS scores at the end of both shifts (effect of time; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001) <break/>
PVT lapses and the slowest 10% of RT were similar at the start and end of the first night of work. Greater impairments in performance occurred at the end of the second night of work (versus night one; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05). There was also a significant shift in the time interaction observed on drive violations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .05). Total sleep time in the 48 hrs prior to the start of shifts significantly impacted performance during night shift-work (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12. Gregory et al. [<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To measure the impact of sleep duration and quality (from in-flight rest breaks) on fatigue</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 <break/>
(% women not reported) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Age not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Time of day during in-flight rest breaks categorized into 4-hr bins: 0200–0600, 0600–1000, 1000–1400, 1400–1800, 1800–2200, 2200–0200 hrs</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Self-reported in-flight sleep and quality (1 = very good; 5 = very poor) and duration <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS, Samn-Perelli scale <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep or performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Only in-flight sleep duration was reported (1.5 ± 0.7 hrs from clock time 0600–1000, 1.2 ± 0.7 hrs from 1400–1800, and 1.4 ± 0.7 hrs from 2200 to 0600) <break/>
Samn-Perelli ratings (at break start) during the night-time (from 0200–0600 hrs) were higher versus the afternoon and early evening. Samn-Perelli ratings during the early evening (1800–2200 hrs) were lower than earlier (0600–1400 hrs) and later (2200-0200 hrs). KSS ratings at break start during the night-time and early-morning (2200–1000 hrs) were higher than those during the afternoon and early evening (1400–2200hrs). Samn-Perelli ratings at TOD during the night-time (0200–0600 hrs) were significantly higher than those obtained during the mid-day (1000–1400 hrs). The KSS ratings at TOD did not differ significantly by time</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13. Gregory et al. [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim:</bold> To examine scheduling practices (over 1 year) and test a fatigue prediction model</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 <break/>
(% women not report) <break/>
≥ 30</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Airline pilots</bold><break/>
(maritime) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/>
Work periods lasted 7.6 hrs on average (pilots had ≤ 4 ship assignments per work period). Work weeks were 35 hrs on average (usually for 3 consecutive days). Night work typically started at 0200 hrs</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fatigue:</bold> The Sleep, Activity, Fatigue, and Task Effectiveness-Fatigue Avoidance Scheduling Tool <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep, subjective measure of fatigue, or objective measures of performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over half of the work periods were assigned high predicted fatigue scores. Higher predicted fatigue was associated with duty starting between 0000 and 0400 hrs. Variability in start times and busy assignments were also associated with higher predicted fatigue scores</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14. Honn et al. [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To examine the impact of multiple flights during the day versus one flight on fatigue and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 <break/>
(8% women) <break/>
33 (range 24–49)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/><bold>Laboratory</bold> (flight simulator) <break/>
Duty periods lasted from 0515 to 1415 hrs. Pilots flew in the stimulator for 2 consecutive days. A randomized cross-over design was used so that pilots had multiple flights one day and flow on flights the other day</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diary <break/><bold>Fatigue (objective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli Fatigue Scale <break/><bold>Performance:</bold> PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The night before the first simulated flight, pilots slept 5.6 ± 1.1 hrs. Before the second day, they slept 6.4 ± 1.2 hrs <break/>
There were significant reductions in Samn-Perelli (by 0.5 ± 0.1) and KSS scores (by 0.4 ± 0.1) for every additional hour of sleep pilots obtained before flying. Prior sleep duration was negatively associated with scores on the Samn-Perelli scale (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) and KSS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). Samn-Perelli and KSS scores were highly correlated over subjects and across test bouts (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). PVT lapses and mean RT were highly correlated over subjects and across test bouts (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.67, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). There was an increase in Samn-Perelli and KSS scores throughout the day over the test bouts regardless of the multi-flight or single segment condition. The number of PVT false starts was negatively associated with the prior night’s sleep duration (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15. Jones e al. [<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To evaluate the impact of spaceflight on sleep–wake activities, workload, stress, fatigue, and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 <break/>
(21% women) <break/>
48 ± 5</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Astronauts</italic></bold><break/><bold>Field</bold> (Space) <break/>
Astronauts on-duty other than scheduled sleep time (2130–0600)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Dairy logging daily sleep–wake schedule; VAS for sleep quality (11-point scale) <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> VAS (11-point scale) for workload, stress, mental fatigue, physical exhaustion, tiredness, and sleepiness <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> Reaction Self-Test using the PVT-B <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astronauts reported an average nightly sleep duration of 6.5 ± 1.4 hrs in-flight in space and only slept the NASA scheduled 8.5-hr sleep opportunity on 6% of nights <break/>
Sleep time ≤6 hrs/night occurred 40% of the time on weekdays versus 23% of the time on weekends. Astronauts did not report changes in their WASO or changes in sleep efficiency while on the ISS <break/>
Sleep durations &lt;7 hrs/night were associated with poorer ratings of sleep quality, and &gt;9 hrs of sleep was associated with more optimal ratings of sleep quality. Their VAS ratings of sleepiness, tiredness, mental fatigue were higher after ≤4, 4–5, and 5–6 hrs of sleep (versus 7–8 hrs) <break/>
Sleep duration was positively associated with the mean RT on the PVT-B. Total sleep time &gt;9 hrs was associated with faster RT relative to all groups with total sleep time ≤7 hrs</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16. Koller et al. [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To characterize slow-wave density, spectral band-power, duration, and slope using EEG sleep data that were collected before, during, and after two Space Shuttle missions</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 <break/><italic toggle="yes">Sex and age not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Astronauts</bold><break/><bold>Field</bold> (Space) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Sleep and work schedules were not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> EEG <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of fatigue or performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
The sleep period time was 42.0 ± 7.9 min shorter in-flight compared to pre-flight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001) and 34.3 ± 9.9 min shorter compared to post-flight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .013). Total sleep time was significantly reduced by 48.2 ± 16.0 min in-flight compared to pre-flight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .029). The duration of sleep stages and WASO did not differ pre-flight versus in-flight versus post-flight. Slow spindle frequency was significantly affected by pre-flight versus in-flight versus post-flight condition (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01). There was a slow spindle shift towards higher frequencies by 0.17 ± 0.03 Hz in-flight compared to pre-flight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). The spindle frequency increased by 0.27 ± 0.06 Hz in-flight compared to pre-flight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). Slow-wave amplitude decreased by 2.53 ± 0.70 μV in-flight compared to pre-flight (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .011). Slow-wave duration or band-power were not affected by flight condition (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .54)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17. Mollicone et al. [<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To predict fatigue from sleep/wake patterns using a bio-mathematical fatigue model examine relationships between predicted fatigue levels and hard-braking events</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 <break/>
(6% women) <break/>
45 ± 11</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Truck drivers</italic></bold><break/><bold>Laboratory</bold> (United States) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Schedules were not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective)</bold>: Actigraphy <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT; hard-braking events</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Of the total hrs truck drivers were driving, 50% were associated with predicted fatigue scores ≥5.9 (median); 5% were associated with predicted fatigue scores ≥12.8, 1% were associated with predicted fatigue scores &gt;16.5 <break/>
The frequency of hard-braking events increased as predicted fatigue levels worsened, after controlling for time of day (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .018). Of the hard-breaking events, 58% were associated with predicted fatigue (derived from sleep/wake by actigraphy) ≥5.9; each 1-unit increment on the fatigue scale (equivalent to 1 lapse on the PVT) increased the frequency of hard-braking events by 7.8%</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18. Moore et al. [<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine the impact of long-duration spaceflight and microgravity on post-landing motor vehicle operator proficiency</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Tested before and after 142–200 days on the ISS <break/>
(0% women) <break/>
48 ± 7 <break/>
12 Controls (ground-based healthy subjects; 0% women) <break/>
39 ± 10 <break/>
12 (sleep-restriction group) <break/>
40 ± 11 <break/>
(44% women)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Astronauts</italic></bold><break/><bold>Laboratory</bold> (United States)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Stanford Sleepiness Scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> Cognitive/sensorimotor test battery <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upon returning from the ISS, astronauts demonstrated significant deficits in manual dexterity, dual-tasking, motion perception, and the ability to operate a motor vehicle. Astronauts post-flight motor functions recovered (returned to baseline) 4 days after landing</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19. Morris et al. [<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine relationships among pilot’s perceptions of fatigue, circadian preferences, fatigue mitigation strategies, and performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 <break/>
(14% women) <break/>
29 ± 2</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(Cargo; Air Force) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Schedules were not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy (but data were not reported) <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Fatigue perceptions (five items ranging from 1 = strongly agree and 5 = strongly disagree); five fatigue mitigation strategies (responding never, sometimes, half of the time, most of the time, and always) <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT (but data were not reported)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Pilot perceptions of fatigue as a serious safety of flight concern was positively associated with personal concerns of fatigue (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.67, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01), and the perception that changes are needed to address pilot fatigue (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.55, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; . 05). The perception that changes are needed to address pilot fatigue was positively associated with personal concerns of fatigue (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.57, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01), and pilots reported feeling pressured to continue a mission despite fatigue (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.60, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01) <break/>
In this sample, 5% of pilots a had a “moderate evening” chronotype, 29% were “intermediate evening”, 33% were “intermediate morning”, and 33% were “moderate morning”. In addition, 67% of pilots responded, “strongly agree” to the question: “Fatigue is a serious safety of flight concern for the air mobility community”. 38% of pilots responded, “strongly agree” and 38% of pilots responded “agree” to the question: “I have personally felt concerned about my fatigue level with respect to safety of flight”</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20. Nasrini et al. [<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To evaluate fatigue and performance after sleep-restriction</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 <break/>
(53% women) <break/>
36 ± 8</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Astronauts</italic></bold><break/><bold>Laboratory</bold> (spaceflight mission simulator) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Astronauts on-duty other than scheduled sleep time (2300–0700). In campaign 1, participants underwent one-night of sleep-restriction (scheduled sleep time 0300–0700). In campaign 2 participants underwent one-night of sleep deprivation (no scheduled sleep time)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective)</bold>: Time in bed; Perceived sleep quality (Campaign 2 only) <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective)</bold>: Perceived alertness; Perceived workload, sleepiness, happiness, sickness, physical exhaustion, mental fatigue, stress, depression, boredom, loneliness, monotony, and crewmember conflicts (campaign 2 only) <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> Cognition test battery and PVT <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Over time (excluding sleep deprivation days), there were decreasing ratings of poor sleep quality in campaign 2. In general, subjects reported high sleep quality. Subjects were more likely to report tiredness during sleep deprivation in both campaigns. In campaign 2 there was a significant effect of sleep deprivation on subjects reporting increased workload, sleepiness, physical exhaustion, and mental fatigue <break/>
Accuracy on the PVT increased significantly over time in mission (excluding sleep deprivation days). Reduced sleep impaired PVT response speed and accuracy was lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21. Powell et al. [<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To evaluate a bio-mathematical model to predict fatigue</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324 (53% female) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Age not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long and short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (New Zealand and Australia) <break/>
Data analyzed from 11 studies across both day and night duty periods</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diary (documenting in-flight sleep periods and sleeping locations) <break/><bold>Fatigue (objective):</bold> Pilot Alertness Test <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli fatigue scale; VAS for fatigue and drowsiness; System for Aircrew Fatigue Evaluation (SAFE) model for predicting fatigue levels from in-flight sleep and duty information <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> Pilot Alertness Test <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Predicted fatigue values from the SAFE model were positively associated with VAS scores (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.85). Predicted fatigue values were positively associated with RT on the Pilot Alertness Test (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.57). The SAFE model overestimated fatigue during the morning and underestimated fatigue during the evening. A similar trend was noted for over- and under-estimation of the RT during the morning and evening (not statistically significant). Subjective fatigue (VAS) was positively associated with the RT determined by the Pilot Alertness Test (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.74)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22. Sallinen et al. [<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To examine aircrew fatigue during night duty shifts</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">392 (24% women) <break/>
Mean age not reported</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long and short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (European Union) <break/>
Day and night duty periods were analyzed. The analysis focused on high-risk schedules: night work &gt;10 hrs and disruptive schedules (i.e. early-starts, late finishes, and nights)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> PVT-B</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms</italic>
                        <break/>
                        <italic toggle="yes">were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-duty napping occurred during long night duty periods (pilots: 31%, cabin crew: 20%) and short night duty (pilots: 11%, cabin crew: 8%) of employees. Prior sleep duration was a main predictor of high fatigue levels. The probability of high fatigue (KSS ≥7 at TOD) was 0.41 and 0.32 during long (&gt;10 hr) and short (&lt;10 hr) night duty periods. Start time was a significant predictor of fatigue levels. When the duty period occurred between 0200 and 0559 hrs, higher fatigue levels were more likely</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23. Sallinen et al. [<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine levels and predictors of fatigue at TOD and determine the in-flight sleep/wake ratio according to the ‘window of circadian low’</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">519 <break/>
(18%women) <break/>
38 ± 9</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long and short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (European Union) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Analysis focused on high-risk schedules: &gt;10 on-duty hrs at night and schedules that are considered disruptive of circadian rhythm (early-starts = duty period start time between 0500 and 0659 hrs; late finishes = duty period end time between 2300 and 0159 hrs; FDPs during the window of circadian low between 0200 and 0459 hrs)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diary; Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli scale <break/><bold>Performance:</bold>PVT (pilots only)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-duty napping occurred in 5% of early-starts (pilots: 8%, cabin crew: 1%), 11% of late finishes (pilots: 12%, cabin crew: 8%), and 15% of night FDPs (pilots: 16%, cabin crew: 13%) <break/>
High KSS scores at TOD were more likely during night-shifts (both long and short flights). Point estimates for high KSS scores were higher for both types of shifts with consecutive late finishes or night-shifts. Start time, end time, number of time zones crossed, and number of shifts during the ‘window of circadian low’ were significant predictors of high KSS scores at TOD <break/>
The mean KSS score at TOD was 5.4 for both long and short nights. The odds ratio for high fatigue (KSS) at TOD was 2.0 during early-starts (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .026), 3.8 during late finishes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), and 3.0 during nights (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001; compared with daytime as a reference). Longer time awake at TOD was associated with increased odds of reporting high KSS scores (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). More hrs of sleep in the previous 24 hrs were associated with lower odds of reporting high KSS scores at TOD (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24. Sparrow et al. [<xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine how restart breaks affected sleep, fatigue, and performance in daytime and night-time drivers</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 <break/>
(6% women) <break/>
45 ± 11</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Truck drivers</italic></bold><break/><bold>Field</bold> (United States) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Time of day (hr) was used in statistic models</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective)</bold>: KSS <break/><bold>Performance:</bold> PVT, driving activity</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before restart breaks, drivers slept a mean of 6.0 ± 0.2 hrs per 24 hrs before the one-night restart condition, and 6.2 ± 0.1 hrs in the &gt; one-night restart group. The one-night restart group slept an average of 8.8 ± 0.3 hrs per 24 hrs during the restart break and the &gt; one-night restart group slept an average of 8.9 ± 0.2 hrs <break/>
The KSS scores were higher in the one-night restart condition. The 24-hr patterns of lane deviation in the two conditions were consistent with the 24-hr patterns observed for the PVT-B. On PVT-B, drivers exhibited 2.0 ± 0.3 lapses of attention during duty cycles preceded by the one-night restart condition, and 1.7 ± 0.3 lapses of attention per PVT-B assessment during duty cycles preceded by the &gt; one-night restart condition (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .015) <break/>
There was a significant interaction of condition (one-night versus &gt; one-night restart group) and hour of the day for sleep obtained during both duty time and the restart break. The one-night restart group obtained more of their sleep during daytime hrs, while the &gt; one-night restart group obtained more sleep at night <break/>
In the one-night restart group, KSS scales were significantly higher during daytime periods. There was a significant effect of both condition and time of day on PVT lapses. There was a significant interaction of condition by hour in the number of lane deviations. Lane deviations in the one-night restart group were higher during 0400–0500, 0800–0900, and 1500–1600 hrs. Lane deviations were higher in the &gt;1-night restart group during 1900–2000 hrs</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25. van den Berg et al. [<xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] <break/>
Aim: To determine how in-flight sleep and time of day affect fatigue</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">298 <break/><italic toggle="yes">Sex and age not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (New Zealand) <break/>
Day and night duty periods analyzed. Time of day during in-flight rest breaks and arrival times categorized into 4-hr bins: 0200–0559, 0600–959, 1000–1359, 1400–1759, 1800–2159, 2200–0159</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diary; sleep quality on 7-point scale where 1 = extremely good and 7 = extremely poor <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli scale, Crew Status Check <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep or performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
Fewer pilots attempted to nap from 1800 to 2159 compared with 2200–0159 and 0200–0559. Pilots obtained more sleep during breaks starting 0200–0559 versus breaks starting 0600–0959 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001), 1000–1359 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .004), and 1800–2159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001). Sleep quality was rated as significantly better for breaks starting 0200–0559 than for breaks starting 1800–2159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001) and 2200–0159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .032) <break/>
Pilots reported higher KSS scores (at TOD) on flights arriving 0200–0559 than on flights arriving 1000–1359 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001), 1400–1759 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001), and 2200–0159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001). Pilots also reported higher KSS scores at TOD on flights arriving 0600–0959 than on flights arriving between 1000–1359 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001), 1400–1759 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001), and 2200–0159 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001) <break/>
With every 1-hr increase in sleep duration in-flight, KSS sleepiness ratings decreased by 0.6 points and Samn-Perelli fatigue ratings decreased by 0.4 points. Most pilots surveyed attempted sleep during their scheduled rest break. Samn-Perelli fatigue ratings had the same relationships with arrival times as KSS scores at TOD</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26. Vejvoda et al. [<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To compare fatigue levels upon landing for late and early flights</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 <break/>
(0% female) <break/>
32 ± 6</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(short-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (Germany) <break/>
Early starting duty periods (0500–0659) were compared to late-finishing duty periods (0000–0159)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diaries <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> KSS; Samn-Perelli scale; Crew Status Check <break/>
The NASA Task Load index was used to measure workload complexity <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The duration of the preceding night sleep time (which averaged 6.5 hrs in early starters and 7.6 hrs in late finishers, respectively) had no significant effect on fatigue (Samn-Perelli) at end of shift <break/>
Pilots were significantly more fatigued when they started working in the afternoon or evening, compared with the morning (Samn-Perelli scale scores obtained at the end of duty) <break/>
A comparison of early-starts and late-landings showed that pilots’ fatigue was higher for the latter condition (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), reaching moderate to severe levels, even though the prior sleep period time was longer by 1.1 hrs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) and duty duration was shorter by 0.7 hrs (8.6 versus 9.3 hrs, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .047) <break/>
Fatigue and sleepiness increased in the late evening hrs, which were paralleled by longer time awake. Fatigue reached critical values after 2200 hrs. Fatigue was lower in the morning despite shorter previous night sleep period time. Time awake at start of shift was a main predictor Samn-Perelli scale scores (at shift end).Sleep period time before a shift had no significant effect on fatigue</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27. Wong et al. [<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To determine how 28-hrs of sleep deprivation affected ROBoT metrics(e.g.% of successful captures, alignment-reversal score, and efficiency to capture)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 <break/>
(44%women) <break/>
32 ± 10</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy volunteers recruited to simulate<bold><italic toggle="yes">astronauts’</italic></bold> activities <break/><bold>Laboratory</bold> (NASA; spaceflight mission simulator for 28-hrs) <break/>
Participants were studied during the day and night</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (objective):</bold> Actigraphy (before sleep deprivation) <break/><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> PSQI (global PSQI scores &lt; 5 were required for study participation) <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Fatigue Severity Index (scores &lt; 36 were required for study participation); KSS <break/><bold>Circadian Preference (subjective):</bold> Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire (scores &lt; 58 or &gt; 42 were required for study participation) <break/><bold>Performance (objective):</bold> ROBoT; PVT</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before the sleep deprivation period, subjects obtained 8.1 ± 0.5 hrs of sleep (PSQI global score = 2.8 ± 1.6) <break/>
Subjects demonstrated improved performance (learning effects) over time despite sleep loss. Participants improved from the second to the last training session in the alignment-reversal score (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), efficiency to capture (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .004), and percentage of successful captures (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .01). When skills were separated by difficulty, there was an improvement in the medium-easy and hard trials with increased time awake, but not other levels of difficulty. There was a significant change in several components of PVT with increased time awake including: decreased mean 1/RT (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), decrease in slowest 10% RT (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), increase in the fastest 10% RT (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), and an increase in number of lapses (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). No ROBoT performance metrics had significant correlations with PVT scores. Subjects’ KSS scores were correlated with the % of successful captures (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.24, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05) but not with any other ROBoT metrics</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28. Zaslona et al. [<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] <break/><bold>Aim</bold>: To qualitatively analyze pilots’ experiences with in-flight sleep and their efforts to mitigate fatigue</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 <break/>
(% women not reported) <break/><italic toggle="yes">Age not reported</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Airline pilots</italic></bold><break/>
(long-haul) <break/><bold>Field</bold> (New Zealand) <break/>
Data from pilots working long-range and ultra-long-range flights across day and night duty periods</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep (subjective):</bold> Diaries <break/><bold>Fatigue (subjective):</bold> Open-ended questions about in-flight fatigue mitigation strategies <break/><italic toggle="yes">No objective measures of sleep or performance were examined</italic></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">Circadian rhythms were not examined</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep duration was not reported</italic><break/>
The designs/locations of the aircrafts’ rest facilities affected pilots’ perceptions of sleep quality, fatigue, and alertness. Uncertainty about the scheduling of breaks/naps disrupted pilots’ in-flight rest, especially for junior pilots. Pilots experienced enhanced sleep quality (and improved alertness) when the timing of their in-flight naps were aligned with their perceived circadian rhythms. Pilots attempted to adjust the timing of their sleep when they knew their flight schedules in advance</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T1Fn1">
                    <p>Data are mean ± standard deviation (unless noted otherwise).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1Fn2">
                    <p>EEG, Electroencephalogram; ISS, International Space Station; KSS, Karolinska Sleepiness Scale (scores range from 1 [extremely alert] to 9 [extremely sleepy]); MEQ, Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire (scores 70–86 [morning type], 59–69 [moderately-morning], 42–58 [neither type], 31–41 [moderately evening-type]), 16–30 [evening-type]); PSQI, Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index (scores range 0–21 [scores &gt;5 indicate poorer sleep quality]); PVT, psychomotor vigilance task; ROBoT, robotics on-board trainer; RT, reaction time; TOD, top of descent; VAS: Visual Analog Scale.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>The research about pilots [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40–42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47–49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51–53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60–62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], truck drivers [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and astronauts [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] included laboratory studies (e.g. conducted in stimulators) [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] and field investigations (where data acquisition occurred during normal occupational activities) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40–42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45–52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60–65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Most pilots were employed by commercial airlines (to transport passengers) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40–42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47–49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60–62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] with the exception of studies about maritime piloting (to guide ships) [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and military transport operations [<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Two papers about truck drivers utilized the same group of drivers (who had irregular start times) [<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]; another sample of truck drivers worked rotating day- and night-shifts with predictable start times [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Data were also provided by astronauts assigned to the International Space Station (ISS) [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and Space Transportation System [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] as well as healthy volunteers who participated in simulated missions [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The key findings across studies were organized to reflect the following themes: (1) sleep characteristics; (2) fatigue during work, (3) schedules and circadian rhythms; and (4) variables affecting performance.</p>
              <sec id="s4">
                <title>Sleep characteristics</title>
                <p>Sleep was measured objectively in space [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and on Earth [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41–43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45–50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61–63</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In addition to actigraphy [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41–43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45–50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61–63</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], subjects completed sleep diaries [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45–50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], and questionnaires, such as the Pittsburgh Sleep Quantity Index (PSQI) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] and Athens Insomnia Scale [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Polysomnography was utilized in one study for a quantitative analysis of the cortical electroencephalogram (EEG) in astronauts before, during, and after a space mission [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Subjects’ sleeping periods were restricted by researchers in two studies to examine the effects of sleep deprivation [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Eleven of the articles did not provide any sleep duration data [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58–61</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. When sleep durations were calculated, sleeping ~6 hrs/day was common in all three occupations [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Truck drivers, for example, slept 6.2 ± 0.1 [mean ± standard error] hrs/day before driving, and they did not increase their sleep significantly when off-duty [<xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Airline pilots had mean sleep durations &gt;7 hrs in three studies [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Pilots’ sleep durations were affected by their subsequent flight schedules [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. For example, early-morning take-offs were associated with shorter sleep durations in short-haul pilots (compared with their sleep duration before flights with later departure times) [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. On long-haul flights, pilots’ obtained more in-flight sleep when their flights departed later in the day (after 1800 hrs) compared with earlier departure times [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p>
                <p>The data from astronauts illustrated their difficulties with sleeping in space. Astronauts commonly used medications to sleep, such as zolpidem [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], zaleplon [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and melatonin [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] (the use of sleep-inducing medications was not examined in pilots or truck drivers). According to polysomnography recordings analyzed by Koller et al. [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] , astronauts had a significant reduction in daily total sleep time by 0.8 ± 0.3 hrs when they were in space, compared with their sleep on Earth. In other studies about astronauts, shorter sleep durations and poor sleep quality were associated [<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]; astronauts also rated the quality of their sleep in space poorly (compared with their sleep on Earth) [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Importantly, astronauts did not obtain &gt;6 hrs of sleep on the nights before the more dangerous aspects of their missions, such as extravehicular activities (EVA) [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
                <p>Koller et al. [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] hypothesized that microgravity may physiologically alter the structure of sleep in space. To test this hypothesis, four astronauts underwent polysomnography recordings. Koller et al. focused on two features of non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep: sleep spindles and slow-waves. Sleep spindles—bursts of oscillatory activity (9–15 Hz) lasting &lt;2 s—have been associated with memory processing, while slow-waves indicate the depth and quality of NREM sleep. Sleep spindles can be fast (12–15 Hz) or slow (9–12 Hz) and occur during stages 2 and 3 of NREM sleep. Compared with sleep on Earth, the astronauts’ sleep in space was characterized by lower slow-wave amplitude (decreased by 2.5 ± 0.7 µV in-flight versus pre-flight, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .01). They also demonstrated a higher fast spindle density (increased by 1.8 ± 0.5 spindles/min in-flight versus pre-flight, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) and a shift toward higher frequencies in the slow spindles (increased by 0.2 ± 0.03 Hz in-flight versus pre-flight, which returned to baseline when astronauts returned to Earth). The following parameters were examined but did not differ significantly in the space/Earth comparisons: the duration of sleep stages, wake after sleep onset (WASO), fast spindle amplitude, slow spindle density, and slow spindle band-power. Collectively, the findings indicated that the depth of sleep may be reduced in space, and Koller et al. [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] also suggested that the sleep spindle changes could impact the ability to learn new skills, such as adapting to weightlessness in space, although this study did not demonstrate that any specific cognitive tasks were correlated with sleep microstructural changes .</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s5">
                <title>Fatigue during work</title>
                <p>Five validated questionnaires were used to subjectively measure fatigue: the Karolinska Sleepiness Scale (KSS; scores range 0–9) [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49–51</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60–66</xref>], Stanford Sleepiness Scale (scores range 1–7) [<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], Epworth Sleepiness Scale (scores range 0–24) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], and Fatigue Severity Scale (scores range 9–63) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], and Samn-Perelli fatigue scale (scores range 0–7) [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47–49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60–62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Questionnaires were not administered at similar times across the 28 studies. For example, truck drivers’ fatigue questionnaires were completed three times a day [<xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] or at the beginning and end of their shifts [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Pilots’ fatigue levels were usually measured at Top of Descent (TOD, a safety-sensitive time during flight [~30 min before landing]) [<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47–49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], although pilots also completed questionnaires when they reached their cruising speed [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] or every morning and evening [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Maritime pilots did not complete any validated fatigue questionnaires, however, data about their work schedules were used to calculate ‘effectiveness’ scores that reflected their predicted levels of fatigue [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Astronauts’ questionnaires, including fatigue visual analogue scales (VAS), were typically administered immediately before or after they engaged in performance testing [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Some of the papers did not specify the exact times when subjects were asked to complete questionnaires or VAS ratings [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].</p>
                <p>Questionnaire data revealed that truck drivers’ fatigue was affected by their work and rest schedules [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Over 12-hrs of driving, for example, truck drivers’ KSS scores increased throughout their shift (4.1 ± 1.4 to 6.3 ± 1.5 [mean ± standard deviation]; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01) [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], and truck drivers’ on-duty KSS scores were lower after they had &gt;1 nighttime rest period (3.3 ± 0.1 [with only 1 nighttime rest period] versus 3.1 ± 0.1 [mean ± standard error], <italic toggle="yes">p =</italic> .03) [<xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. For astronauts, fatigue levels differed according to whether measures were obtained pre-flight, during spaceflight, or upon returning to Earth [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. When astronauts returned from the ISS, for example, their Stanford Sleepiness Scale scores were higher than their pre-flight scores (4.0 ± 1.6 versus 2.1 ± 0.6, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; .05) [<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Two studies about astronauts, however, did not find fatigue to vary significantly over time and with respect to mission timelines [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p>
                <p>The data from pilots illustrated how their fatigue levels were affected by numerous factors: rank/experience [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], in-flight nap opportunities [<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], flight durations (short-haul [≤3 hrs] or long-haul [&gt;6 hrs] flights) [<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], take-off and landing times [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], high workloads (e.g. multiple assignments/landings per day) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and the duration of time spent awake [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. A comparison of Captains and First Officers revealed that the more experienced pilots (Captains) reported lower Epworth Sleepiness Scale scores (7.7 ± 3.9 versus 9.7 ± 3.8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), and Fatigue Severity Scale scores were inversely correlated with pilots’ age (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.79, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. A qualitative analysis of pilots’ perspectives about their napping opportunities on long flights supported the conclusion that experience provided them with skills for combating fatigue and staying focused—experienced pilots explained how they learned to adapt to their work conditions over time, which allowed them to use their in-flight/pre-scheduled nap periods to effectively mitigate fatigue while their co-pilots were flying [<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Long-haul pilots reported higher levels of fatigue (Samn-Perelli scale) when they had landings in the late evening or night [<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and fatigue scores were higher (Samn-Perelli and KSS at TOD) when pilots were flying between 0200 and 0600 hrs [<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Two studies about short-haul pilots found that they did not experience significantly different Samn-Perelli scores at TOD depending on whether they flew earlier or later in the day [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], but pilots in another study had higher Samn-Perelli scale scores for early-morning versus late-morning flights (4.0 ± 0.9 versus 3.5 ± 0.8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Data from the KSS (at TOD) also showed that pilots were significantly sleepier for early-morning versus nighttime landings (compared with mid-day measures) [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>].</p>
                <p>In pilots, there were inconsistent results about the effects of prior sleep duration on KSS and Samn-Perelli fatigue scale sores—some investigators found that pilots’ prior sleep duration was significantly correlated with these fatigue measures [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] while others did not find significant associations between sleep duration and fatigue [<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. For example, Honn et al. [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] studied pilots who were using a flight simulator; when they had longer sleep before their simulated flights, their KSS and Samn-Perelli fatigue scores were significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001)—every additional hour of sleep reduced their KSS scores by 0.4 ± 0.1 units and Samn-Perelli scores by 0.5 ± 0.1 units. In addition, Gander et al. [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] found that for every additional hour that short-haul pilots had been awake, there were significant increases in Samn-Perelli and KSS scores (at TOD) by 0.1 and 0.2 points, respectively.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s6">
                <title>Schedules and circadian rhythms</title>
                <p>The reviewed studies involved many different types of work schedules. Unpredictable and irregular working hrs were particularly common in the transportation industry [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40–42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60–63</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Maritime pilots, for example, worked ‘on-call’ schedules that depended the movements of oil tankers, container ships, and cruise ships—these pilots’ start times and duty durations were highly-variable [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Long-haul pilots had pre-determined schedules; however, they crossed multiple time zones during their flights, which shifted their clocks by 5–12 hrs [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Commercial airline pilots often flew multiple flights within a single day, and they had to remain alert for daytime, evening, and nighttime take-offs and landings [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Truck drivers had different types of schedules [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In the United States, for example, truck drivers were required to take a 34-hr break after accumulating 60–70 hrs of weekly driving. Although this requirement was intended to allow for rest, it led truck drivers’ subsequent assignments to begin and end at different times [<xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. For Australian truck drivers who worked in the coal mining industry, however, the work schedules were more predictable because they were assigned to day- or night-shifts (lasting 12-hrs), but their schedules rotated weekly [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p>
                <p>The Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire (MEQ; scores range 16–86) was used in four studies, which found that airline pilots and astronauts did not have strong dispositions for being awake or asleep at specific times of the day [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. For example, the MEQ scores from astronauts [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], short-haul commercial pilots [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and military pilots [<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] indicated that they did not favor early or late sleeping and working times (e.g. MEQ scores of 52.9 ± 12.3 for astronauts, 51.4 ± 7.1 for commercial pilots, and 53.9 ± 8.2 for military pilots). The MEQ was not used in any of the studies about truck drivers [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In a stimulated space mission, MEQ scores were used to exclude subjects who reported definite preferences for morningness or eveningness (i.e. study participation required an MEQ score between 42 and 58 to avoid circadian preferences from confounding the study findings) [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p>
                <p>Circadian biomarkers (e.g. urinary 6-sulfatoxymelatonin levels and 24-hr temperature fluctuations) were analyzed in airline pilots and astronauts [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. For example, Arsintescu et al. [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] measured airline pilots’ urinary 6-sulfatoxymelatonin rhythms to understand how flight schedules affected their circadian rhythms. They estimated a baseline acrophase (indicating the circadian nadir in each pilot’s 6-sulfatoxymelatonin rhythm) as they flew for 5 consecutive days with mid-morning take-offs. Wide inter-individual circadian phase differences were found among the pilots during this baseline period—the urinary 6-sulfatoxymelatonin acrophases occurred between 0200 and 0630 hrs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 13). Then, after 3 to 4 days off, the pilots switched to a schedule requiring early-morning take-offs, which was associated with a phase advance in most of the pilots (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9); however, two pilots had a phase delay—the sample’s acrophases ranged between 0030 and 0450 hrs. When pilots’ schedules rotated (to begin with mid-day take-offs), the sample demonstrated a mean phase advance of 1.3 hrs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7 [phase advance]; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1 [phase delay]). When the pilots’ shifts began in the evening, however, the 6-sulfatoxymelatonin rhythm acrophases occurred between 0200 and 0630 hrs. Although this small sample size limited statistical comparisons, these findings illustrated how pilots were able to acclimate to their schedules [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In a study of astronauts, Flynn-Evans et al. [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] tested the hypothesis that space travel would cause a misalignment between the endogenous circadian temperature rhythm and astronauts’ sleep/wake schedules. The Circadian Performance Simulation Software was used to determine how astronauts’ temperatures aligned with their sleep/wake cycles (considering that body temperature rhythms should typically reach a nadir during sleep). A percentage of the astronauts’ temperature rhythms were not aligned with the timing of their sleep/wake periods 11 days before the mission (13%), in space (19%), and on the nights before conducting EVAs (29%). This temperature/sleep timing alignment was an important finding considering that astronauts with a circadian misalignment slept 0.5 fewer hrs and had VAS scores reflecting poorer subjective sleep quality (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ .01) compared with astronauts without the misalignment [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The temperature/sleep timing and alignment was not significantly associated with astronauts’ subjective reports of fatigue [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s7">
                <title>Variables affecting performance</title>
                <p>To objectively measure performance, subjects completed PVTs lasting 3-, 5-, or 10-min [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44–50</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61–63</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Researchers also analyzed performance-related data acquired from the following platforms: NASA Task Load Index (measured mental, physical, and emotional aspects of workload) [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], Reaction Self-Test (a computerized PVT-B that also acquires sleep/wake and workload data) [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], Cognition Test Battery (comprised of 10 neurobehavioral tests designed specifically for astronauts) [<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], Pilot Alertness Test [<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], and the Robotics On-Board Trainer (ROBoT; NASA’s platform for assessing abilities for docking and grappling maneuvers) [<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Trucks’ lane deviations and hard-breaking events (signs of inattention and near-collisions) were also analyzed to understand driver performance [<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and a group of ISS astronauts (and healthy control subjects) underwent computerized testing to compare their driving skills (e.g. manual dexterity, dual-tasking, and motion perception) [<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p>
                <p>Signs of degraded performance on the PVT (e.g. slower reaction time [RT], more lapses in attention, and premature responses) were associated with having higher workloads (e.g. higher NASA Task Load Index subscale scores) [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], early-morning start times [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], longer durations of wakefulness [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], shorter sleep before work [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and elevated fatigue scores (on the KSS, Samn-Perelli scale, or VAS) [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Short commercial airline flights (which posed a higher workload for pilots according to the NASA Task Load Index) and early-morning take-offs (that reduced pilots’ sleep duration) were associated poorer performance [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. For example, comparisons of pilots rotating through schedules with different take-off times revealed how flying earlier in the morning was associated with a slower mean RT and more lapses in attention (257 ± 70 ms [early-morning RT] versus 261 ± 62 ms [mid-day RT], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01; 4.4 ± 5.4 lapses [number &gt;500 ms; early-morning] versus 4.7 ± 5.1 lapses [mid-day], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01) [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In a flight simulator, pilots also demonstrated significantly more PVT lapses when they had to perform multiple take-offs and landings within a single day (as opposed to a single flight) [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The prior night’s sleep duration was associated with the number of PVT lapses and premature responses—each additional hour of sleep reduced the false start rate by 0.4 ± 0.1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In a study of pilots who were flying between the U.S. and Japan, the duration of wakefulness and previous 24-hrs of sleep predicted the slowest 10% RT (at TOD). Every hour of wakefulness increased this PVT metric by 0.05 responses/s, while every additional hour of sleep was associated with an improvement by 0.10 responses/s [<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p>
                <p>The data for truck drivers indicated that off-duty time and rest periods, but not necessarily sleep duration, affected performance. Having &gt;1 night to sleep between jobs was associated with significantly fewer lapses in attention on the PVT-B and fewer lane deviations while driving commercial trucks at night (despite no significant increase in their mean sleep duration during the off-duty period) [<xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. A bio-mathematical model determined by Mollicone et al. used truck drivers’ fatigue levels to predict hard-braking events. They determined that each lapse in the PVT increased the drivers’ risk of hard-braking events by 8%, which demonstrates how poorer PVT performance can indicate an elevated risk for accidents [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Healthy volunteers also demonstrated performance impairments when they underwent simulated astronaut missions with sleep-restriction and deprivation [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. When volunteers were sleep-deprived for 28 consecutive hrs before engaging in simulated spacecraft maneuvers, their PVT indicators worsened as they stayed awake (e.g. increase in lapses, slower RT) [<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In the Human Exploration Research Analog habitat, volunteers’ sleep was restricted to 5 hrs per day (for 5 consecutive nights, followed by 8 hrs of sleep for 2 nights), and their performance was significantly worse during the sleep-restriction period (e.g. slower RT). For astronauts, sleep durations &lt;6 hrs on the ISS were associated with a significantly slower mean RT on the PVT-B [<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], and ISS astronauts did not immediately return to their baseline level of performance post-mission. Astronauts required ~4 days post-mission to recover from deficits in motor functioning/perception as a result of space/microgravity (as determined by comparisons against healthy volunteers) [<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s8">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The present review synthesizes findings about sleep, fatigue, and performance in pilots, truck drivers, and astronauts—all three occupations require sustained periods of vigilance to prevent accidents, injuries, and deaths. Our scoping review found that sleep durations &lt;7 hrs (the recommended sleep duration) [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] were common, particularly for truck drivers, astronauts (before and during missions), and pilots with early-morning take-offs. The reviewed studies also demonstrated how longer sleep could significantly improve performance (likely translating into lower risks for errors, collisions, and accidents). Occupational schedules could cause circadian misalignment; therefore, sleep enhancement interventions, fatigue mitigation strategies, and the development of optimal work schedules will be important for pilots, truck drivers, and astronauts (key mechanisms are illustrated in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="F1">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Key mechanisms. Created with BioRender.com</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zpac033_fig1" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Upon recognizing how sleep significantly affects job performance, several governing bodies enforced regulations requiring specific break times for sleep in the trucking and aviation industries [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Despite the emphasis on breaks, however, the findings of present review illustrate how obtaining ≥7 hrs of sleep remains challenging. It is possible that occupational factors are impairing sleep, such as requirements for working rotating-shifts. Rotating schedules require periods of time when people must sleep during the day, but the schedules’ rotating start and end times make acclimation difficult. Sunlight, an important circadian rhythm regulator, affects neural responses in the anterior hypothalamus, which regulates the pineal gland’s melatonin production [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Melatonin levels typically begin rising when lights are dimmed, but shift-work alters the phase of melatonin rhythms. Consequently, shift-workers cannot always adapt their circadian rhythms to their work schedules, especially when schedules are unpredictable, which has been shown in police officers and nurses [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. These findings emphasize the importance of considering the timing of sleep periods, not only the duration of off-duty time, when designing legislation about workplace health and safety. Complex tasks, learning, memory consolidation, and emotional regulation require adequate sleep. Arsintescu et al. [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] described how pilots’ had higher workload complexities and demands with shorter flights—flight length and sleep duration were both negatively associated with the NASA Task Load Index sub-components, which measured effort, stress, and frustration. These findings illustrate the value of sleep for future endeavors related to workplace satisfaction, training, worker retention, and burnout prevention.</p>
              <p>Astronauts’ EVAs illustrate the highest-risk aspects of their work, considering the exposure to dangerous environmental conditions involving extreme cold and hypobaric hypoxia outside of the spacecraft [<xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Despite the dangers, the literature illustrated how astronauts have short sleep (~6 hrs), and they slept even less before EVAs. Considering how space-exploration endeavors are likely to increase in regularity in the future, it will be imperative to develop protocols for ensuring that astronauts can obtain adequate high-quality sleep in space, despite the potential issues caused by weightlessness, changes in atmospheric gases, and the stressors associated with confinement.</p>
              <p>Women comprise a minority within the aviation, trucking, and space-exploration workforces, and they were underrepresented in the reviewed studies (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Only one study specifically addressed the researchers’ attempts to balance the numbers of men and women in their study design [<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Considering that more women are likely to enter these occupations in the future, it will be important that studies are designed to have adequate statistical power for comparing sleep, fatigue, or performance measures by sex, especially considering previous reports of sex differences in circadian and homeostatic sleep-regulatory factors [<xref rid="CIT0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].</p>
              <p>In conclusion, future research and policy efforts should focus on developing strategies to increase sleep duration and mitigate fatigue, in addition to advancing knowledge about sleep microstructure and circadian rhythms and their effects on performance abilities. Incorporating the neurobehavioral discoveries from Dinges and colleagues’ [<xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] research programs into novel prediction models is important for prospectively determining the risks posed by various occupational activities (e.g. EVAs in space, ultra long-haul flights) according to sleep, circadian, genetic, and mission-related predictors to make well-informed decisions about performance and safety.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack id="a1">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>The authors acknowledge Kevin Grandfield, publications manager, Department of Biobehavioral Health Science, College of Nursing, University of Illinois Chicago.</p>
            </ack>
            <glossary>
              <def-list>
                <title>Abbreviations</title>
                <def-item>
                  <term>EEG</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>electroencephalogram</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>EVA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>extravehicular activity</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ISS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>International Space Station</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>KSS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>Karolinska Sleepiness Scale</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>MEQ</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>NASA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>PSQI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>Pittsburgh Sleep Quantity Index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>PVT</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>Psychomotor Vigilance Test</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>PVT-B</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>Brief Version of the Psychomotor Vigilance Test</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ROBoT</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>robotics on-board trainer</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>RT</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>reaction time</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>TOD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>top of descent</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>VAS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>Visual Analog Scale</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>WASO</term>
                  <def>
                    <p>wake after sleep onset</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <sec id="s9">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Dr. Maki is supported by intramural research funds from the National Institutes of Health, Clinical Center.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s10">
              <title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title>
              <p>Drs. Maki and Fink declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. Dr. Weaver declares the following conflicts of interest: Consultant/Advisory Boards: Bayer AG; Eli Lilly; Idorsia Alliance for Sleep, and Alkermes Orexin Advisory Board. Royalty fee for use FOSQ: Philips Respironics, Nyxoah, ResMed, ResMed Germany, Jazz Pharmaceuticals, Cook Medical, RWS; Verily Life Sciences; Stratevi; LivaNova; Valis Biosciences Inc.; Clinical Outcomes Solutions; Axsome; Eli Lilly; Signant Health; Signifier Medical Technologies; Harmony Biosciences; Alkermes; Syneos; Ignes Therapeutics; Takeda Development Center Americas Inc.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s11">
              <title>Author’s Note</title>
              <p>The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list id="r1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CIT0001">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Joint consensus statement of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and Sleep Research Society on the recommended amount of sleep for a healthy adult: Methodology and discussion</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1161</fpage>–<lpage>1183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4886</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26194576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0002">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The link between fatigue and safety</article-title>. <source>Accid Anal Prev.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2009.11.011</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21130213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0003">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Circadian adaptation of airline pilots during extended duration operations between the USA and Asia</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2013.790042</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23834703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0004">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gurubhagavatula</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Guiding principles for determining work shift duration and addressing the effects of work shift duration on performance, safety, and health: Guidance from the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and the Sleep Research Society</article-title>. <source>J Clin Sleep Med.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2283</fpage>–<lpage>2306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9512</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34666885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0005">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Psychological impact of shift work</article-title>. <source>Curr Sleep Med Rep.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29984133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0006">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Shift work: a perspective on shift work disorder-Is prevention the answer?</article-title><source>J Clin Sleep Med.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1863</fpage>–<lpage>1865</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8104</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31855173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0007">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Borbély</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Two process model of sleep regulation</article-title>. <source>Hum Neurobiol.</source><year>1982</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7185792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0008">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cordoza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep and alertness among interns in intensive care compared to general medicine rotations: a secondary analysis of the iCOMPARE trial</article-title>. <source>J Grad Med Educ.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4300/JGME-D-21-00045.1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34721802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0009">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rangan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Predictive and proactive fatigue risk management approaches in commercial aviation</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1479</fpage>–<lpage>1482</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2020.1803902</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32819179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0010">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Flight controller alertness and performance during spaceflight shiftwork operations</article-title>. <source>Hum Perf Extrem Environ.</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12190073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0011">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wingelaar-Jagt</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Fatigue in aviation: safety risks, preventive strategies and pharmacological interventions</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>712628</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2021.712628</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34552504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0012">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Controlled breaks as a fatigue countermeasure on the flight deck</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Environ Med.</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>654</fpage>–<lpage>664</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12137101</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0013">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Lost in space: sleep</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>860</fpage>–<lpage>862</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(14)70176-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25127233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0014">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moore-Ede</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Circadian alertness simulator for fatigue risk assessment in transportation: application to reduce frequency and severity of truck accidents</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Environ Med.</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>A107</fpage>–<lpage>A118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15018271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0015">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep, performance, circadian rhythms, and light-dark cycles during two space shuttle flights</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol.</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>R1647</fpage>–<lpage>R1664</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.2001.281.5.R1647</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0016">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gundel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The alteration of human sleep and circadian rhythms during spaceflight</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res.</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.1997.00028.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9125693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0017">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Alertness and psychomotor performance levels of marine pilots on an irregular work roster</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>784</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1466796</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29787295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0018">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Petrilli</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The sleep, subjective fatigue, and sustained attention of commercial airline pilots during an international pattern</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1357</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420520601085925</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0019">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A preliminary review of fatigue among rail staff</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>634</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00634</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0020">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Predicting risk in space: genetic markers for differential vulnerability to sleep restriction</article-title>. <source>Acta Astronaut.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actaastro.2012.04.002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524958</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0021">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleepiness and safety: where biology needs technology</article-title>. <source>Sleep Biol Rhythms.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sbr.12067</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24955033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0022">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Flight And Duty Limitations And Rest Requirements For Flightcrew Members.</collab><comment>14 CFR 117</comment>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.govinfo.gov/app/details/CFR-2014-title14-vol3/CFR-2014-title14-vol3-part117" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.govinfo.gov/app/details/CFR-2014-title14-vol3/CFR-2014-title14-vol3-part117</ext-link>. Accessed May 1, 2022.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0023">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dinges</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><source>Commercial Motor Vehicle (CMV) Driver Restart Study: Final Report FMCSA-RRR-15-011</source>. <publisher-name>Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0024">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>International Civil Aviation Organization.</collab><comment>Fatigue management guide for the airline operators</comment>. <year>2015</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.icao.int/safety/fatiguemanagement/FRMS%20Tools/FMG%20for%20Airline%20Operators%202nd%20Ed%20(final)%20EN.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.icao.int/safety/fatiguemanagement/FRMS%20Tools/FMG%20for%20Airline%20Operators%202nd%20Ed%20(final)%20EN.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed May 1, 2022.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0025">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Circadian rhythms, sleep deprivation, and human performance</article-title>. <source>Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-396971-2.00007-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23899598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0026">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chugh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Neurobehavioral consequences of arousals</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>S198</fpage>–<lpage>S201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/19.suppl_10.s198</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9085510</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0027">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Maximizing sensitivity of the psychomotor vigilance test (PVT) to sleep loss</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/34.5.581</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21532951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0028">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dorrian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Psychomotor vigilance performance: neurocognitive assay sensitive to sleep loss, sleep deprivation</article-title>. Boca Raton: CRC Press. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/9780203998007</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0029">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Validity and sensitivity of a brief psychomotor vigilance test (PVT-B) to total and partial sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source>Acta Astronaut.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actaastro.2011.07.015</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0030">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Response speed measurements on the psychomotor vigilance test: how precise is precise enough?</article-title><source>Sleep.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>zsaa121</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa121</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32556295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0031">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of the cognition test battery for spaceflight</article-title>. <source>Aerosp Med Hum Perform.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>942</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/AMHP.4343.2015</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26564759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0032">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>T. The cumulative cost of additional wakefulness: dose-response effects on neurobehavioral functions and sleep physiology from chronic sleep restriction and total sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.2.117</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12683469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0033">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The efficacy of a restart break for recycling with optimal performance depends critically on circadian timing</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>917</fpage>–<lpage>929</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/SLEEP.1128</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731142</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0034">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Neurocognitive consequences of sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source>Semin Neurol.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1237117</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19742409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0035">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The cognitive cost of sleep lost</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Learn Mem.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>582</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nlm.2011.07.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21875679</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0036">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep deprivation, vigilant attention, and brain function: a review</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-019-0432-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31176308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0037">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Scoping reviews: time for clarity in definition, methods, and reporting</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1291</fpage>–<lpage>1294</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.03.013</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25034198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0038">
                <label>38.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arksey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework</article-title>. <source>Int J Soc Res Methodol.</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1364557032000119616</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0039">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Commission Regulation.</collab><comment>EU no 83/2014 amending regulation (EU) no 965/2012</comment>. Technical requirements and administrative procedures related to air operations pursuant to regulation (EC) no 216/2008. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eurocockpit.be/sites/default/files/ftl_commission_regulation_83_2014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eurocockpit.be/sites/default/files/ftl_commission_regulation_83_2014.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed May 1, 2022.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0040">
                <label>40.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Alzehairi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep disorders among commercial airline pilots</article-title>. <source>Aerosp Med Hum Perform.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>944</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/amhp.5809.2021</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34986931</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0041">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arsintescu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The relationship between workload, performance and fatigue in a short-haul airline</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1492</fpage>–<lpage>1494</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2020.1804924</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32838580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0042">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arsintescu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Collecting sleep, circadian, fatigue, and performance data in complex operational environments</article-title>. <source>J Vis Exp.</source><year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0043">
                <label>43.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Barger</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of sleep deficiency and use of hypnotic drugs in astronauts before, during, and after spaceflight: an observational study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>912</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(14)70122-X</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25127232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0044">
                <label>44.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flynn-Evans</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Changes in performance and bio-mathematical model performance predictions during 45 days of sleep restriction in a simulated space mission</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>15594</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-71929-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32973159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0045">
                <label>45.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flynn-Evans</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep and neurobehavioral performance vary by work start time during non-traditional day shifts</article-title>. <source>Sleep Health.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>484</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2018.08.002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30241664</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0046">
                <label>46.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flynn-Evans</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Circadian misalignment affects sleep and medication use before and during spaceflight</article-title>. <source>Npj Microgravity.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>15019</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npjmgrav.2015.19</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28725719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0047">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Does the circadian clock drift when pilots fly multiple transpacific flights with 1- to 2-day layovers?</article-title><source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>982</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2016.1189430</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27253676</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0048">
                <label>48.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gander</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Effects of sleep/wake history and circadian phase on proposed pilot fatigue safety performance indicators</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12197</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25082509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0049">
                <label>49.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gander</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Pilot fatigue: relationships with departure and arrival times, flight duration, and direction</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Environ Med.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>840</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/ASEM.3963.2014</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25199126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0050">
                <label>50.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep, alertness and performance across a first and a second night shift in mining haul truck drivers</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>769</fpage>–<lpage>780</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2022.2034838</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35176952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0051">
                <label>51.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Flight crew alertness and sleep relative to timing of in-flight rest periods in long-haul flights</article-title>. <source>Aerosp Med Hum Perform.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/AMHP.5672.2021</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33468288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0052">
                <label>52.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of fatigue factors in maritime pilot work scheduling</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1495</fpage>–<lpage>1501</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2020.1817932</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32911999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0053">
                <label>53.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Honn</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Fatiguing effect of multiple take-offs and landings in regional airline operations</article-title>. <source>Accid Anal Prev.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2015.10.005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0054">
                <label>54.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep deficiency in spaceflight is associated with degraded neurobehavioral functions and elevated stress in astronauts on six-month missions aboard the international space station</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>zsac006</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac006</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35023565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0055">
                <label>55.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Altered sleep spindles and slow waves during space shuttle missions</article-title>. <source>Npj Microgravity.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41526-021-00177-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34795291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0056">
                <label>56.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollicone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Predicting performance and safety based on driver fatigue</article-title>. <source>Accid Anal Prev.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2018.03.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29622267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0057">
                <label>57.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Long-duration spaceflight adversely affects post-landing operator proficiency</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2677</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-39058-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30804413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0058">
                <label>58.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Aircrew fatigue perceptions, fatigue mitigation strategies, and circadian typology</article-title>. <source>Aerosp Med Hum Perform.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/AMHP.5396.2020</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32493560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0059">
                <label>59.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nasrini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Cognitive performance during confinement and sleep restriction in NASA’s human exploration research analog (HERA)</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>394</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2020.00394</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32411017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0060">
                <label>60.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Comparison of in-flight measures with predictions of a bio-mathematical fatigue model</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Environ Med.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1177</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/ASEM.3806.2014</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25479259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0061">
                <label>61.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sallinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>A large-scale European Union study of aircrew fatigue during long night and disruptive duties</article-title>. <source>Aerosp Med Hum Perform.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>635</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/amhp.5561.2020</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32693870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0062">
                <label>62.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sallinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep, alertness and alertness management among commercial airline pilots on short-haul and long-haul flights</article-title>. <source>Accid Anal Prev.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2016.10.029</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27816011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0063">
                <label>63.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Naturalistic field study of the restart break in US commercial motor vehicle drivers: truck driving, sleep, and fatigue</article-title>. <source>Accid Anal Prev.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2016.04.019</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27173360</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0064">
                <label>64.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Subjective measurements of in-flight sleep, circadian variation, and their relationship with fatigue</article-title>. <source>Aerosp Med Hum Perform.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3357/AMHP.4587.2016</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27662349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0065">
                <label>65.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vejvoda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Significance of time awake for predicting pilots’ fatigue on short-haul flights: Implications for flight duty time regulations</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12186</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25040665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0066">
                <label>66.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Performance on the robotics on-board trainer (ROBoT-r) spaceflight simulation during acute sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source>Front Neurosci.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>697</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2020.00697</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32792894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0067">
                <label>67.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zaslona</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Shared responsibility for managing fatigue: hearing the pilots</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0195530</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0195530</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29782533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0068">
                <label>68.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The central circadian timing system</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>747</fpage>–<lpage>751</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2013.04.004</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0069">
                <label>69.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Sleep strategies of night-shift nurses on days off: Which ones are most adaptive?</article-title><source>Front Neurol.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2014.00277</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25566182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0070">
                <label>70.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Resuehr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Shift work disrupts circadian regulation of the transcriptome in hospital nurses</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0748730419826694</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30712475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0071">
                <label>71.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The exercise and environmental physiology of extravehicular activity</article-title>. <source>Aviat Space Environ Med.</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11817621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0072">
                <label>72.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Katuntsev</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The main results of EVA medical support on the MIR space station</article-title>. <source>Acta Astronaut.</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0094-5765(03)00231-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14740657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0073">
                <label>73.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Predictors of interindividual differences in vulnerability to neurobehavioral consequences of chronic partial sleep restriction</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>zsab278</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab278</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34897501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0074">
                <label>74.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Optimization of biomathematical model predictions for cognitive performance impairment in individuals: accounting for unknown traits and uncertain states in homeostatic and circadian processes</article-title>. <source>Sleep.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.9.1129</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17910385</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
