<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-23T14:45:09Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9352751" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9352751</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-08-06</datestamp>
        <setSpec>sdata</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="data-paper" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Data</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Data</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Scientific Data</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2052-4463</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9352751</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9352751</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9352751</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35927555</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1565</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-022-01565-2</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Data Descriptor</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Near-real-time MODIS-derived vegetation index data products and online services for CONUS based on NASA LANCE</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Chen</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhengwei</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>zhengwei.yang@usda.gov</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Di</surname>
                    <given-names>Liping</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>ldi@gmu.edu</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>Eugene G.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Bei</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Han</surname>
                    <given-names>Weiguo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7753-2270</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>Li</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Guo</surname>
                    <given-names>Liying</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22448.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8032</institution-id><institution>Center for Spatial Information Science and Systems, </institution><institution>George Mason University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fairfax, VA 22030 USA </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22448.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8032</institution-id><institution>Department of Geography and Geoinformation Science, </institution><institution>George Mason University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fairfax, VA 22030 USA </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.483015.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0943 0531</institution-id><institution>Research and Development Division, U.S. Department of Agriculture National Agricultural Statistics Service, </institution></institution-wrap>Washington, DC 20250 USA </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>9</volume>
              <elocation-id>477</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>20</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <p id="Par1">This paper describes a set of Near-Real-Time (NRT) Vegetation Index (VI) data products for the Conterminous United States (CONUS) based on Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) data from Land, Atmosphere Near-real-time Capability for EOS (LANCE), an openly accessible NASA NRT Earth observation data repository. The data set offers a variety of commonly used VIs, including Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI), Vegetation Condition Index (VCI), Mean-referenced Vegetation Condition Index (MVCI), Ratio to Median Vegetation Condition Index (RMVCI), and Ratio to previous-year Vegetation Condition Index (RVCI). LANCE enables the NRT monitoring of U.S. cropland vegetation conditions within 24 hours of observation. With more than 20 years of observations, this continuous data set enables geospatial time series analysis and change detection in many research fields such as agricultural monitoring, natural resource conservation, environmental modeling, and Earth system science. The complete set of VI data products described in the paper is openly distributed via Web Map Service (WMS) and Web Coverage Service (WCS) as well as the VegScape web application (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/VegScape/">https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/VegScape/</ext-link>).</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="summary">
                <p id="Par2">
                  <table-wrap id="Taba">
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td>Measurement(s)</td>
                          <td>vegetation index</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td>Technology Type(s)</td>
                          <td>remote sensing</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject">
                <title>Subject terms</title>
                <kwd>Agriculture</kwd>
                <kwd>Geography</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100009174</institution-id>
                      <institution>United States Department of Agriculture | National Agricultural Statistics Service (USDA&amp;apos;s National Agricultural Statistics Service)</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>58-3AEU-7-0080</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Di</surname>
                      <given-names>Liping</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id>
                      <institution>National Science Foundation (NSF)</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>CNS-1739705</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Di</surname>
                      <given-names>Liping</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2022</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background &amp; Summary</title>
              <p id="Par3">The vegetation index (VI) is an effective indicator of vegetation photosynthetic activity and canopy structural variations in the study of geosciences and remote sensing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. A variety of VIs, including Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, Enhanced Vegetation Index (EVI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, Leaf Area Index (LAI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, have been derived from Earth observation data captured by different sensors. As one of the most widely used remote sensing data, Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) has been providing daily observation of global land surface from 2000 to the present. With the high spatial/temporal resolution and data continuity, the MODIS data products have been widely used in time series analysis and change detection studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Specifically, it is an ideal data source for deriving VI to measure crop conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The vegetation condition information derived from the MODIS data can provide timely decision support to vegetation phenology monitoring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, crop progress mapping<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, crop type classification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, crop yield estimation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, cropping patterns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, flood and drought detection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and other applications in agriculture.</p>
              <p id="Par4">Created from the surface reflectance bands, the MODIS VI Product (MOD13/MYD13)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> provides the Level-3 global mapping of NDVI and EVI with spatial resolution of 250 m, 500 m, and 1 km (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/data/dataprod/mod13.php">https://modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/data/dataprod/mod13.php</ext-link>). One limitation of MOD13/MYD13 is that these products are only generated at 16-day and monthly intervals, which cannot meet the timeliness requirement for many agricultural applications and decision-making, especially during disastrous events, such as storms and floods, wildfires, and droughts, occur. On the other hand, the standard, science-quality Terra/Aqua MODIS products are normally available after 20–48 hours of observation. This latency could also potentially affect the real-time observation of crop conditions. To reduce the latency of MODIS data, NASA has launched the Land, Atmosphere Near-real-time Capability for EOS (LANCE) program, which provides Level 0–3 near-real-time (NRT) Terra/Aqua MODIS data within less than 3 hours of observation. Based on the LANCE-MODIS, the daily 8-day rolling VI products at the spatial resolution of 250 m (MOD13Q4N) and 500 m (MOD13A4N) are also available. However, the current NASA MODIS VI products only have daily NDVI and EVI, which cannot reflect the vegetation condition within the historical time series. Therefore, an operational NRT VI data set with plentiful index types and temporal options to meet the timeliness needs of forecasting and monitoring crop conditions is desirable by the public.</p>
              <p id="Par5">This paper describes a set of NRT VI products and its associated online service for the Conterminous United States (CONUS) based on NASA’s LANCE-MODIS. Updated and published within 24 hours of observation, this data set aims to meet the timely needs for vegetation condition monitoring for U.S. cropland. Meanwhile, we have archived the complete volume of historical VI data back to 2000. This continuous data set with more than 20 years of vegetation condition observation would be suitable for time series analysis in many research fields such as agriculture, remote sensing, geographical information science and systems, environmental modeling, and Earth system sciences.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Workflow</title>
                <p id="Par6">The data set described in this paper covers five types of indices, Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI), Vegetation Condition Index (VCI), Mean-referenced Vegetation Condition Index (MVCI), Ratio to Median Vegetation Condition Index (RMVCI), and Ratio to previous-year Vegetation Condition Index (RVCI). Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the overall workflow for the production of all VI data products described in this paper. Based on the temporal resolution, our VI products can be grouped into the daily product (NDVI) and the weekly/biweekly products (NDVI/VCI/MVCI/RMVCI/RVCI). The main source of the daily NDVI is the LANCE-MODIS data. Other VI products are derived from the daily NDVI data. The rest of this section will describe the details of calculation and processing for NDVI, VCI, and MVCI/RMVCI/VCI data products.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Overall workflow for the production of NDVI, VCI, MVCI, RMVCI, and RVCI data products based on LANCE-MODIS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e419"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>NDVI</title>
                <p id="Par7">NDVI is the most widely used measurement to quantify vegetation conditions of remotely sensed imagery. The daily NDVI data described in this study are derived from the RED band and the NIR (near-infrared) band of MODIS data. It is noteworthy that the NRT daily NDVI data described in this study are produced based on the MODIS NRT Terra Surface Reflectance Daily Level-2G Global 250 m product (MOD09GQ NRT v061, dataset 10.5067/MODIS/MOD09GQ.NRT.061) within one day of observation. The archived daily NDVI from 2000 to 2019 and the derived weekly VI data are produced based on the MODIS Terra Surface Reflectance Daily Level-2G Global 250 m product (MOD09GQ v061, dataset 10.5067/MODIS/MOD09GQ.061). Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the information on surface reflectance bands for the MOD09GQ NRT product.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Surface reflectance bands for the MOD09GQ NRT product.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>HDF Layer</th><th>Data Type</th><th>Valid Range</th><th>Wavelength</th><th>Spatial Resolution</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Surface reflectance band 1</td><td>16-bit signed integer</td><td>−100 to 16000</td><td>620 to 670 nm</td><td>250 m</td><td>RED band</td></tr><tr><td>Surface reflectance band 2</td><td>16-bit signed integer</td><td>−100 to 16000</td><td>841 to 876 nm</td><td>250 m</td><td>NIR band</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par8">The first step of NRT VI calculation is to mosaic the daily MODIS images and clip the area to the CONUS. Then the NDVI is calculated using surface reflectance bands of the MODIS data, which is defined as:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$NDV{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)=\frac{NI{R}_{i}\left(x,y\right)-Re{d}_{i}\left(x,y\right)}{NI{R}_{i}\left(x,y\right)+Re{d}_{i}\left(x,y\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>NIR</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>Red</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> represent the surface reflectance value for the near-infrared band and red band of each pixel. Based on the above equation, the NDVI value ranges from −1 to 1. The common NDVI value range for vegetation is 0.2 to 0.8<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. The weekly and biweekly NDVI data are calculated by picking up the maximum daily raw NDVI in the 7-day/14-day period for every week/two-week using the maximum value composite (MVC) method. This is different from the rolling 8-day average method used in MODIS VI products (MOD13Q4N/MOD13A4N). The MVC method will keep the pixel of the maximum value from daily NDVI maps within a week or two weeks. This method can efficiently reduce the effect of bad pixels (e.g., cloud, fog, or no data) in a single daily NDVI.</p>
                <p id="Par9">To reduce the file size, we converted the NDVI data type from float to integer by scaling the index range from [−1, 1] to [0, 250], which can be defined as:<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$NDV{I}_{scaled}(x,y)=NDV{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)\times 125+125$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>125</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>125</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>VCI</title>
                <p id="Par10">VCI is a vegetation index derived from historical NDVI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. It indicates the percentage of the difference between the current NDVI value and historical minimum NDVI value with the NDVI dynamic range, which is defined as:<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$VC{I}_{i}(x,y)=\frac{NDV{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)-NDV{I}_{min}\left(x,y\right)}{NDV{I}_{max}\left(x,y\right)-NDV{I}_{min}\left(x,y\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where NDVI<sub>i</sub>(x,y) represents the current NDVI value for the given pixel, <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub>(<italic>x, y</italic>) and <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>min</italic></sub>(<italic>x, y</italic>) represent the maximum and minimum value of the historical NDVI time series for the given pixel.</p>
                <p id="Par11">Similar to NDVI data, the index range of VCI is rescaled from [0, 1] to [0, 250], which can be defined as:<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$VC{I}_{scaled}(x,y)=VC{I}_{i}(x,y)\times 250$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>250</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>MVCI/RMVCI/RVCI</title>
                <p id="Par12">MVCI and RMVCI are indices measuring the deviation of the current year’s NDVI value to the mean and median value of the historical NDVI from 2000 to the current year. The equations of MVCI and RMVCI are respectively defined as:<disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$MVC{I}_{i}(x,y)=\frac{NDV{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)-NDV{I}_{mean}\left(x,y\right)}{NDV{I}_{mean}\left(x,y\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Eque.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equf"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$RMVC{I}_{i}(x,y)=\frac{NDV{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)-NDV{I}_{median}\left(x,y\right)}{NDV{I}_{median}\left(x,y\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equf.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>
<italic>(x,y)</italic> represents the current NDVI value for the given pixel. <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>mean</italic></sub>
<italic>(x,y)</italic> and <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>median</italic></sub>
<italic>(x,y)</italic> represent the mean and median value of the historical NDVI within the same period for the given pixel.</p>
                <p id="Par13">RVCI, on the other hand, stands for the ratio of the current year’s NDVI to the previous years within the same periods. The equation is listed as:<disp-formula id="Equg"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$RVC{I}_{i}(x,y)=\frac{NDV{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)-NDV{I}_{i-1}\left(x,y\right)}{NDV{I}_{i-1}\left(x,y\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equg.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>
<italic>(x, y)</italic> represents the NDVI value of the current year and <italic>NDVI</italic><sub><italic>i-1</italic></sub>
<italic>(x, y)</italic> represents the NDVI value of the previous year.</p>
                <p id="Par14">To reduce the file size and remove the anomaly pixels, we limited the absolute value of the ratio to 125% and scaled the index range to [0, 250]. This conversion can be defined as:<disp-formula id="Equh"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$V{I}_{scaled}(x,y)=\left\{\begin{array}{cc}0 &amp; if\;V{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)\le -1.25\\ V{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)\times 100+125 &amp; if-1.25 &lt; V{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right) &lt; 1.25\\ 250 &amp; if\;V{I}_{i}\left(x,y\right)\ge 1.25\end{array}\right.$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16" display="block"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>125</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mn>250</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Article_Equh.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec7">
              <title>Data Records</title>
              <p id="Par15">The data set described in this paper includes the up-to-date NRT VI products and the historical VI data derived from the archived MODIS data since 2000. The complete data set is deposited at Center for Spatial Information Science and Systems of George Mason University. Our NRT VI products are grouped into daily, weekly, and bi-weekly products based on temporal period. The latest daily NDVI data is normally produced and published within 24 hours of observation. The weekly and biweekly VI data are produced once the daily NDVI data within the start date and end date of the week are completed. Each data set is registered and assigned the Digital Object Identifier (DOI) by the International Society of Agromatics and distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License. The records of all types of data products are summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of MODIS-derived NRT VI products.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Product</th><th align="left">Spatial Resolution</th><th align="left">Index Range</th><th align="left">Scaled Index Range</th><th align="left">No Data Value</th><th align="left">Data Volume</th><th align="left">DOI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>NDVI (Daily)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[−1, 1]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>365–366 files (~35GB)/year</td><td>10.55130/data.HYEZ6201<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>NDVI (Weekly/Biweekly)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[−1, 1]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>52–53 files (~5GB)/year</td><td>10.55130/data.OWHP6479<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Multi-year NDVI (Min/Max/Mean/Median)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[−1, 1]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>53 files (~5GB)</td><td>10.55130/data.SXBO9729<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>VCI (Weekly/Biweekly)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[0, 1]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>52–53 files (~7GB)/year</td><td>10.55130/data.XMAD9899<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>MVCI (Weekly/Biweekly)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[−1.25, 1.25]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>52–53 files (~3.5GB)/year</td><td>10.55130/data.MZXO5125<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>RMVCI (Weekly/Biweekly)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[−1.25, 1.25]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>52–53 files (~3.5GB)/year</td><td>10.55130/data.YDWF4243<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td>RVCI (Weekly/Biweekly)</td><td>250 m</td><td>[−1.25, 1.25]</td><td>[0, 250]</td><td>255</td><td>52–53 files (~4.0GB)/year</td><td>10.55130/data.CYIL3313<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par16">The data type of all VI products is 8-bit unsigned integer. The index of each data product has been scaled to the range from 0 to 250. The value of no data pixels is 255. There are 365/366 data files for the daily NDVI product as well as 52/53 data files for each weekly/biweekly VI product in a normal year. The multi-year NDVI products (mean/median/min/max) are dynamically updated with the production of new weekly/biweekly data while their file numbers are fixed (53 data files of each).</p>
              <p id="Par17">To make the data set findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable (FAIR), all VI data products are also available through standard geospatial web service interfaces, including Web Map Service (WMS) and Web Coverage Service (WCS). The WMS/WCS is implemented using MapServer, where the endpoint can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/cgi-bin/mapserv">https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/cgi-bin/mapserv</ext-link>. For example, the metadata of WMS capabilities for daily NDVI data of 2021 can be requested through <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/cgi-bin/mapserv?MAP=/WMS/NDVI-DAILY_2021.map&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.3.0&amp;REQUESTa=GetCapabilities">https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/cgi-bin/mapserv?MAP=/WMS/NDVI-DAILY_2021.map&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.3.0&amp;REQUEST=GetCapabilities</ext-link>. To access the specific data record, users may change the map name in the request example according to data type and year. The naming convention of the WMS/WCS map file for all data products described in this paper is summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Naming convention of MODIS-derived VI data products for WMS and WCS. (The YEAR option is the year from 2000 to 2021. The DATE/STARTDATE/ENDDATE option is the date in format of YYYY.MM.DD. The WEEK option is a two-digit week number from 01 to 53. The METHOD option for multi-year NDVI data can be one of MIN/MAX/MEAN/MEDIAN).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Product</th><th>Map File</th><th>Layer Name</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>NDVI (Daily)</td><td>NDVI-DAILY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., NDVI-DAILY_2021)</td><td>NDVI-DAILY_<italic>DATE</italic> (e.g., NDVI-DAILY_2021.01.01)</td></tr><tr><td>NDVI (Weekly)</td><td>NDVI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., NDVI-WEEKLY_2021)</td><td>NDVI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., NDVI-WEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.10)</td></tr><tr><td>NDVI (Biweekly)</td><td>NDVI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., NDVI-BIWEEKLY_2021)</td><td>NDVI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., NDVI-BIWEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.17)</td></tr><tr><td>Multi-year NDVI (Weekly)</td><td>NDVI-MULTIYEAR-WEEKLY</td><td>NDVI-MULTIYEAR-WEEKLY_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>METHOD</italic> (e.g., NDVI-MULTIYEAR-WEEKLY_01_MEAN)</td></tr><tr><td>Multi-year NDVI (Biweekly)</td><td>NDVI-MULTIYEAR-BIWEEKLY</td><td>NDVI-MULTIYEAR-BIWEEKLY_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>METHOD</italic> (e.g., NDVI-MULTIYEAR-WEEKLY_01_MEAN)</td></tr><tr><td>VCI (Weekly)</td><td>VCI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., VCI-WEEKLY_2021)</td><td>VCI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., VCI-WEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.10)</td></tr><tr><td>VCI (Biweekly)</td><td>VCI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., VCI-BIWEEKLY_2021)</td><td>VCI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., VCI-BIWEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.17)</td></tr><tr><td>MVCI (Weekly)</td><td>MVCI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., MVCI-WEEKLY_2021)</td><td>MVCI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., MVCI-WEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.10)</td></tr><tr><td>MVCI (Biweekly)</td><td>MVCI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., MVCI-BIWEEKLY_2021)</td><td>MVCI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., MVCI-BIWEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.17)</td></tr><tr><td>RVCI (Weekly)</td><td>RNDVI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., RNDVI-WEEKLY_2021)</td><td>RNDVI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., RNDVI-WEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.10)</td></tr><tr><td>RVCI (Biweekly)</td><td>RNDVI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., RNDVI-BIWEEKLY_2021)</td><td>RNDVI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., RNDVI-BIWEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.17)</td></tr><tr><td>RMVCI (Weekly)</td><td>RMNDVI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., RMNDVI-WEEKLY_2021)</td><td>RMNDVI-WEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., RMNDVI-WEEKLY_2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.10)</td></tr><tr><td>RMVCI (Biweekly)</td><td>RMNDVI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic> (e.g., RMNDVI-BIWEEKLY_2021)</td><td>RMNDVI-BIWEEKLY_<italic>YEAR</italic>_<italic>WEEK</italic>_<italic>STARTDATE</italic>_<italic>ENDDATE</italic> (e.g., RMNDVI-BIWEEKLY _2021_01_2021.01.04_2021.01.17)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8">
              <title>Technical Validation</title>
              <p id="Par18">The sample datasets demonstrated in this data descriptor, including daily NDVI data from 6/7/2021 to 6/13/2021, and weekly/biweekly NDVI, VCI, MVCI, RMVCI, RVCI data for week 23 in 2021, are available on Figshare at 10.6084/m9.figshare.15130857.v5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> illustrates the validation of the NDVI data product. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> shows the categorical maps for daily NDVI data from 6/7/21 to 6/13/21 as well as the weekly NDVI data composited by daily NDVI data. The index value of the NDVI categorical map ranges from 0 to 1. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> shows histograms of category distribution for all daily and weekly maps. The mapping and quantitative results suggest the weekly NDVI map reflects the maximum value (the greenest pixels) in a week over the CONUS.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Example of daily and weekly NDVI data for CONUS. The index value of the NDVI categorical map ranges from 0 to 1 (values less than 0 are categorized as 0 to 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e2141"/></fig></p>
              <p id="Par19">The other weekly VI data products are calculated based on the weekly NDVI data products. As introduced in the method section, the VCI index is derived from the current week’s NDVI and the dynamic NDVI range for the same period in history. Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows an example of VCI data derived from the NDVI data for week 23 in 2021 (6/7/21 to 6/13/21). The current week’s VCI, the current week’s NDVI, and the multi-year minimum/maximum NDVI composited from the historical NDVI for the same period are demonstrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>. In the figure, the Delta Region, which mainly covers southeastern Arkansas, western Mississippi, and northeastern Louisiana, is selected as the area of interest (AOI) to demonstrate the detailed crop condition. In the detailed map, the cropland within the AOI is highlighted by the Crop Mask Layer derived from the 2017–2021 Cropland Data Layer (CDL) of USDA NASS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The pink pixels suggest the cropland is suffering from severe vegetative drought stress, while the blue pixels indicate the cropland is in good vegetation state conditions. To further validate the VCI result, the NDVI profiles of two anomaly points are compared in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>. Profile A indicates the vegetation condition of 2021 for the corresponding crop field is under the severe drought stress (NDVI &lt; 0.2) in history. On the contrary, profile B shows the corresponding crop field had a good vegetation condition (NDVI &gt; 0.9) in 2021.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Example of weekly VCI data. The index value of the NDVI and VCI categorical map ranges from 0 to 1 (values less than 0 are categorized as 0 to 0.05). The cropland within the AOI is highlighted by the Crop Mask Layer derived from the 2017–2021 CDL data of USDA NASS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Fig3_HTML" id="d32e2165"/></fig></p>
              <p id="Par20">The MVCI, RMVCI, and RVCI are the ratios of the current week’s NDVI to the multi-year mean NDVI, multi-year median NDVI, and the previous year’s NDVI for the same period, respectively. Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> compares the categorical map of MVCI, RMVCI, and RVCI with their referenced NDVI data. In the MVCI, RMVCI, and RVCI map, the red pixels suggest the cropland has a more severe vegetative drought stress condition than the referenced data. In contrast, the green pixels indicate the cropland has better vegetation conditions than the referenced data. Meanwhile, the absolute values of these indices indicate the anomaly of the current week NDVI.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Example of weekly MVCI, RMVCI, and RVCI data. The index value of the NDVI categorical map ranges from 0 to 1 (values less than 0 are categorized as 0 to 0.05). The index value of the MVCI/RMVCI/RVCI categorical map ranges from −100% to 100% (values less than −100% are categorized as −100% to −25%, and values greater than 100% are categorized as 25% to 100%). The cropland within the AOI is highlighted by the Crop Mask Layer derived from the 2017–2021 CDL data of USDA NASS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Fig4_HTML" id="d32e2179"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9">
              <title>Usage Notes</title>
              <p id="Par21">The VI data products described in this paper can be directly used in WMS/WCS compliant Geographic Information System (GIS) web applications and software. The complete VI data products are available on VegScape (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/VegScape/">https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/VegScape/</ext-link>), a web-based online service operated and maintained by the Center for Spatial Information Science and Systems of George Mason University. This web client delivers a suite of FAIR geoprocessing and map services to explore and analyze U.S. crop condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. In addition, all data records summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> are interoperable with desktop GIS software, such as ArcGIS and QGIS. Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> demonstrates the FAIR capability of the VI data products through VegScape and ArcGIS Pro.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>FAIR capability of VI data products with online service and desktop GIS software. The VegScape web application can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/VegScape/">https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/VegScape/</ext-link>. The GetCapabilities request of WMS layers demonstrated in ArcGIS Pro is available on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/cgi-bin/mapserv?MAP=/WMS/NDVI-WEEKLY_2021.map&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.3.0&amp;REQUEST=GetCapabilities">https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/cgi-bin/mapserv?MAP=/WMS/NDVI-WEEKLY_2021.map&amp;SERVICE=WMS&amp;VERSION=1.3.0&amp;REQUEST=GetCapabilities</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41597_2022_1565_Fig5_HTML" id="d32e2221"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>This work is supported in parts by grants from the U.S. Department of Agriculture National Agricultural Statistics Service (Grant #: 58-3AEU-7-0080) and the National Science Foundation (CNS-1739705).</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>Chen Zhang: Formal analysis, Data curation, Software, Writing - original draft; Zhengwei Yang: Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Supervision, Methodology, Writing - review and editing; Liping Di: Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing - review &amp; editing; Eugene G. Yu: Investigation, Software; Bei Zhang: Software; Weiguo Han: Software; Li Lin: Investigation, Validation; Liying Guo: Investigation, Review.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Code availability</title>
              <p>Code, documentation, and other related sources used to produce VI data described in this work are available on GitHub at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/CSISS/NRT_VI">https://github.com/CSISS/NRT_VI</ext-link>. The usage and examples of requesting VI data through WMS/WCS are available on the Developer Guide page of VegScape at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/VegScape/devhelp/help.html">https://nassgeo.csiss.gmu.edu/VegScape/devhelp/help.html</ext-link>.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p id="Par22">The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huete</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Overview of the radiometric and biophysical performance of the MODIS vegetation indices</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>83</volume>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <lpage>213</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0034-4257(02)00096-2</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tucker</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Red and photographic infrared linear combinations for monitoring vegetation</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>1979</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <lpage>150</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0034-4257(79)90013-0</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huete</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A soil-adjusted vegetation index (SAVI)</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <lpage>309</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0034-4257(88)90106-X</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jiang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huete</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Didan</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miura</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Development of a two-band enhanced vegetation index without a blue band</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>112</volume>
                  <fpage>3833</fpage>
                  <lpage>3845</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rse.2008.06.006</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Price</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating leaf area index from satellite data</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>727</fpage>
                  <lpage>734</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/36.225538</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asner</surname>
                      <given-names>GP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scurlock</surname>
                      <given-names>JMO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hicke</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global synthesis of leaf area index observations: implications for ecological and remote sensing studies</article-title>
                  <source>Global Ecology and Biogeography</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <lpage>205</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1466-822X.2003.00026.x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Justice</surname>
                      <given-names>CO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS): land remote sensing for global change research</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <fpage>1228</fpage>
                  <lpage>1249</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/36.701075</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huete, A., Didan, K., van Leeuwen, W., Miura, T. &amp; Glenn, E. MODIS Vegetation Indices. In <italic>Land Remote Sensing and Global Environmental Change: NASA’s Earth Observing System and the Science of ASTER and MODIS</italic> (eds. Ramachandran, B., Justice, C. O. &amp; Abrams, M. J.) 579–602 (Springer, 2011).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Monitoring vegetation phenology using MODIS</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>84</volume>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
                  <lpage>475</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0034-4257(02)00135-9</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Toward mapping crop progress at field scales through fusion of Landsat and MODIS imagery</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>188</volume>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <lpage>25</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rse.2016.11.004</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wardlow</surname>
                      <given-names>BD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egbert</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Large-area crop mapping using time-series MODIS 250 m NDVI data: An assessment for the U.S. Central Great Plains</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>112</volume>
                  <fpage>1096</fpage>
                  <lpage>1116</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rse.2007.07.019</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hao</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Niu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shakir</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Feature Selection of Time Series MODIS Data for Early Crop Classification Using Random Forest: A Case Study in Kansas, USA</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>5347</fpage>
                  <lpage>5369</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs70505347</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An assessment of pre- and within-season remotely sensed variables for forecasting corn and soybean yields in the United States</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>141</volume>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <lpage>128</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rse.2013.10.027</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taff</surname>
                      <given-names>GN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An analysis of cropland mask choice and ancillary data for annual corn yield forecasting using MODIS data</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <lpage>87</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jag.2014.12.017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shrestha</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Regression model to estimate flood impact on corn yield using MODIS NDVI and USDA cropland data layer</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Integrative Agriculture</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>398</fpage>
                  <lpage>407</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2095-3119(16)61502-2</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Medina</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abebe</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>On optimizing a MODIS-based framework for in-season corn yield forecast</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>95</volume>
                  <fpage>102258</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jag.2020.102258</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mapping croplands, cropping patterns, and crop types using MODIS time-series data</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <lpage>147</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jag.2018.03.005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Improvement and Validation of NASA/MODIS NRT Global Flood Mapping</article-title>
                  <source>Remote Sensing</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs11020205</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xie</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Deriving drought indices from MODIS vegetation indices (NDVI/EVI) and Land Surface Temperature (LST): Is data reconstruction necessary?</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>101</volume>
                  <fpage>102352</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jag.2021.102352</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huete, A., Justice, C. &amp; van Leeuwen, W. MODIS Vegetation Index (MOD13): Algorithm Theoretical Basis Document (1999).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sabins, F. F. &amp; Ellis, J. M. <italic>Remote Sensing: Principles, Interpretation, and Applications</italic>, <italic>Fourth Edition</italic>. (Waveland Press, 2020).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kogan</surname>
                      <given-names>FN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Application of vegetation index and brightness temperature for drought detection</article-title>
                  <source>Advances in Space Research</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <lpage>100</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0273-1177(95)00079-T</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11539265</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Near-real-time MODIS-derived vegetation index data products for CONUS (sample data)</data-title>
                  <source>Figshare</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6084/m9.figshare.15130857.v5</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boryan</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mueller</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Craig</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Monitoring US agriculture: the US Department of Agriculture, National Agricultural Statistics Service, Cropland Data Layer Program</article-title>
                  <source>Geocarto International</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <lpage>358</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10106049.2011.562309</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <data-title>Web service-based vegetation condition monitoring system - VegScape</data-title>
                  <source>IEEE</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/IGARSS.2013.6723618</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang, C. <italic>et al</italic>. An Overview of Agriculture Cyberinformatics Tools to Support USDA NASS Decision Making. In <italic>2021 9th International Conference on Agro-Geoinformatics</italic>10.1109/Agro-Geoinformatics50104.2021.9530327 (2021).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Daily NDVI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.HYEZ6201</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Weekly NDVI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.OWHP6479</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Weekly Multiyear NDVI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.SXBO9729</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Weekly VCI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.XMAD9899</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Weekly MVCI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.MZXO5125</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Weekly RMVCI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.YDWF4243</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="data">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <data-title>Weekly RVCI for CONUS</data-title>
                  <source>International Society of Agromatics</source>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55130/data.CYIL3313</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
